<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- Search-Engine-Total-Number-Of-Results: 135 -->
<xml>
<records>
<record>
  <contributors>
    <authors>
      <author>Burrage, Clare</author>
      <author>Sakstein, Jeremy</author>
    </authors>
  </contributors>
  <titles>
    <title>Tests of Chameleon Gravity</title>
    <secondary-title>Living Rev.Rel.</secondary-title>
  </titles>
  <electronic-resource-num>10.1007/s41114-018-0011-x</electronic-resource-num>
  <pages>1</pages>
  <volume>21</volume>
  <number>1</number>
  <keywords>
    <keyword>Scalar-tensor theories</keyword>
    <keyword>Modified gravity</keyword>
    <keyword>Tests of gravity</keyword>
  </keywords>
  <dates>
    <year>2018</year>
    <pub-dates>
      <date>2018-03-16</date>
    </pub-dates>
  </dates>
  <abstract>Theories of modified gravity where light scalars with non-trivial self-interactions and non-minimal couplings to matter-chameleon and symmetron theories-dynamically suppress deviations from general relativity in the solar system. On other scales, the environmental nature of the screening means that such scalars may be relevant. The highly-nonlinear nature of screening mechanisms means that they evade classical fifth-force searches, and there has been an intense effort towards designing new and novel tests to probe them, both in the laboratory and using astrophysical objects, and by reinterpreting existing datasets. The results of these searches are often presented using different parametrizations, which can make it difficult to compare constraints coming from different probes. The purpose of this review is to summarize the present state-of-the-art searches for screened scalars coupled to matter, and to translate the current bounds into a single parametrization to survey the state of the models. Presently, commonly studied chameleon models are well-constrained but less commonly studied models have large regions of parameter space that are still viable. Symmetron models are constrained well by astrophysical and laboratory tests, but there is a desert separating the two scales where the model is unconstrained. The coupling of chameleons to photons is tightly constrained but the symmetron coupling has yet to be explored. We also summarize the current bounds on $f(R)$ models that exhibit the chameleon mechanism (Hu \&amp; Sawicki models). The simplest of these are well constrained by astrophysical probes, but there are currently few reported bounds for theories with higher powers of $R$. The review ends by discussing the future prospects for constraining screened modified gravity models further using upcoming and planned experiments.</abstract>
</record>

<record>
  <contributors>
    <authors>
      <author>Winicour, Jeffrey</author>
    </authors>
  </contributors>
  <titles>
    <title>Characteristic Evolution and Matching</title>
    <secondary-title>Living Rev.Rel.</secondary-title>
  </titles>
  <electronic-resource-num>10.12942/lrr-2012-2</electronic-resource-num>
  <pages>2</pages>
  <volume>15</volume>
  <number>1</number>
  <dates>
    <year>2012</year>
    <pub-dates>
      <date>2012-01-25</date>
    </pub-dates>
  </dates>
  <abstract>characteristic initial-value problem. Progress in characteristic evolution is traced from the early stage of 1D feasibility studies to 2D-axisymmetric codes that accurately simulate the oscillations and gravitational collapse of relativistic stars and to current 3D codes that provide pieces of a binary black-hole spacetime. Cauchy codes have now been successful at simulating all aspects of the binary black-hole problem inside an artificially constructed outer boundary. A prime application of characteristic evolution is to extend such simulations to null infinity where the waveform from the binary inspiral and merger can be unambiguously computed. This has now been accomplished by Cauchy-characteristic extraction, where data for the characteristic evolution is supplied by Cauchy data on an extraction worldtube inside the artificial outer boundary. The ultimate application of characteristic evolution is to eliminate the role of this outer boundary by constructing a global solution via Cauchy-characteristic matching. Progress in this direction is discussed.</abstract>
</record>

<record>
  <contributors>
    <authors>
      <author>Frolov, Valeri</author>
      <author>Krtous, Pavel</author>
      <author>Kubiznak, David</author>
    </authors>
  </contributors>
  <titles>
    <title>Black holes, hidden symmetries, and complete integrability</title>
    <secondary-title>Living Rev.Rel.</secondary-title>
  </titles>
  <electronic-resource-num>10.1007/s41114-017-0009-9</electronic-resource-num>
  <pages>6</pages>
  <volume>20</volume>
  <number>1</number>
  <keywords>
    <keyword>General relativity</keyword>
    <keyword>Higher dimensions</keyword>
    <keyword>Black holes</keyword>
    <keyword>Kerr–NUT–(A)dS</keyword>
    <keyword>Hidden symmetries</keyword>
    <keyword>Principal tensor</keyword>
    <keyword>Complete integrability</keyword>
    <keyword>Separability</keyword>
  </keywords>
  <dates>
    <year>2017</year>
    <pub-dates>
      <date>2017-11-22</date>
    </pub-dates>
  </dates>
  <abstract>The study of higher-dimensional black holes is a subject which has recently attracted a vast interest. Perhaps one of the most surprising discoveries is a realization that the properties of higher-dimensional black holes with the spherical horizon topology and described by the Kerr-NUT-(A)dS metrics are very similar to the properties of the well known four-dimensional Kerr metric. This remarkable result stems from the existence of a single object called the principal tensor. In our review we discuss explicit and hidden symmetries of higher-dimensional black holes. We start with the overview of the Liouville theory of completely integrable systems and introduce Killing and Killing-Yano objects representing explicit and hidden symmetries. We demonstrate that the principal tensor can be used as a `seed object' which generates all these symmetries. It determines the form of the black hole geometry, as well as guarantees its remarkable properties, such as special algebraic type of the spacetime, complete integrability of geodesic motion, and separability of the Hamilton-Jacobi, Klein-Gordon, and Dirac equations. The review also contains a discussion of different applications of the developed formalism and its possible generalizations.</abstract>
</record>

<record>
  <contributors>
    <authors>
      <author>Winicour, Jeffrey</author>
    </authors>
  </contributors>
  <titles>
    <title>Characteristic Evolution and Matching</title>
    <secondary-title>Living Rev.Rel.</secondary-title>
  </titles>
  <electronic-resource-num>10.12942/lrr-2009-3</electronic-resource-num>
  <pages>3</pages>
  <volume>12</volume>
  <number/>
  <dates>
    <year>2009</year>
  </dates>
  <abstract>I review the development of numerical evolution codes for general relativity based upon the characteristic initial value problem. Progress in characteristic evolution is traced from the early stage of 1D feasibility studies to 2D axisymmetric codes that accurately simulate the oscillations and gravitational collapse of relativistic stars and to current 3D codes that provide pieces of a binary black hole spacetime. Cauchy codes have now been successful at simulating all aspects of the binary black hole problem inside an artificially constructed outer boundary. A prime application of characteristic evolution is to extend such simulations to null infinity where the waveform from the binary inspiral and merger can be unambiguously computed. This has now been accomplished by Cauchy-characteristic extraction, where data for the characteristic evolution is supplied by Cauchy data on an extraction worldtube inside the artificial outer boundary. The ultimate application of characteristic evolution is to eliminate the role of this outer boundary by constructing a global solution via Cauchy-characteristic matching. Progress in this direction is discussed.</abstract>
</record>

<record>
  <contributors>
    <authors>
      <author>Paschalidis, Vasileios</author>
      <author>Stergioulas, Nikolaos</author>
    </authors>
  </contributors>
  <titles>
    <title>Rotating Stars in Relativity</title>
    <secondary-title>Living Rev.Rel.</secondary-title>
  </titles>
  <electronic-resource-num>10.1007/s41114-017-0008-x</electronic-resource-num>
  <pages>7</pages>
  <volume>20</volume>
  <number>1</number>
  <keywords>
    <keyword>Relativistic stars</keyword>
    <keyword>Rotation</keyword>
    <keyword>Stability</keyword>
    <keyword>Oscillations</keyword>
    <keyword>Magnetic fields</keyword>
    <keyword>Numerical relativity</keyword>
  </keywords>
  <dates>
    <year>2017</year>
    <pub-dates>
      <date>2017-11-29</date>
    </pub-dates>
  </dates>
  <abstract>Rotating relativistic stars have been studied extensively in recent years, both theoretically and observationally, because of the information they might yield about the equation of state of matter at extremely high densities and because they are considered to be promising sources of gravitational waves. The latest theoretical understanding of rotating stars in relativity is reviewed in this updated article. The sections on equilibrium properties and on nonaxisymmetric oscillations and instabilities in $f$-modes and $r$-modes have been updated. Several new sections have been added on equilibria in modified theories of gravity, approximate universal relationships, the one-arm spiral instability, on analytic solutions for the exterior spacetime, rotating stars in LMXBs, rotating strange stars, and on rotating stars in numerical relativity including both hydrodynamic and magnetohydrodynamic studies of these objects.</abstract>
</record>

<record>
  <contributors>
    <authors>
      <author>Winicour, Jeffrey</author>
    </authors>
  </contributors>
  <titles>
    <title>Characteristic Evolution and Matching</title>
    <secondary-title>Living Rev.Rel.</secondary-title>
  </titles>
  <electronic-resource-num>10.12942/lrr-2005-10</electronic-resource-num>
  <pages>10</pages>
  <volume>8</volume>
  <number/>
  <dates>
    <year>2005</year>
  </dates>
  <abstract>I review the development of numerical evolution codes for general relativity based upon the characteristic initial value problem. Progress is traced from the early stage of 1D feasibility studies to 2D axisymmetric codes that accurately simulate the oscillations and gravitational collapse of relativistic stars and to current 3D codes that provide pieces of a binary black spacetime. A prime application of characteristic evolution is to compute waveforms via Cauchy-characteristic matching, which is also reviewed.</abstract>
</record>

<record>
  <contributors>
    <authors>
      <author>Metzger, Brian D.</author>
    </authors>
  </contributors>
  <titles>
    <title>Kilonovae</title>
    <secondary-title>Living Rev.Rel.</secondary-title>
  </titles>
  <electronic-resource-num>10.1007/s41114-017-0006-z</electronic-resource-num>
  <pages>3</pages>
  <volume>20</volume>
  <number>1</number>
  <keywords>
    <keyword>Gravitational waves</keyword>
    <keyword>Neutron stars</keyword>
    <keyword>Nucleosynthesis</keyword>
    <keyword>Black holes</keyword>
    <keyword>Radiative transfer</keyword>
  </keywords>
  <dates>
    <year>2017</year>
    <pub-dates>
      <date>2017-05-16</date>
    </pub-dates>
  </dates>
  <abstract>The mergers of double neutron star (NS-NS) and black hole (BH)-NS binaries are promising gravitational wave (GW) sources for Advanced LIGO and future GW detectors. The neutron-rich ejecta from such merger events undergoes rapid neutron capture (r-process) nucleosynthesis, enriching our Galaxy with rare heavy elements like gold and platinum. The radioactive decay of these unstable nuclei also powers a rapidly evolving, supernova-like transient known as a "kilonova". Kilonovae provide an approximately isotropic electromagnetic counterpart to the GW signal, which also provides a unique and direct probe of an important, if not dominant, r-process site. This handbook reviews the history and physics of kilonovae, leading to the current paradigm of week-long emission with a spectral peak at near-infrared wavelengths. Using a simple light curve model to illustrate the basic physics, I introduce potentially important variations on this canonical picture, including: ~day-long optical ("blue") emission from lanthanide-free components of the ejecta; ~hours-long precursor UV/blue emission, powered by the decay of free neutrons in the outermost ejecta layers; and enhanced emission due to energy input from a long-lived central engine, such as an accreting BH or millisecond magnetar. I assess the prospects of detecting kilonovae following future GW detections of NS-NS/BH-NS mergers in light of the recent follow-up campaign of the LIGO binary BH-BH mergers.</abstract>
</record>

<record>
  <contributors>
    <authors>
      <author>Romano, Joseph D.</author>
      <author>Cornish, Neil J.</author>
    </authors>
  </contributors>
  <titles>
    <title>Detection methods for stochastic gravitational-wave backgrounds: a unified treatment</title>
    <secondary-title>Living Rev.Rel.</secondary-title>
  </titles>
  <electronic-resource-num>10.1007/s41114-017-0004-1</electronic-resource-num>
  <pages>2</pages>
  <volume>20</volume>
  <number>1</number>
  <keywords>
    <keyword>Gravitational waves</keyword>
    <keyword>Data analysis</keyword>
    <keyword>Stochastic backgrounds</keyword>
  </keywords>
  <dates>
    <year>2017</year>
    <pub-dates>
      <date>2017-04-04</date>
    </pub-dates>
  </dates>
  <abstract>We review detection methods that are currently in use or have been proposed to search for a stochastic background of gravitational radiation. We consider both Bayesian and frequentist searches using ground-based and space-based laser interferometers, spacecraft Doppler tracking, and pulsar timing arrays; and we allow for anisotropy, non-Gaussianity, and non-standard polarization states. Our focus is on relevant data analysis issues, and not on the particular astrophysical or early Universe sources that might give rise to such backgrounds. We provide a unified treatment of these searches at the level of detector response functions, detection sensitivity curves, and, more generally, at the level of the likelihood function, since the choice of signal and noise models and prior probability distributions are actually what define the search. Pedagogical examples are given whenever possible to compare and contrast different approaches. We have tried to make the article as self-contained and comprehensive as possible, targeting graduate students and new researchers looking to enter this field.</abstract>
</record>

<record>
  <contributors>
    <authors>
      <author>Bishop, Nigel T.</author>
      <author>Rezzolla, Luciano</author>
    </authors>
  </contributors>
  <titles>
    <title>Extraction of Gravitational Waves in Numerical Relativity</title>
    <secondary-title>Living Rev.Rel.</secondary-title>
  </titles>
  <electronic-resource-num>10.1007/s41114-016-0001-9</electronic-resource-num>
  <pages>2</pages>
  <volume>19</volume>
  <number/>
  <dates>
    <year>2016</year>
  </dates>
  <abstract>A numerical-relativity calculation yields in general a solution of the Einstein equations including also a radiative part, which is in practice computed in a region of finite extent. Since gravitational radiation is properly defined only at null infinity and in an appropriate coordinate system, the accurate estimation of the emitted gravitational waves represents an old and non-trivial problem in numerical relativity. A number of methods have been developed over the years to "extract" the radiative part of the solution from a numerical simulation and these include: quadrupole formulas, gauge-invariant metric perturbations, Weyl scalars, and characteristic extraction. We review and discuss each method, in terms of both its theoretical background as well as its implementation. Finally, we provide a brief comparison of the various methods in terms of their inherent advantages and disadvantages.</abstract>
</record>

<record>
  <contributors>
    <authors>
      <author>Amendola, Luca</author>
      <author>Appleby, Stephen</author>
      <author>Avgoustidis, Anastasios</author>
      <author>Bacon, David</author>
      <author>Baker, Tessa</author>
      <author>Baldi, Marco</author>
      <author>Bartolo, Nicola</author>
      <author>Blanchard, Alain</author>
      <author>Bonvin, Camille</author>
      <author>Borgani, Stefano</author>
      <author>Branchini, Enzo</author>
      <author>Burrage, Clare</author>
      <author>Camera, Stefano</author>
      <author>Carbone, Carmelita</author>
      <author>Casarini, Luciano</author>
      <author>Cropper, Mark</author>
      <author>de Rham, Claudia</author>
      <author>Dietrich, Joerg P.</author>
      <author>Di Porto, Cinzia</author>
      <author>Durrer, Ruth</author>
      <author>Ealet, Anne</author>
      <author>Ferreira, Pedro G.</author>
      <author>Finelli, Fabio</author>
      <author>Garcia-Bellido, Juan</author>
      <author>Giannantonio, Tommaso</author>
      <author>Guzzo, Luigi</author>
      <author>Heavens, Alan</author>
      <author>Heisenberg, Lavinia</author>
      <author>Heymans, Catherine</author>
      <author>Hoekstra, Henk</author>
      <author>Hollenstein, Lukas</author>
      <author>Holmes, Rory</author>
      <author>Horst, Ole</author>
      <author>Hwang, Zhiqi</author>
      <author>Jahnke, Knud</author>
      <author>Kitching, Thomas D.</author>
      <author>Koivisto, Tomi</author>
      <author>Kunz, Martin</author>
      <author>La Vacca, Giuseppe</author>
      <author>Linder, Eric</author>
      <author>March, Marisa</author>
      <author>Marra, Valerio</author>
      <author>Martins, Carlos</author>
      <author>Majerotto, Elisabetta</author>
      <author>Markovic, Dida</author>
      <author>Marsh, David</author>
      <author>Marulli, Federico</author>
      <author>Massey, Richard</author>
      <author>Mellier, Yannick</author>
      <author>Montanari, Francesco</author>
      <author>Mota, David F.</author>
      <author>Nunes, Nelson J.</author>
      <author>Percival, Will</author>
      <author>Pettorino, Valeria</author>
      <author>Porciani, Cristiano</author>
      <author>Quercellini, Claudia</author>
      <author>Read, Justin</author>
      <author>Rinaldi, Massimiliano</author>
      <author>Sapone, Domenico</author>
      <author>Sawicki, Ignacy</author>
      <author>Scaramella, Roberto</author>
      <author>Skordis, Constantinos</author>
      <author>Simpson, Fergus</author>
      <author>Taylor, Andy</author>
      <author>Thomas, Shaun</author>
      <author>Trotta, Roberto</author>
      <author>Verde, Licia</author>
      <author>Vernizzi, Filippo</author>
      <author>Vollmer, Adrian</author>
      <author>Wang, Yun</author>
      <author>Weller, Jochen</author>
      <author>Zlosnik, Tom</author>
    </authors>
  </contributors>
  <titles>
    <title>Cosmology and fundamental physics with the Euclid satellite</title>
    <secondary-title>Living Rev.Rel.</secondary-title>
  </titles>
  <electronic-resource-num>10.1007/s41114-017-0010-3</electronic-resource-num>
  <pages>2</pages>
  <volume>21</volume>
  <number>1</number>
  <keywords>
    <keyword>Dark energy</keyword>
    <keyword>Cosmology</keyword>
    <keyword>Galaxy evolution</keyword>
  </keywords>
  <dates>
    <year>2018</year>
    <pub-dates>
      <date>2018-04-12</date>
    </pub-dates>
  </dates>
  <abstract>Euclid is a European Space Agency medium class mission selected for launch in 2020 within the Cosmic Vision 2015 2025 program. The main goal of Euclid is to understand the origin of the accelerated expansion of the universe. Euclid will explore the expansion history of the universe and the evolution of cosmic structures by measuring shapes and redshifts of galaxies as well as the distribution of clusters of galaxies over a large fraction of the sky. Although the main driver for Euclid is the nature of dark energy, Euclid science covers a vast range of topics, from cosmology to galaxy evolution to planetary research. In this review we focus on cosmology and fundamental physics, with a strong emphasis on science beyond the current standard models. We discuss five broad topics: dark energy and modified gravity, dark matter, initial conditions, basic assumptions and questions of methodology in the data analysis. This review has been planned and carried out within Euclid's Theory Working Group and is meant to provide a guide to the scientific themes that will underlie the activity of the group during the preparation of the Euclid mission.</abstract>
</record>

<record>
  <contributors>
    <authors>
      <author>Harms, Jan</author>
    </authors>
  </contributors>
  <titles>
    <title>Terrestrial Gravity Fluctuations</title>
    <secondary-title>Living Rev.Rel.</secondary-title>
  </titles>
  <electronic-resource-num>10.1007/lrr-2015-3</electronic-resource-num>
  <pages>3</pages>
  <volume>18</volume>
  <number/>
  <keywords>
    <keyword>Wiener filter</keyword>
    <keyword>Terrestrial gravity</keyword>
    <keyword>Mitigation</keyword>
    <keyword>Newtonian noise</keyword>
  </keywords>
  <dates>
    <year>2015</year>
    <pub-dates>
      <date>2015</date>
    </pub-dates>
  </dates>
  <abstract>The article reviews the current state of the field, and also presents new analyses especially with respect to the impact of seismic scattering on gravity perturbations, active gravity noise cancellation, and time-domain models of gravity perturbations from atmospheric and seismic point sources. Our understanding of terrestrial gravity fluctuations will have great impact on the future development of GW detectors and high-precision gravimetry in general, and many open questions need to be answered still as emphasized in this article.</abstract>
</record>

<record>
  <contributors>
    <authors>
      <author>Tinto, Massimo</author>
      <author>Dhurandhar, Sanjeev V.</author>
    </authors>
  </contributors>
  <titles>
    <title>Time-Delay Interferometry</title>
    <secondary-title>Living Rev.Rel.</secondary-title>
  </titles>
  <electronic-resource-num>10.12942/lrr-2014-6</electronic-resource-num>
  <pages>6</pages>
  <volume>17</volume>
  <number/>
  <keywords>
    <keyword>Interferometry</keyword>
    <keyword>Gravitational-wave detectors</keyword>
  </keywords>
  <dates>
    <year>2014</year>
    <pub-dates>
      <date>2014</date>
    </pub-dates>
  </dates>
  <abstract>Equal-arm detectors of gravitational radiation allow phase measurements many orders of magnitude below the intrinsic phase stability of the laser injecting light into their arms. This is because the noise in the laser light is common to both arms, experiencing exactly the same delay, and thus cancels when it is differenced at the photo detector. In this situation, much lower level secondary noises then set the overall performance. If, however, the two arms have different lengths (as will necessarily be the case with space-borne interferometers), the laser noise experiences different delays in the two arms and will hence not directly cancel at the detector. In order to solve this problem, a technique involving heterodyne interferometry with unequal arm lengths and independent phase-difference readouts has been proposed. It relies on properly time-shifting and linearly combining independent Doppler measurements, and for this reason it has been called time-delay interferometry (TDI). This article provides an overview of the theory, mathematical foundations, and experimen- tal aspects associated with the implementation of TDI. Although emphasis on the application of TDI to the Laser Interferometer Space Antenna (LISA) mission appears throughout this article, TDI can be incorporated into the design of any future space-based mission aiming to search for gravitational waves via interferometric measurements. We have purposely left out all theoretical aspects that data analysts will need to account for when analyzing the TDI data combinations</abstract>
</record>

<record>
  <contributors>
    <authors>
      <author>Goenner, Hubert F.M.</author>
    </authors>
  </contributors>
  <titles>
    <title>On the History of Unified Field Theories. Part II. (ca. 1930 - ca. 1965)</title>
    <secondary-title>Living Rev.Rel.</secondary-title>
  </titles>
  <electronic-resource-num>10.12942/lrr-2014-5</electronic-resource-num>
  <pages>5</pages>
  <volume>17</volume>
  <number/>
  <keywords>
    <keyword>Differential geometry</keyword>
    <keyword>History of science</keyword>
    <keyword>Unified field theory</keyword>
  </keywords>
  <dates>
    <year>2014</year>
    <pub-dates>
      <date>2014</date>
    </pub-dates>
  </dates>
  <abstract>The present review intends to provide an overall picture of the research concerning classical unified field theory, worldwide, in the decades between the mid-1930 and mid-1960. Main themes are the conceptual and methodical development of the field, the interaction among the scientists working in it, their opinions and interpretations. Next to the most prominent players, A. Einstein and E. Schro&lt;dinger, V. Hlavaty and the French groups around A. Lichnerowicz, M.-A. Tonnelat, and Y. Thiry are presented. It is shown that they have given contributions of comparable importance. The review also includes a few sections on the fringes of the central topic like Born-Infeld electromagnetic theory or scalar-tensor theory. Some comments on the structure and organization of research-groups are also made.</abstract>
</record>

<record>
  <contributors>
    <authors>
      <author>Will, Clifford M.</author>
    </authors>
  </contributors>
  <titles>
    <title>The Confrontation between General Relativity and Experiment</title>
    <secondary-title>Living Rev.Rel.</secondary-title>
  </titles>
  <electronic-resource-num>10.12942/lrr-2014-4</electronic-resource-num>
  <pages>4</pages>
  <volume>17</volume>
  <number/>
  <keywords>
    <keyword>Gravitational radiation</keyword>
    <keyword>Theories of gravity</keyword>
    <keyword>Post-Newtonian limit</keyword>
    <keyword>Tests of relativistic gravity</keyword>
  </keywords>
  <dates>
    <year>2014</year>
    <pub-dates>
      <date>2014</date>
    </pub-dates>
  </dates>
  <abstract>The status of experimental tests of general relativity and of theoretical frameworks for analyzing them are reviewed and updated. Einstein's equivalence principle (EEP) is well supported by experiments such as the Eotvos experiment, tests of local Lorentz invariance and clock experiments. Ongoing tests of EEP and of the inverse square law are searching for new interactions arising from unification or quantum gravity. Tests of general relativity at the post-Newtonian level have reached high precision, including the light deflection, the Shapiro time delay, the perihelion advance of Mercury, the Nordtvedt effect in lunar motion, and frame-dragging. Gravitational-wave damping has been detected in an amount that agrees with general relativity to better than half a percent using the Hulse-Taylor binary pulsar, and a growing family of other binary pulsar systems is yielding new tests, especially of strong-field effects. Current and future tests of relativity will center on strong gravity and gravitational waves.</abstract>
</record>

<record>
  <contributors>
    <authors>
      <author>Postnov, Konstantin A.</author>
      <author>Yungelson, Lev R.</author>
    </authors>
  </contributors>
  <titles>
    <title>The Evolution of Compact Binary Star Systems</title>
    <secondary-title>Living Rev.Rel.</secondary-title>
  </titles>
  <electronic-resource-num>10.12942/lrr-2014-3</electronic-resource-num>
  <pages>3</pages>
  <volume>17</volume>
  <number/>
  <keywords>
    <keyword>Black holes</keyword>
    <keyword>Astrophysics</keyword>
    <keyword>Binary systems</keyword>
    <keyword>Neutron stars</keyword>
    <keyword>White dwarfs</keyword>
    <keyword>AM CVn stars</keyword>
    <keyword>Supernovae</keyword>
    <keyword>Gravitational-wave sources</keyword>
  </keywords>
  <dates>
    <year>2014</year>
    <pub-dates>
      <date>2014</date>
    </pub-dates>
  </dates>
  <abstract>We review the formation and evolution of compact binary stars consisting of white dwarfs (WDs), neutron stars (NSs), and black holes (BHs). Mergings of compact binary stars are expected to be the most important sources for the forthcoming gravitational-wave (GW) astronomy. In the first part of the review, we discuss observational manifestations of close binary stars with NS and/or black components and their merger rate, crucial points in the formation and evolution of compact stars in binary systems, including the treatment of the natal kicks which NSs and BHs acquire during the core collapse of massive stars and the common envelope phase of binary evolution, which are most relevant to the merging rates of NS-NS, NS-BH and BH-BH binaries. The second part of the review is devoted mainly to formation and evolution of binary WDs and their observational manifestations, including their role as progenitors of cosmologically important thermonuclear SN Ia. We also consider AM CVn-stars which are thought to be the best verification binary GW sources for future low-frequency GW space interferometers.</abstract>
</record>

<record>
  <contributors>
    <authors>
      <author>de Rham, Claudia</author>
    </authors>
  </contributors>
  <titles>
    <title>Massive Gravity</title>
    <secondary-title>Living Rev.Rel.</secondary-title>
  </titles>
  <electronic-resource-num>10.12942/lrr-2014-7</electronic-resource-num>
  <pages>7</pages>
  <volume>17</volume>
  <number/>
  <keywords>
    <keyword>General relativity</keyword>
    <keyword>Gravity</keyword>
    <keyword>Alternative theories of gravity</keyword>
    <keyword>Modified theories of gravity</keyword>
    <keyword>Massive gravity</keyword>
  </keywords>
  <dates>
    <year>2014</year>
    <pub-dates>
      <date>2014</date>
    </pub-dates>
  </dates>
  <abstract>We review recent progress in massive gravity. We start by showing how different theories of massive gravity emerge from a higher-dimensional theory of general relativity, leading to the Dvali-Gabadadze-Porrati model, cascading gravity and ghost-free massive gravity. We then explore their theoretical and phenomenological consistency, proving the absence of Boulware-Deser ghosts and reviewing the Vainshtein mechanism and the cosmological solutions in these models. Finally we present alternative and related models of massive gravity such as new massive gravity, Lorentz-violating massive gravity and non-local massive gravity.</abstract>
</record>

<record>
  <contributors>
    <authors>
      <author>Blanchet, Luc</author>
    </authors>
  </contributors>
  <titles>
    <title>Gravitational Radiation from Post-Newtonian Sources and Inspiralling Compact Binaries</title>
    <secondary-title>Living Rev.Rel.</secondary-title>
  </titles>
  <electronic-resource-num>10.12942/lrr-2014-2</electronic-resource-num>
  <pages>2</pages>
  <volume>17</volume>
  <number/>
  <keywords>
    <keyword>Inspiralling compact binary</keyword>
    <keyword>Multipolar expansion</keyword>
    <keyword>Gravitational radiation</keyword>
    <keyword>Post-Newtonian approximations</keyword>
  </keywords>
  <dates>
    <year>2014</year>
    <pub-dates>
      <date>2014</date>
    </pub-dates>
  </dates>
  <abstract>To be observed and analyzed by the network of gravitational wave detectors on ground (LIGO, VIRGO, etc.) and by the future detectors in space (eLISA, etc.), inspiralling compact binaries -- binary star systems composed of neutron stars and/or black holes in their late stage of evolution -- require high-accuracy templates predicted by general relativity theory. The gravitational waves emitted by these very relativistic systems can be accurately modelled using a high-order post-Newtonian gravitational wave generation formalism. In this article, we present the current state of the art on post-Newtonian methods as applied to the dynamics and gravitational radiation of general matter sources (including the radiation reaction back onto the source) and inspiralling compact binaries. We describe the post-Newtonian equations of motion of compact binaries and the associated Lagrangian and Hamiltonian formalisms, paying attention to the self-field regularizations at work in the calculations. Several notions of innermost circular orbits are discussed. We estimate the accuracy of the post-Newtonian approximation and make a comparison with numerical computations of the gravitational self-force for compact binaries in the small mass ratio limit. The gravitational waveform and energy flux are obtained to high post-Newtonian order and the binary's orbital phase evolution is deduced from an energy balance argument. Some landmark results are given in the case of eccentric compact binaries -- moving on quasi-elliptical orbits with non-negligible eccentricity. The spins of the two black holes play an important role in the definition of the gravitational wave templates. We investigate their imprint on the equations of motion and gravitational wave phasing up to high post-Newtonian order (restricting to spin-orbit effects which are linear in spins), and analyze the post-Newtonian spin precession equations as well as the induced precession of the orbital plane.</abstract>
</record>

<record>
  <contributors>
    <authors>
      <author>Merkowitz, Stephen M.</author>
    </authors>
  </contributors>
  <titles>
    <title>Tests of Gravity Using Lunar Laser Ranging</title>
    <secondary-title>Living Rev.Rel.</secondary-title>
  </titles>
  <electronic-resource-num>10.12942/lrr-2010-7</electronic-resource-num>
  <pages>7</pages>
  <volume>13</volume>
  <number/>
  <dates>
    <year>2010</year>
  </dates>
  <abstract/>
</record>

<record>
  <contributors>
    <authors>
      <author>Taniguchi, Keisuke</author>
      <author>Shibata, Masaru</author>
    </authors>
  </contributors>
  <titles>
    <title>Coalescence of Black Hole-Neutron Star Binaries</title>
    <secondary-title>Living Rev.Rel.</secondary-title>
  </titles>
  <electronic-resource-num>10.12942/lrr-2011-6</electronic-resource-num>
  <pages>6</pages>
  <volume>14</volume>
  <number/>
  <dates>
    <year>2011</year>
  </dates>
  <abstract>We review the current status of general relativistic studies for the coalescence of black hole-neutron star (BH-NS) binaries. First, procedures for a solution of BH-NS binaries in quasi-equilibrium circular orbits and the numerical results, such as quasi-equilibrium sequence and mass-shedding limit, of the high-precision computation, are summarized. Then, the current status of numerical-relativity simulations for the merger of BH-NS binaries is described. We summarize our understanding for the merger and/or tidal disruption processes, the criterion for tidal disruption, the properties of the remnant formed after the tidal disruption, gravitational waveform, and gravitational-wave spectrum.</abstract>
</record>

<record>
  <contributors>
    <authors>
      <author>Benacquista, Matthew J.</author>
    </authors>
  </contributors>
  <titles>
    <title>Relativistic Binaries in Globular Clusters</title>
    <secondary-title>Living Rev.Rel.</secondary-title>
  </titles>
  <electronic-resource-num>10.12942/lrr-2006-2</electronic-resource-num>
  <pages>2</pages>
  <volume>9</volume>
  <number/>
  <dates>
    <year>2006</year>
  </dates>
  <abstract>The galactic population of globular clusters are old, dense star systems, with a typical cluster containing 10^4 - 10^7 stars. As an old population of stars, globular clusters contain many collapsed and degenerate objects. As a dense population of stars, globular clusters are the scene of many interesting close dynamical interactions between stars. These dynamical interactions can alter the evolution of individual stars and can produce tight binary systems containing one or two compact objects. In this review, we discuss the theoretical models of globular cluster evolution and binary evolution, techniques for simulating this evolution which lead to relativistic binaries, and current and possible future observational evidence for this population. Globular cluster evolution will focus on the properties that boost the production of hard binary systems and on the tidal interactions of the galaxy with the cluster, which tend to alter the structure of the globular cluster with time. The interaction of the components of hard binary systems alters the evolution of both bodies and can lead to exotic objects. Direct N-body integrations and Fokker-Planck simulations of the evolution of globular clusters that incorporate tidal interactions and lead to predictions of relativistic binary populations are also discussed. We discuss the current observational evidence for cataclysmic variables, millisecond pulsars, and low-mass X-ray binaries as well as possible future detection of relativistic binaries with gravitational radiation.</abstract>
</record>

<record>
  <contributors>
    <authors>
      <author>Font, Jose A.</author>
    </authors>
  </contributors>
  <titles>
    <title>Numerical Hydrodynamics and Magnetohydrodynamics in General Relativity</title>
    <secondary-title>Living Rev.Rel.</secondary-title>
  </titles>
  <electronic-resource-num>10.12942/lrr-2008-7</electronic-resource-num>
  <pages>7</pages>
  <volume>11</volume>
  <number/>
  <dates>
    <year>2008</year>
  </dates>
  <abstract>This article presents a comprehensive overview of numerical hydrodynamics and magnetohydrodynamics (MHD) in general relativity. Some significant additions have been incorporated with respect to the previous two versions of this review (2000, 2003), most notably the coverage of general-relativistic MHD, a field in which remarkable activity and progress has occurred in the last few years. Correspondingly, the discussion of astrophysical simulations in general-relativistic hydrodynamics is enlarged to account for recent relevant advances, while those dealing with general-relativistic MHD are amply covered in this review for the first time. The basic outline of this article is nevertheless similar to its earlier versions, save for the addition of MHD-related issues throughout. Hence, different formulations of both the hydrodynamics and MHD equations are presented, with special mention of conservative and hyperbolic formulations well adapted to advanced numerical methods. A large sample of numerical approaches for solving such hyperbolic systems of equations is discussed, paying particular attention to solution procedures based on schemes exploiting the characteristic structure of the equations through linearized Riemann solvers. As previously stated, a comprehensive summary of astrophysical simulations in strong gravitational fields is also presented. These are detailed in three basic sections, namely gravitational collapse, black-hole accretion, and neutron-star evolutions; despite the boundaries, these sections may (and in fact do) overlap throughout the discussion. The material contained in these sections highlights the numerical challenges of various representative simulations. It also follows, to some extent, the chronological development of the field, concerning advances in the formulation of the gravitational field, hydrodynamics and MHD equations and the numerical methodology designed to solve them. To keep the length of this article reasonable, an effort has been made to focus on multidimensional studies, directing the interested reader to earlier versions of the review for discussions on one-dimensional works.</abstract>
</record>

<record>
  <contributors>
    <authors>
      <author>Szabados, László B.</author>
    </authors>
  </contributors>
  <titles>
    <title>Quasi-Local Energy-Momentum and Angular Momentum in General Relativity</title>
    <secondary-title>Living Rev.Rel.</secondary-title>
  </titles>
  <electronic-resource-num>10.12942/lrr-2009-4</electronic-resource-num>
  <pages>4</pages>
  <volume>12</volume>
  <number/>
  <dates>
    <year>2009</year>
  </dates>
  <abstract>The present status of the quasi-local mass, energy-momentum and angular-momentum constructions in general relativity is reviewed. First, the general ideas, concepts, and strategies, as well as the necessary tools to construct and analyze the quasi-local quantities, are recalled. Then, the various specific constructions and their properties (both successes and deficiencies are discussed. Finally, some of the (actual and potential) applications of the quasi-local concepts and specific constructions are briefly mentioned.</abstract>
</record>

<record>
  <contributors>
    <authors>
      <author>Rendall, Alan D.</author>
    </authors>
  </contributors>
  <titles>
    <title>Local and Global Existence Theorems for the Einstein Equations</title>
    <secondary-title>Living Rev.Rel.</secondary-title>
  </titles>
  <electronic-resource-num>10.12942/lrr-1998-4</electronic-resource-num>
  <pages>4</pages>
  <volume>1</volume>
  <number/>
  <dates>
    <year>1998</year>
  </dates>
  <abstract>This article is a guide to the literature on existence theorems for the Einstein equations which also draws attention to open problems in the field. The local in time Cauchy problem, which is relatively well understood, is treated first. Next global results for solutionswith symmetry are discussed. This is followed by a presentation of global results in the case of small data, and some miscellaneous topics connected with the main theme.</abstract>
</record>

<record>
  <contributors>
    <authors>
      <author>Anninos, Peter</author>
    </authors>
  </contributors>
  <titles>
    <title>Physical and Relativistic Numerical Cosmology</title>
    <secondary-title>Living Rev.Rel.</secondary-title>
  </titles>
  <electronic-resource-num>10.12942/lrr-1998-2</electronic-resource-num>
  <pages>2</pages>
  <volume>1</volume>
  <number/>
  <dates>
    <year>1998</year>
  </dates>
  <abstract>In order to account for the observable Universe, any comprehensive theory or model of cosmology must draw from many disciplines of physics, including gauge theories of strong and weak interactions, the hydrodynamics and microphysics of baryonic matter, electromagnetic fields, and spacetime curvature, for example. Although it is difficult to incorporate all these physical elements into a single complete model of our Universe, advances in computing methods and technologies have contributed significantly towards our understanding of cosmological models, the Universe, and astrophysical processes within them. A sample of numerical calculations addressing specific issues in cosmology are reviewed in this article: from the Big Bang singularity dynamics to the fundamental interactions of gravitational waves; from the quark--hadron phase transition to the large scale structure of the Universe. The emphasis, although not exclusively, is on those calculations designed to test different models of cosmology against the observed Universe.</abstract>
</record>

<record>
  <contributors>
    <authors>
      <author>Ashby, Neil</author>
    </authors>
  </contributors>
  <titles>
    <title>Relativity in the Global Positioning System</title>
    <secondary-title>Living Rev.Rel.</secondary-title>
  </titles>
  <electronic-resource-num>10.12942/lrr-2003-1</electronic-resource-num>
  <pages>1</pages>
  <volume>6</volume>
  <number/>
  <dates>
    <year>2003</year>
  </dates>
  <abstract>The Global Positioning System (GPS) uses accurate, stable atomic clocks in satellites and on the ground to provide world-wide position and time determination. These clocks have gravitational and motional frequency shifts which are so large that, without carefully accounting for numerous relativistic effects, the system would not work. This paper discusses the conceptual basis, founded on special and general relativity, for navigation using GPS. Relativistic principles and effects which must be considered include the constancy of the speed of light, the equivalence principle, the Sagnac effect, time dilation, gravitational frequency shifts, and relativity of synchronization. Experimental tests of relativity obtained with a GPS receiver aboard the TOPEX/POSEIDON satellite will be discussed. Recently frequency jumps arising from satellite orbit adjustments have been identified as relativistic effects. These will be explained and some interesting applications of GPS will be discussed.</abstract>
</record>

<record>
  <contributors>
    <authors>
      <author>Kunduri, Hari K.</author>
      <author>Lucietti, James</author>
    </authors>
  </contributors>
  <titles>
    <title>Classification of near-horizon geometries of extremal black holes</title>
    <secondary-title>Living Rev.Rel.</secondary-title>
  </titles>
  <electronic-resource-num>10.12942/lrr-2013-8</electronic-resource-num>
  <pages>8</pages>
  <volume>16</volume>
  <number/>
  <keywords>
    <keyword>Black holes</keyword>
    <keyword>Extremal black holes</keyword>
    <keyword>Near-horizon geometry</keyword>
  </keywords>
  <dates>
    <year>2013</year>
    <pub-dates>
      <date>2013</date>
    </pub-dates>
  </dates>
  <abstract>Any spacetime containing a degenerate Killing horizon, such as an extremal black hole, possesses a well-defined notion of a near-horizon geometry. We review such near-horizon geometry solutions in a variety of dimensions and theories in a unified manner. We discuss various general results including horizon topology and near-horizon symmetry enhancement. We also discuss the status of the classification of near-horizon geometries in theories ranging from vacuum gravity to Einstein-Maxwell theory and supergravity theories. Finally, we discuss applications to the classification of extremal black holes and various related topics. Several new results are presented and open problems are highlighted throughout.</abstract>
</record>

<record>
  <contributors>
    <authors>
      <author>Yunes, Nicolás</author>
      <author>Siemens, Xavier</author>
    </authors>
  </contributors>
  <titles>
    <title>Gravitational-Wave Tests of General Relativity with Ground-Based Detectors and Pulsar Timing-Arrays</title>
    <secondary-title>Living Rev.Rel.</secondary-title>
  </titles>
  <electronic-resource-num>10.12942/lrr-2013-9</electronic-resource-num>
  <pages>9</pages>
  <volume>16</volume>
  <number/>
  <keywords>
    <keyword>Alternative theories</keyword>
    <keyword>Pulsar timing</keyword>
    <keyword>General relativity</keyword>
    <keyword>Gravitational waves</keyword>
    <keyword>Observational tests</keyword>
    <keyword>Experimental tests</keyword>
    <keyword>Compact binaries</keyword>
  </keywords>
  <dates>
    <year>2013</year>
    <pub-dates>
      <date>2013</date>
    </pub-dates>
  </dates>
  <abstract>This review is focused on tests of Einstein's theory of general relativity with gravitational waves that are detectable by ground-based interferometers and pulsar-timing experiments. Einstein's theory has been greatly constrained in the quasi-linear, quasi-stationary regime, where gravity is weak and velocities are small. Gravitational waves will allow us to probe a complimentary, yet previously unexplored regime: the non-linear and dynamical strong-field regime. Such a regime is, for example, applicable to compact binaries coalescing, where characteristic velocities can reach fifty percent the speed of light and gravitational fields are large and dynamical. This review begins with the theoretical basis and the predicted gravitational-wave observables of modified gravity theories. The review continues with a brief description of the detectors, including both gravitational-wave interferometers and pulsar-timing arrays, leading to a discussion of the data analysis formalism that is applicable for such tests. The review ends with a discussion of gravitational-wave tests for compact binary systems.</abstract>
</record>

<record>
  <contributors>
    <authors>
      <author>Abbott, Benjamin P.</author>
      <author>Abbott, Rich</author>
      <author>Abbott, Thomas D.</author>
      <author>Abernathy, Matthew R.</author>
      <author>Acernese, Fausto</author>
      <author>Ackley, Kendall</author>
      <author>Adams, Carl</author>
      <author>Adams, Thomas</author>
      <author>Addesso, Paolo</author>
      <author>Adhikari, Rana X.</author>
      <author>Adya, Vaishali B.</author>
      <author>Affeldt, Christoph</author>
      <author>Agathos, Michalis</author>
      <author>Agatsuma, Kazuhiro</author>
      <author>Aggarwal, Nancy</author>
      <author>Aguiar, Odylio D.</author>
      <author>Aiello, Lorenzo</author>
      <author>Ain, Anirban</author>
      <author>Ajith, P.</author>
      <author>Akutsu, T.</author>
      <author>Allen, Bruce</author>
      <author>Allocca, Annalisa</author>
      <author>Altin, Paul A.</author>
      <author>Ananyeva, Alena</author>
      <author>Anderson, Stuart B.</author>
      <author>Anderson, Warren G.</author>
      <author>Ando, M.</author>
      <author>Appert, Stephen</author>
      <author>Arai, Koji</author>
      <author>Araya, A.</author>
      <author>Araya, Melody C.</author>
      <author>Areeda, Joseph S.</author>
      <author>Arnaud, Nicolas</author>
      <author>Arun, Kg G.</author>
      <author>Asada, H.</author>
      <author>Ascenzi, Stefano</author>
      <author>Ashton, Gregory</author>
      <author>Aso, Y.</author>
      <author>Ast, M.</author>
      <author>Aston, Stuart M.</author>
      <author>Astone, Pia</author>
      <author>Atsuta, S.</author>
      <author>Aufmuth, Peter</author>
      <author>Aulbert, Carsten</author>
      <author>Avila-Alvarez, A.</author>
      <author>Awai, K.</author>
      <author>Babak, Stanislav</author>
      <author>Bacon, Philippe</author>
      <author>Bader, Maria K.M.</author>
      <author>Baiotti, L.</author>
      <author>Baker, Paul T.</author>
      <author>Baldaccini, Francesca</author>
      <author>Ballardin, Giulio</author>
      <author>Ballmer, Stefan W.</author>
      <author>Barayoga, Juan C.</author>
      <author>Barclay, Sheena E.</author>
      <author>Barish, Barry C.</author>
      <author>Barker, David</author>
      <author>Barone, Fabrizio</author>
      <author>Barr, Bryan</author>
      <author>Barsotti, Lisa</author>
      <author>Barsuglia, Matteo</author>
      <author>Barta, Daniel</author>
      <author>Bartlett, Jeffrey</author>
      <author>Barton, M.A.</author>
      <author>Bartos, Imre</author>
      <author>Bassiri, Riccardo</author>
      <author>Basti, Andrea</author>
      <author>Batch, James C.</author>
      <author>Baune, Christoph</author>
      <author>Bavigadda, Viswanath</author>
      <author>Bazzan, Marco</author>
      <author>Bécsy, B.</author>
      <author>Beer, Christian</author>
      <author>Bejger, Michal</author>
      <author>Belahcene, Imene</author>
      <author>Belgin, Mehmet</author>
      <author>Bell, Angus S.</author>
      <author>Berger, Beverly K.</author>
      <author>Bergmann, Gerald</author>
      <author>Berry, Christopher P.L.</author>
      <author>Bersanetti, Diego</author>
      <author>Bertolini, Alessandro</author>
      <author>Betzwieser, Joseph</author>
      <author>Bhagwat, Swetha</author>
      <author>Bhandare, Rohan</author>
      <author>Bilenko, Igor A.</author>
      <author>Billingsley, Garilynn</author>
      <author>Billman, Chris R.</author>
      <author>Birch, Jeremy</author>
      <author>Birney, Ross</author>
      <author>Birnholtz, Ofek</author>
      <author>Biscans, Sebastien</author>
      <author>Bisht, Aparna</author>
      <author>Bitossi, Massimiliano</author>
      <author>Biwer, Christopher</author>
      <author>Bizouard, Marieanne A.</author>
      <author>Blackburn, J.K.</author>
      <author>Blackman, Jonathan</author>
      <author>Blair, Carl D.</author>
      <author>Blair, David G.</author>
      <author>Blair, Ryan M.</author>
      <author>Bloemen, Steven</author>
      <author>Bock, Oliver</author>
      <author>Boer, Michel</author>
      <author>Bogaert, Gilles</author>
      <author>Bohe, Alejandro</author>
      <author>Bondu, Francois</author>
      <author>Bonnand, Romain</author>
      <author>Boom, Boris A.</author>
      <author>Bork, Rolf</author>
      <author>Boschi, Valerio</author>
      <author>Bose, Sukanta</author>
      <author>Bouffanais, Yann</author>
      <author>Bozzi, Antonella</author>
      <author>Bradaschia, Carlo</author>
      <author>Brady, Patrick R.</author>
      <author>Branchesi, Marica</author>
      <author>Brau, Jim E.</author>
      <author>Briant, Tristan</author>
      <author>Brillet, Alain</author>
      <author>Brinkmann, Marc</author>
      <author>Brisson, Violette</author>
      <author>Brockill, Patrick</author>
      <author>Broida, Jacob E.</author>
      <author>Brooks, Aidan F.</author>
      <author>Brown, Duncan A.</author>
      <author>Brown, Daniel D.</author>
      <author>Brown, Nicolas M.</author>
      <author>Brunett, Sharon</author>
      <author>Buchanan, Christopher C.</author>
      <author>Buikema, Aaron</author>
      <author>Bulik, Tomasz</author>
      <author>Bulten, Henk J.</author>
      <author>Buonanno, Alessandra</author>
      <author>Buskulic, Damir</author>
      <author>Buy, Christelle</author>
      <author>Byer, Robert L.</author>
      <author>Cabero, Miriam</author>
      <author>Cadonati, Laura</author>
      <author>Cagnoli, Giampietro</author>
      <author>Cahillane, Craig</author>
      <author>Calderón Bustillo, J.</author>
      <author>Callister, Thomas A.</author>
      <author>Calloni, Enrico</author>
      <author>Camp, Jordan B.</author>
      <author>Cannon, Kipp C.</author>
      <author>Cao, H.</author>
      <author>Cao, Junwei</author>
      <author>Capano, Collin D.</author>
      <author>Capocasa, Eleonora</author>
      <author>Carbognani, Franco</author>
      <author>Caride, Santiago</author>
      <author>Casanueva Diaz, J.</author>
      <author>Casentini, Claudio</author>
      <author>Caudill, Sarah</author>
      <author>Cavaglià, Marco</author>
      <author>Cavalier, Fabien</author>
      <author>Cavalieri, Roberto</author>
      <author>Cella, Giancarlo</author>
      <author>Cepeda, Christian B.</author>
      <author>Cerboni Baiardi, L.</author>
      <author>Cerretani, Giovanni</author>
      <author>Cesarini, Elisabetta</author>
      <author>Chamberlin, Sydney J.</author>
      <author>Chan, Manleong</author>
      <author>Chao, Shiuh</author>
      <author>Charlton, Philip</author>
      <author>Chassande-Mottin, E.</author>
      <author>Cheeseboro, Belinda D.</author>
      <author>Chen, H.Y.</author>
      <author>Chen, Yanbei</author>
      <author>Cheng, H.-P.</author>
      <author>Chincarini, Andrea</author>
      <author>Chiummo, Antonino</author>
      <author>Chmiel, Theresa</author>
      <author>Cho, Heesuk S.</author>
      <author>Cho, M.</author>
      <author>Chow, Jong H.</author>
      <author>Christensen, Nelson</author>
      <author>Chu, Qi</author>
      <author>Chua, Alvin J.K.</author>
      <author>Chua, Sheon</author>
      <author>Chung, Shinkee</author>
      <author>Ciani, Giacomo</author>
      <author>Clara, Filiberto</author>
      <author>Clark, James A.</author>
      <author>Cleva, Frederic</author>
      <author>Cocchieri, Camillo</author>
      <author>Coccia, Eugenio</author>
      <author>Cohadon, P.-F.</author>
      <author>Colla, Alberto</author>
      <author>Collette, Christophe G.</author>
      <author>Cominsky, Lynn</author>
      <author>Constancio, M., Jr.</author>
      <author>Conti, Livia</author>
      <author>Cooper, Sam J.</author>
      <author>Corbitt, Thomas R.</author>
      <author>Cornish, Neil</author>
      <author>Corsi, Alessandra</author>
      <author>Cortese, Stefano</author>
      <author>Costa, Cesar A.</author>
      <author>Coughlin, Michael W.</author>
      <author>Coughlin, Scott B.</author>
      <author>Coulon, J.-P.</author>
      <author>Countryman, Stefan T.</author>
      <author>Couvares, Peter</author>
      <author>Covas, Pep B.</author>
      <author>Cowan, Erika E.</author>
      <author>Coward, David M.</author>
      <author>Cowart, Matthew J.</author>
      <author>Coyne, Dennis C.</author>
      <author>Coyne, Robert</author>
      <author>Creighton, Jolien D.E.</author>
      <author>Creighton, Teviet D.</author>
      <author>Cripe, Jonathan</author>
      <author>Crowder, Sgwynne G.</author>
      <author>Cullen, Torrey J.</author>
      <author>Cumming, Alan</author>
      <author>Cunningham, Liam</author>
      <author>Cuoco, Elena</author>
      <author>Dal Canton, Tito</author>
      <author>Danilishin, Stefan L.</author>
      <author>D'Antonio, S.</author>
      <author>Danzmann, Karsten</author>
      <author>Dasgupta, Arnab</author>
      <author>Da Silva Costa, C.F.</author>
      <author>Dattilo, Vincenzo</author>
      <author>Dave, Ishant</author>
      <author>Davier, Michel</author>
      <author>Davies, Gareth S.</author>
      <author>Davis, Derek</author>
      <author>Daw, Edward J.</author>
      <author>Day, Brian</author>
      <author>Day, R.</author>
      <author>De, Soumi</author>
      <author>DeBra, D.</author>
      <author>Debreczeni, Gergely</author>
      <author>Degallaix, Jerome</author>
      <author>De Laurentis, M.</author>
      <author>Deléglise, Samuel</author>
      <author>Del Pozzo, W.</author>
      <author>Denker, Timo</author>
      <author>Dent, Thomas</author>
      <author>Dergachev, Vladimir</author>
      <author>De Rosa, R.</author>
      <author>DeRosa, R.T.</author>
      <author>DeSalvo, R.</author>
      <author>Devine, Richard C.</author>
      <author>Dhurandhar, Sanjeev</author>
      <author>Díaz, Mario C.</author>
      <author>Di Fiore, L.</author>
      <author>Di Giovanni, M.</author>
      <author>Di Girolamo, T.</author>
      <author>Di Lieto, A.</author>
      <author>Di Pace, S.</author>
      <author>Di Palma, I.</author>
      <author>Di Virgilio, A.</author>
      <author>Doctor, Zoheyr</author>
      <author>Doi, K.</author>
      <author>Dolique, Vincent</author>
      <author>Donovan, Fred</author>
      <author>Dooley, Katherine L.</author>
      <author>Doravari, Suresh</author>
      <author>Dorrington, Iain</author>
      <author>Douglas, Rebecca</author>
      <author>Dovale Álvarez, M.</author>
      <author>Downes, Thomas P.</author>
      <author>Drago, Marco</author>
      <author>Driggers, Jenne C.</author>
      <author>Du, Zhihui</author>
      <author>Ducrot, Marine</author>
      <author>Dwyer, Sheila E.</author>
      <author>Eda, K.</author>
      <author>Edo, Tega B.</author>
      <author>Edwards, Matthew C.</author>
      <author>Effler, Anamaria</author>
      <author>Eggenstein, H.-B.</author>
      <author>Ehrens, Phil</author>
      <author>Eichholz, Johannes</author>
      <author>Eikenberry, Stephen S.</author>
      <author>Eisenstein, Robert A.</author>
      <author>Essick, Reed C.</author>
      <author>Etienne, Zachariah</author>
      <author>Etzel, Todd</author>
      <author>Evans, Matthew</author>
      <author>Evans, Tom M.</author>
      <author>Everett, Ryan</author>
      <author>Factourovich, Maxim</author>
      <author>Fafone, Viviana</author>
      <author>Fair, Hannah</author>
      <author>Fairhurst, Stephen</author>
      <author>Fan, Xilong</author>
      <author>Farinon, Stefania</author>
      <author>Farr, Benjamin</author>
      <author>Farr, Will M.</author>
      <author>Fauchon-Jones, E.J.</author>
      <author>Favata, Marc</author>
      <author>Fays, Maxime</author>
      <author>Fehrmann, Henning</author>
      <author>Fejer, Martin M.</author>
      <author>Fernández Galiana, A.</author>
      <author>Ferrante, Isidoro</author>
      <author>Ferreira, Elvis C.</author>
      <author>Ferrini, Federico</author>
      <author>Fidecaro, Francesco</author>
      <author>Fiori, Irene</author>
      <author>Fiorucci, Donatella</author>
      <author>Fisher, Ryan P.</author>
      <author>Flaminio, Raffaele</author>
      <author>Fletcher, Mark</author>
      <author>Fong, Heather</author>
      <author>Forsyth, Steven S.</author>
      <author>Fournier, J.-D.</author>
      <author>Frasca, Sergio</author>
      <author>Frasconi, Franco</author>
      <author>Frei, Zsolt</author>
      <author>Freise, Andreas</author>
      <author>Frey, Raymond</author>
      <author>Frey, Valentin</author>
      <author>Fries, Eric M.</author>
      <author>Fritschel, Peter</author>
      <author>Frolov, Valery V.</author>
      <author>Fujii, Y.</author>
      <author>Fujimoto, M.-K.</author>
      <author>Fulda, Paul</author>
      <author>Fyffe, Michael</author>
      <author>Gabbard, Hunter</author>
      <author>Gadre, Bhooshan U.</author>
      <author>Gaebel, Sebastian M.</author>
      <author>Gair, Jonathan R.</author>
      <author>Gammaitoni, Luca</author>
      <author>Gaonkar, Sharad G.</author>
      <author>Garufi, Fabio</author>
      <author>Gaur, Gurudatt</author>
      <author>Gayathri, V.</author>
      <author>Gemme, Gianluca</author>
      <author>Genin, Eric</author>
      <author>Gennai, Alberto</author>
      <author>George, Jogy</author>
      <author>Gergely, Laszlo</author>
      <author>Germain, Vincent</author>
      <author>Ghonge, Sudarshan</author>
      <author>Ghosh, Abhirup</author>
      <author>Ghosh, Archisman</author>
      <author>Ghosh, Shaon</author>
      <author>Giaime, Joe A.</author>
      <author>Giardina, K.D.</author>
      <author>Giazotto, Adalberto</author>
      <author>Gill, Kiranjyot</author>
      <author>Glaefke, Andreas</author>
      <author>Goetz, Evan</author>
      <author>Goetz, Ryan</author>
      <author>Gondan, Laszlo</author>
      <author>González, Gabriela</author>
      <author>Gonzalez Castro, J.M.</author>
      <author>Gopakumar, A.</author>
      <author>Gorodetsky, Michael L.</author>
      <author>Gossan, Sarah E.</author>
      <author>Gosselin, M.</author>
      <author>Gouaty, Romain</author>
      <author>Grado, Aniello</author>
      <author>Graef, Christian</author>
      <author>Granata, Massimo</author>
      <author>Grant, Alastair</author>
      <author>Gras, Slawomir</author>
      <author>Gray, Corey</author>
      <author>Greco, Giuseppe</author>
      <author>Green, Anna C.</author>
      <author>Groot, Paul</author>
      <author>Grote, Hartmut</author>
      <author>Grunewald, Steffen</author>
      <author>Guidi, Gianluca M.</author>
      <author>Guo, Xiangyu</author>
      <author>Gupta, Anuradha</author>
      <author>Gupta, Manojipr K.</author>
      <author>Gushwa, Kaitlin E.</author>
      <author>Gustafson, Eric K.</author>
      <author>Gustafson, R.</author>
      <author>Hacker, Joshua J.</author>
      <author>Hagiwara, A.</author>
      <author>Hall, Bernard R.</author>
      <author>Hall, Evan D.</author>
      <author>Hammond, Giles</author>
      <author>Haney, Maria</author>
      <author>Hanke, Manuela M.</author>
      <author>Hanks, Jonathan</author>
      <author>Hanna, Chad</author>
      <author>Hannam, Mark D.</author>
      <author>Hanson, Joe</author>
      <author>Hardwick, Terra</author>
      <author>Harms, Jan</author>
      <author>Harry, Gregg M.</author>
      <author>Harry, Ian W.</author>
      <author>Hart, Martin J.</author>
      <author>Hartman, Michael T.</author>
      <author>Haster, C.-J.</author>
      <author>Haughian, Karen</author>
      <author>Hayama, K.</author>
      <author>Healy, James</author>
      <author>Heidmann, Antoine</author>
      <author>Heintze, Matthew C.</author>
      <author>Heitmann, Henrich</author>
      <author>Hello, Patrice</author>
      <author>Hemming, Gary</author>
      <author>Hendry, Martin</author>
      <author>Heng, I.S.</author>
      <author>Hennig, J.</author>
      <author>Henry, Jackson</author>
      <author>Heptonstall, Alastair W.</author>
      <author>Heurs, Michele</author>
      <author>Hild, Stefan</author>
      <author>Hirose, E.</author>
      <author>Hoak, Daniel</author>
      <author>Hofman, David</author>
      <author>Holt, Kathy</author>
      <author>Holz, Daniel E.</author>
      <author>Hopkins, Paul</author>
      <author>Hough, James</author>
      <author>Houston, Ewan A.</author>
      <author>Howell, Eric J.</author>
      <author>Hu, Yiming M.</author>
      <author>Huerta, Eliu A.</author>
      <author>Huet, Dominique</author>
      <author>Hughey, Brennan</author>
      <author>Husa, Sascha</author>
      <author>Huttner, Sabina H.</author>
      <author>Huynh-Dinh, T.</author>
      <author>Indik, Nathaniel</author>
      <author>Ingram, Dale R.</author>
      <author>Inta, Ra</author>
      <author>Ioka, K.</author>
      <author>Isa, Hafizah N.</author>
      <author>Isac, J.-M.</author>
      <author>Isi, Max</author>
      <author>Isogai, Tomoki</author>
      <author>Itoh, Y.</author>
      <author>Iyer, Bala R.</author>
      <author>Izumi, Kiwamu</author>
      <author>Jacqmin, Thibaut</author>
      <author>Jani, Karan</author>
      <author>Jaranowski, Piotr</author>
      <author>Jawahar, Sharat</author>
      <author>Jiménez-Forteza, F.</author>
      <author>Johnson, Warren W.</author>
      <author>Jones, D.I.</author>
      <author>Jones, Russell</author>
      <author>Jonker, Reinier J.G.</author>
      <author>Ju, L.</author>
      <author>Junker, Jonas</author>
      <author>Kagawa, T.</author>
      <author>Kajita, T.</author>
      <author>Kakizaki, M.</author>
      <author>Kalaghatgi, Chinmay V.</author>
      <author>Kalogera, Vassiliki</author>
      <author>Kamiizumi, M.</author>
      <author>Kanda, N.</author>
      <author>Kandhasamy, Shivaraj</author>
      <author>Kanemura, S.</author>
      <author>Kaneyama, M.</author>
      <author>Kang, Gungwon</author>
      <author>Kanner, Jonah B.</author>
      <author>Karki, Sudarshan</author>
      <author>Karvinen, Kai S.</author>
      <author>Kasprzack, Marie</author>
      <author>Kataoka, Y.</author>
      <author>Katsavounidis, Erik</author>
      <author>Katzman, William</author>
      <author>Kaufer, Steffen</author>
      <author>Kaur, Tejinder</author>
      <author>Kawabe, Keita</author>
      <author>Kawai, N.</author>
      <author>Kawamura, S.</author>
      <author>Kéfélian, Fabien</author>
      <author>Keitel, David</author>
      <author>Kelley, David B.</author>
      <author>Kennedy, Ross</author>
      <author>Key, Joey S.</author>
      <author>Khalili, Farit Y.</author>
      <author>Khan, I.</author>
      <author>Khan, Sebastian</author>
      <author>Khan, Ziauddin</author>
      <author>Khazanov, Efim A.</author>
      <author>Kijbunchoo, Nutsinee</author>
      <author>Kim, C.</author>
      <author>Kim, H.</author>
      <author>Kim, Jeongcho C.</author>
      <author>Kim, J.</author>
      <author>Kim, Won</author>
      <author>Kim, Y.-M.</author>
      <author>Kimbrell, Seth J.</author>
      <author>Kimura, N.</author>
      <author>King, Eleanor J.</author>
      <author>King, Peter J.</author>
      <author>Kirchhoff, Robin</author>
      <author>Kissel, Jeffrey S.</author>
      <author>Klein, Brian</author>
      <author>Kleybolte, Lisa</author>
      <author>Klimenko, Sergei</author>
      <author>Koch, Philip</author>
      <author>Koehlenbeck, Sina M.</author>
      <author>Kojima, Y.</author>
      <author>Kokeyama, K.</author>
      <author>Koley, S.</author>
      <author>Komori, K.</author>
      <author>Kondrashov, Veronica</author>
      <author>Kontos, Antonios</author>
      <author>Korobko, Mikhail</author>
      <author>Korth, William Z.</author>
      <author>Kotake, K.</author>
      <author>Kowalska, Izabela</author>
      <author>Kozak, Dan B.</author>
      <author>Krämer, Christina</author>
      <author>Kringel, Volker</author>
      <author>Krishnan, Badri</author>
      <author>Królak, Andrzej</author>
      <author>Kuehn, Gerrit</author>
      <author>Kumar, Prayush</author>
      <author>Kumar, Rahul</author>
      <author>Kumar, Rakesh</author>
      <author>Kuo, L.</author>
      <author>Kuroda, K.</author>
      <author>Kutynia, Adam</author>
      <author>Kuwahara, Y.</author>
      <author>Lackey, Benjamin D.</author>
      <author>Landry, Michael</author>
      <author>Lang, Ryan N.</author>
      <author>Lange, Jacob</author>
      <author>Lantz, Brian</author>
      <author>Lanza, Robert K.</author>
      <author>Lartaux-Vollard, A.</author>
      <author>Lasky, Paul D.</author>
      <author>Laxen, Michael</author>
      <author>Lazzarini, Albert</author>
      <author>Lazzaro, Claudia</author>
      <author>Leaci, Paola</author>
      <author>Leavey, Sean</author>
      <author>Lebigot, E.O.</author>
      <author>Lee, C.H.</author>
      <author>Lee, Hyunkyu K.</author>
      <author>Lee, H.M.</author>
      <author>Lee, H.W.</author>
      <author>Lee, K.</author>
      <author>Lehmann, Johannes</author>
      <author>Lenon, Amber</author>
      <author>Leonardi, Matteo</author>
      <author>Leong, Jonathan R.</author>
      <author>Leroy, Nicolas</author>
      <author>Letendre, Nicolas</author>
      <author>Levin, Yuri</author>
      <author>Li, Tjonnie G.F.</author>
      <author>Libson, Adam</author>
      <author>Littenberg, Tyson B.</author>
      <author>Liu, J.</author>
      <author>Lockerbie, Nick A.</author>
      <author>Lombardi, Alexander L.</author>
      <author>London, Lionel T.</author>
      <author>Lord, Jaysin E.</author>
      <author>Lorenzini, Matteo</author>
      <author>Loriette, Vincent</author>
      <author>Lormand, Marc</author>
      <author>Losurdo, Giovanni</author>
      <author>Lough, James D.</author>
      <author>Lousto, Carlos O.</author>
      <author>Lovelace, Geoffrey</author>
      <author>Lück, Harald</author>
      <author>Lundgren, Andrew P.</author>
      <author>Lynch, Ryan</author>
      <author>Ma, Y.</author>
      <author>Macfoy, Sean</author>
      <author>Machenschalk, Bernd</author>
      <author>MacInnis, M.</author>
      <author>Macleod, Duncan M.</author>
      <author>Magaña-Sandoval, F.</author>
      <author>Majorana, Ettore</author>
      <author>Maksimovic, Ivan</author>
      <author>Malvezzi, Valeria</author>
      <author>Man, N.</author>
      <author>Mandic, Vuk</author>
      <author>Mangano, Valentina</author>
      <author>Mano, S.</author>
      <author>Mansell, Georgia L.</author>
      <author>Manske, Michael</author>
      <author>Mantovani, Maddalena</author>
      <author>Marchesoni, Fabio</author>
      <author>Marchio, M.</author>
      <author>Marion, Frederique</author>
      <author>Márka, Szabolcs</author>
      <author>Márka, Zsuzsanna</author>
      <author>Markosyan, Ashot S.</author>
      <author>Maros, Ed</author>
      <author>Martelli, Filippo</author>
      <author>Martellini, Lionel</author>
      <author>Martin, Ian W.</author>
      <author>Martynov, Denis V.</author>
      <author>Mason, Ken</author>
      <author>Masserot, Alain</author>
      <author>Massinger, Thomas J.</author>
      <author>Masso-Reid, M.</author>
      <author>Mastrogiovanni, Simone</author>
      <author>Matichard, Fabrice</author>
      <author>Matone, Luca</author>
      <author>Matsumoto, N.</author>
      <author>Matsushima, F.</author>
      <author>Mavalvala, Nergis</author>
      <author>Mazumder, Nairwita</author>
      <author>McCarthy, R.</author>
      <author>McClelland, D.E.</author>
      <author>McCormick, S.</author>
      <author>McGrath, C.</author>
      <author>McGuire, S.C.</author>
      <author>McIntyre, G.</author>
      <author>McIver, J.</author>
      <author>McManus, David J.</author>
      <author>McRae, T.</author>
      <author>McWilliams, S.T.</author>
      <author>Meacher, Duncan</author>
      <author>Meadors, Grant D.</author>
      <author>Meidam, Jeroen</author>
      <author>Melatos, Andrew</author>
      <author>Mendell, Gregory</author>
      <author>Mendoza-Gandara, D.</author>
      <author>Mercer, R.A.</author>
      <author>Merilh, Edmond L.</author>
      <author>Merzougui, Mourad</author>
      <author>Meshkov, Syd</author>
      <author>Messenger, Chris</author>
      <author>Messick, Cody</author>
      <author>Metzdorff, R.</author>
      <author>Meyers, Patrick M.</author>
      <author>Mezzani, F.</author>
      <author>Miao, Haixing</author>
      <author>Michel, Christophe</author>
      <author>Michimura, Y.</author>
      <author>Middleton, Hannah</author>
      <author>Mikhailov, Eugeniy E.</author>
      <author>Milano, Leopoldo</author>
      <author>Miller, Andrewlawrence L.</author>
      <author>Miller, Avery</author>
      <author>Miller, Brandon B.</author>
      <author>Miller, John</author>
      <author>Millhouse, Meg</author>
      <author>Minenkov, Yuri</author>
      <author>Ming, Jing</author>
      <author>Mirshekari, Saeed</author>
      <author>Mishra, Chandra</author>
      <author>Mitrofanov, Valery P.</author>
      <author>Mitselmakher, Guenakh</author>
      <author>Mittleman, Richard</author>
      <author>Miyakawa, O.</author>
      <author>Miyamoto, A.</author>
      <author>Miyamoto, T.</author>
      <author>Miyoki, S.</author>
      <author>Moggi, A.</author>
      <author>Mohan, Martin</author>
      <author>Mohapatra, S.R.P.</author>
      <author>Montani, Matteo</author>
      <author>Moore, Blake C.</author>
      <author>Moore, Christopher J.</author>
      <author>Moraru, Dan</author>
      <author>Moreno, Gerardo</author>
      <author>Morii, W.</author>
      <author>Morisaki, S.</author>
      <author>Moriwaki, Y.</author>
      <author>Morriss, Sean R.</author>
      <author>Mours, Benoit</author>
      <author>Mow-Lowry, C.M.</author>
      <author>Mueller, Guido</author>
      <author>Muir, Alistair W.</author>
      <author>Mukherjee, Arunava</author>
      <author>Mukherjee, Debnandini</author>
      <author>Mukherjee, Soma</author>
      <author>Mukund, Nikhil</author>
      <author>Mullavey, Adam</author>
      <author>Munch, Jesper</author>
      <author>Muniz, Erik A.M.</author>
      <author>Murray, Peter G.</author>
      <author>Mytidis, Antonis</author>
      <author>Nagano, S.</author>
      <author>Nakamura, K.</author>
      <author>Nakamura, T.</author>
      <author>Nakano, H.</author>
      <author>Nakano, Masaya</author>
      <author>Nakano, Masayuki</author>
      <author>Nakao, K.</author>
      <author>Napier, Kate</author>
      <author>Nardecchia, Ilaria</author>
      <author>Narikawa, T.</author>
      <author>Naticchioni, Luca</author>
      <author>Nelemans, Gijs</author>
      <author>Nelson, Timothy J.N.</author>
      <author>Neri, Martina</author>
      <author>Nery, Marina</author>
      <author>Neunzert, Ansel</author>
      <author>Newport, Jonathan M.</author>
      <author>Nguyen, Thanh T.</author>
      <author>Ni, W.-T.</author>
      <author>Nielsen, Alex B.</author>
      <author>Nissanke, Samaya</author>
      <author>Nitz, Alex</author>
      <author>Noack, Andreas</author>
      <author>Nocera, Flavio</author>
      <author>Nolting, David</author>
      <author>Normandin, Marc E.N.</author>
      <author>Nuttall, Laura K.</author>
      <author>Oberling, Jason</author>
      <author>Ochsner, Evan</author>
      <author>Oelker, Eric</author>
      <author>Ogin, Greg H.</author>
      <author>Oh, John J.</author>
      <author>Oh, Sanghoon H.</author>
      <author>Ohashi, M.</author>
      <author>Ohishi, N.</author>
      <author>Ohkawa, M.</author>
      <author>Ohme, Frank</author>
      <author>Okutomi, K.</author>
      <author>Oliver, Miquel</author>
      <author>Ono, K.</author>
      <author>Ono, Y.</author>
      <author>Oohara, K.</author>
      <author>Oppermann, Patrick</author>
      <author>Oram, Richard J.</author>
      <author>O'Reilly, B.</author>
      <author>O'Shaughnessy, R.</author>
      <author>Ottaway, David J.</author>
      <author>Overmier, Harry</author>
      <author>Owen, Ben J.</author>
      <author>Pace, Alexander E.</author>
      <author>Page, Jessica</author>
      <author>Pai, Archana</author>
      <author>Pai, Siddhesh A.</author>
      <author>Palamos, Jordan R.</author>
      <author>Palashov, Oleg</author>
      <author>Palomba, Cristiano</author>
      <author>Pal-Singh, A.</author>
      <author>Pan, H.</author>
      <author>Pankow, Chris</author>
      <author>Pannarale, Francesco</author>
      <author>Pant, Brijesh C.</author>
      <author>Paoletti, Federico</author>
      <author>Paoli, Andrea</author>
      <author>Papa, Maria A.</author>
      <author>Paris, Hugo R.</author>
      <author>Parker, William</author>
      <author>Pascucci, Daniela</author>
      <author>Pasqualetti, Antonio</author>
      <author>Passaquieti, Roberto</author>
      <author>Passuello, Diego</author>
      <author>Patricelli, Barbara</author>
      <author>Pearlstone, Brynley L.</author>
      <author>Pedraza, Mike</author>
      <author>Pedurand, Richard</author>
      <author>Pekowsky, Larne</author>
      <author>Pele, Arnaud</author>
      <author>Peña Arellano, F.E.</author>
      <author>Penn, Steven</author>
      <author>Perez, Carlos J.</author>
      <author>Perreca, Antonio</author>
      <author>Perri, Leah M.</author>
      <author>Pfeiffer, Harald P.</author>
      <author>Phelps, Margot</author>
      <author>Piccinni, Ornella J.</author>
      <author>Pichot, Mikhael</author>
      <author>Piergiovanni, Francesco</author>
      <author>Pierro, Vincenzo</author>
      <author>Pillant, Gabriel</author>
      <author>Pinard, Laurent</author>
      <author>Pinto, Innocenzo M.</author>
      <author>Pitkin, Matthew</author>
      <author>Poe, Mark</author>
      <author>Poggiani, Rosa</author>
      <author>Popolizio, Pasquale</author>
      <author>Post, Alexander</author>
      <author>Powell, Jade</author>
      <author>Prasad, Jayanti</author>
      <author>Pratt, James W.W.</author>
      <author>Predoi, Valeriu</author>
      <author>Prestegard, Tanner</author>
      <author>Prijatelj, Mirko</author>
      <author>Principe, Maria</author>
      <author>Privitera, Stephen</author>
      <author>Prodi, Giovanni A.</author>
      <author>Prokhorov, Leonid G.</author>
      <author>Puncken, Oliver</author>
      <author>Punturo, Michele</author>
      <author>Puppo, Paola</author>
      <author>Pürrer, Michael</author>
      <author>Qi, Hong</author>
      <author>Qin, Jiayi</author>
      <author>Qiu, Shi</author>
      <author>Quetschke, Volker</author>
      <author>Quintero, Eric A.</author>
      <author>Quitzow-James, R.</author>
      <author>Raab, Fred J.</author>
      <author>Rabeling, David S.</author>
      <author>Radkins, Hugh</author>
      <author>Raffai, Peter</author>
      <author>Raja, Sendhil</author>
      <author>Rajan, C.</author>
      <author>Rakhmanov, Malik</author>
      <author>Rapagnani, Piero</author>
      <author>Raymond, Vivien</author>
      <author>Razzano, Massimiliano</author>
      <author>Re, Virginia</author>
      <author>Read, Jocelyn</author>
      <author>Regimbau, Tania</author>
      <author>Rei, Luca</author>
      <author>Reid, Stuart</author>
      <author>Reitze, David H.</author>
      <author>Rew, Hunter</author>
      <author>Reyes, Steven D.</author>
      <author>Rhoades, Elaine</author>
      <author>Ricci, Fulvio</author>
      <author>Riles, Keith</author>
      <author>Rizzo, Monica</author>
      <author>Robertson, Norna A.</author>
      <author>Robie, Raymond</author>
      <author>Robinet, Florent</author>
      <author>Rocchi, Alessio</author>
      <author>Rolland, Loic</author>
      <author>Rollins, Jameson G.</author>
      <author>Roma, Vincent J.</author>
      <author>Romano, Rocco</author>
      <author>Romie, Janeen H.</author>
      <author>Rosińska, Dorota</author>
      <author>Rowan, Sheila</author>
      <author>Rüdiger, Albrecht</author>
      <author>Ruggi, Paolo</author>
      <author>Ryan, Kyle</author>
      <author>Sachdev, Surabhi</author>
      <author>Sadecki, Travis</author>
      <author>Sadeghian, Laleh</author>
      <author>Sago, N.</author>
      <author>Saijo, M.</author>
      <author>Saito, Y.</author>
      <author>Sakai, K.</author>
      <author>Sakellariadou, Mairi</author>
      <author>Salconi, Livio</author>
      <author>Saleem, Muhammed</author>
      <author>Salemi, Francesco</author>
      <author>Samajdar, Anuradha</author>
      <author>Sammut, Letizia</author>
      <author>Sampson, Laura M.</author>
      <author>Sanchez, Eduardo J.</author>
      <author>Sandberg, Vernon</author>
      <author>Sanders, Jaclyn R.</author>
      <author>Sasaki, Y.</author>
      <author>Sassolas, Benoit</author>
      <author>Sathyaprakash, B.S.</author>
      <author>Sato, S.</author>
      <author>Sato, T.</author>
      <author>Saulson, Peter R.</author>
      <author>Sauter, Orion</author>
      <author>Savage, Richard L.</author>
      <author>Sawadsky, Andreas</author>
      <author>Schale, Paul</author>
      <author>Scheuer, Jacob</author>
      <author>Schmidt, Eric</author>
      <author>Schmidt, Justus</author>
      <author>Schmidt, Patricia</author>
      <author>Schnabel, Roman</author>
      <author>Schofield, Robert M.S.</author>
      <author>Schönbeck, Axel</author>
      <author>Schreiber, Emil</author>
      <author>Schuette, Dirk</author>
      <author>Schutz, Bernard F.</author>
      <author>Schwalbe, Sophia G.</author>
      <author>Scott, Jamie</author>
      <author>Scott, Susan M.</author>
      <author>Sekiguchi, T.</author>
      <author>Sekiguchi, Y.</author>
      <author>Sellers, Danny</author>
      <author>Sengupta, Anand S.</author>
      <author>Sentenac, Daniel</author>
      <author>Sequino, Valeria</author>
      <author>Sergeev, Alexander</author>
      <author>Setyawati, Yoshinta</author>
      <author>Shaddock, Daniel A.</author>
      <author>Shaffer, Thomas J.</author>
      <author>Shahriar, M.S.</author>
      <author>Shapiro, Brett</author>
      <author>Shawhan, Peter</author>
      <author>Sheperd, Alec</author>
      <author>Shibata, M.</author>
      <author>Shikano, Y.</author>
      <author>Shimoda, T.</author>
      <author>Shoda, A.</author>
      <author>Shoemaker, David H.</author>
      <author>Shoemaker, Deirdre M.</author>
      <author>Siellez, Karelle</author>
      <author>Siemens, Xavier</author>
      <author>Sieniawska, Magdalena</author>
      <author>Sigg, Daniel</author>
      <author>Silva, Allan D.</author>
      <author>Singer, Abe</author>
      <author>Singer, Leo P.</author>
      <author>Singh, Avneet</author>
      <author>Singh, Robinjeet</author>
      <author>Singhal, Akshat</author>
      <author>Sintes, Alicia M.</author>
      <author>Slagmolen, Bram J.J.</author>
      <author>Smith, Bryan</author>
      <author>Smith, Joshua R.</author>
      <author>Smith, Rory J.E.</author>
      <author>Somiya, K.</author>
      <author>Son, Edwin J.</author>
      <author>Sorazu, Borja</author>
      <author>Sorrentino, Fiodor</author>
      <author>Souradeep, Tarun</author>
      <author>Spencer, Andrew P.</author>
      <author>Srivastava, Amit K.</author>
      <author>Staley, Alexan</author>
      <author>Steinke, Michael</author>
      <author>Steinlechner, Jessica</author>
      <author>Steinlechner, Sebastian</author>
      <author>Steinmeyer, Daniel</author>
      <author>Stephens, Branson C.</author>
      <author>Stevenson, Simon P.</author>
      <author>Stone, Robert</author>
      <author>Strain, Ken A.</author>
      <author>Straniero, Nicolas</author>
      <author>Stratta, Giulia</author>
      <author>Strigin, Sergey E.</author>
      <author>Sturani, Riccardo</author>
      <author>Stuver, Amber L.</author>
      <author>Sugimoto, Y.</author>
      <author>Summerscales, Tiffany Z.</author>
      <author>Sun, Ling</author>
      <author>Sunil, S.</author>
      <author>Sutton, Patrick J.</author>
      <author>Suzuki, T.</author>
      <author>Swinkels, Bas L.</author>
      <author>Szczepańczyk, Marek J.</author>
      <author>Tacca, Matteo</author>
      <author>Tagoshi, H.</author>
      <author>Takada, S.</author>
      <author>Takahashi, H.</author>
      <author>Takahashi, R.</author>
      <author>Takamori, A.</author>
      <author>Talukder, Dipongkar</author>
      <author>Tanaka, H.</author>
      <author>Tanaka, K.</author>
      <author>Tanaka, T.</author>
      <author>Tanner, David B.</author>
      <author>Tápai, Marton</author>
      <author>Taracchini, Andrea</author>
      <author>Tatsumi, D.</author>
      <author>Taylor, Robert</author>
      <author>Telada, S.</author>
      <author>Theeg, Thomas</author>
      <author>Thomas, E.G.</author>
      <author>Thomas, Michael</author>
      <author>Thomas, Patrick</author>
      <author>Thorne, Keith A.</author>
      <author>Thrane, Eric</author>
      <author>Tippens, Tyler</author>
      <author>Tiwari, Shubhanshu</author>
      <author>Tiwari, Vaibhav</author>
      <author>Tokmakov, Kirill V.</author>
      <author>Toland, Karl</author>
      <author>Tomaru, T.</author>
      <author>Tomlinson, Clive</author>
      <author>Tonelli, Mauro</author>
      <author>Tornasi, Zeno</author>
      <author>Torrie, Calum I.</author>
      <author>Töyrä, Daniel</author>
      <author>Travasso, Flavio</author>
      <author>Traylor, Gary</author>
      <author>Trifirò, Daniele</author>
      <author>Trinastic, Jonathan</author>
      <author>Tringali, Maria C.</author>
      <author>Trozzo, Lucia</author>
      <author>Tse, Maggie</author>
      <author>Tso, Rhondale</author>
      <author>Tsubono, K.</author>
      <author>Tsuzuki, T.</author>
      <author>Turconi, M.</author>
      <author>Tuyenbayev, Darkhan</author>
      <author>Uchiyama, T.</author>
      <author>Uehara, T.</author>
      <author>Ueki, S.</author>
      <author>Ueno, K.</author>
      <author>Ugolini, Dennis</author>
      <author>Unnikrishnan, Cs S.</author>
      <author>Urban, Alexander L.</author>
      <author>Ushiba, T.</author>
      <author>Usman, Samantha A.</author>
      <author>Vahlbruch, Henning</author>
      <author>Vajente, Gabriele</author>
      <author>Valdes, Guillermo</author>
      <author>van Bakel, N.</author>
      <author>van Beuzekom, Martin</author>
      <author>van den Brand, J.F.J.</author>
      <author>Van Den Broeck, C.</author>
      <author>Vander-Hyde, D.C.</author>
      <author>van der Schaaf, L.</author>
      <author>van Heijningen, J.V.</author>
      <author>van Putten, M.H.P.M.</author>
      <author>van Veggel, A.A.</author>
      <author>Vardaro, M.</author>
      <author>Varma, Vijay</author>
      <author>Vass, Steve</author>
      <author>Vasúth, Matyas</author>
      <author>Vecchio, Alberto</author>
      <author>Vedovato, Gabriele</author>
      <author>Veitch, John</author>
      <author>Veitch, Peter J.</author>
      <author>Venkateswara, Krishna</author>
      <author>Venugopalan, Gautam</author>
      <author>Verkindt, Didier</author>
      <author>Vetrano, Flavio</author>
      <author>Viceré, Andrea</author>
      <author>Viets, Aaron D.</author>
      <author>Vinciguerra, Serena</author>
      <author>Vine, David J.</author>
      <author>Vinet, J.-Y.</author>
      <author>Vitale, Salvatore</author>
      <author>Vo, Thomas</author>
      <author>Vocca, Helios</author>
      <author>Vorvick, Cheryl</author>
      <author>Voss, D.V.</author>
      <author>Vousden, Will D.</author>
      <author>Vyatchanin, Sergey P.</author>
      <author>Wade, Andrew R.</author>
      <author>Wade, Leslie E.</author>
      <author>Wade, Madeline</author>
      <author>Wakamatsu, T.</author>
      <author>Walker, Marissa</author>
      <author>Wallace, Larry</author>
      <author>Walsh, Sinead</author>
      <author>Wang, Gang</author>
      <author>Wang, Haoyu</author>
      <author>Wang, Mengyao</author>
      <author>Wang, Yan</author>
      <author>Ward, Robert L.</author>
      <author>Warner, Jim</author>
      <author>Was, Michal</author>
      <author>Watchi, Jennifer</author>
      <author>Weaver, Betsy</author>
      <author>Wei, L.-W.</author>
      <author>Weinert, Michael</author>
      <author>Weinstein, Alan J.</author>
      <author>Weiss, Rainer</author>
      <author>Wen, Linqing</author>
      <author>Weßels, Peter</author>
      <author>Westphal, Tobias</author>
      <author>Wette, Karl</author>
      <author>Whelan, John T.</author>
      <author>Whiting, Bernard F.</author>
      <author>Whittle, Chris</author>
      <author>Williams, Daniel</author>
      <author>Williams, Roy D.</author>
      <author>Williamson, Andrew R.</author>
      <author>Willis, Joshua L.</author>
      <author>Willke, Benno</author>
      <author>Wimmer, Maximilian H.</author>
      <author>Winkler, Walter</author>
      <author>Wipf, Christopher C.</author>
      <author>Wittel, Holger</author>
      <author>Woan, Graham</author>
      <author>Woehler, Janis</author>
      <author>Worden, John</author>
      <author>Wright, Jennifer L.</author>
      <author>Wu, David S.</author>
      <author>Wu, Guimin</author>
      <author>Yam, William</author>
      <author>Yamamoto, Hiro</author>
      <author>Yamamoto, K.</author>
      <author>Yamamoto, T.</author>
      <author>Yancey, Cregg C.</author>
      <author>Yano, K.</author>
      <author>Yap, M.J.</author>
      <author>Yokoyama, J.</author>
      <author>Yokozawa, T.</author>
      <author>Yoon, T.H.</author>
      <author>Yu, Hang</author>
      <author>Yu, Haocun</author>
      <author>Yuzurihara, H.</author>
      <author>Yvert, Michel</author>
      <author>Zadrożny, Adam</author>
      <author>Zangrando, Lisa</author>
      <author>Zanolin, Michele</author>
      <author>Zeidler, S.</author>
      <author>Zendri, J.-P.</author>
      <author>Zevin, Michael</author>
      <author>Zhang, Liyuan</author>
      <author>Zhang, Mi</author>
      <author>Zhang, Teng</author>
      <author>Zhang, Yuanhao</author>
      <author>Zhao, Chunnong</author>
      <author>Zhou, Minchuan</author>
      <author>Zhou, Zifan</author>
      <author>Zhu, Sylvia J.</author>
      <author>Zhu, Xingjiang J.</author>
      <author>Zucker, Michael E.</author>
      <author>Zweizig, John</author>
    </authors>
  </contributors>
  <titles>
    <title>Prospects for Observing and Localizing Gravitational-Wave Transients with Advanced LIGO, Advanced Virgo and KAGRA</title>
    <secondary-title>Living Rev.Rel.</secondary-title>
  </titles>
  <electronic-resource-num>10.1007/lrr-2016-1</electronic-resource-num>
  <pages>1</pages>
  <volume>19</volume>
  <number/>
  <dates>
    <year>2016</year>
  </dates>
  <abstract>We present possible observing scenarios for the Advanced LIGO, Advanced Virgo and KAGRA gravitational-wave detectors over the next decade, with the intention of providing information to the astronomy community to facilitate planning for multi-messenger astronomy with gravitational waves. We estimate the sensitivity of the network to transient gravitational-wave signals, and study the capability of the network to determine the sky location of the source. We report our findings for gravitational-wave transients, with particular focus on gravitational-wave signals from the inspiral of binary neutron star systems, which are the most promising targets for multi-messenger astronomy. The ability to localize the sources of the detected signals depends on the geographical distribution of the detectors and their relative sensitivity, and 90% credible regions can be as large as thousands of square degrees when only two sensitive detectors are operational. Determining the sky position of a significant fraction of detected signals to areas of 5-20 square degrees requires at least three detectors of sensitivity within a factor of ~2 of each other and with a broad frequency bandwidth. When all detectors, including KAGRA and the third LIGO detector in India, reach design sensitivity, a significant fraction of gravitational-wave signals will be localized to a few square degrees by gravitational-wave observations alone.</abstract>
</record>

<record>
  <contributors>
    <authors>
      <author>Gair, Jonathan R.</author>
      <author>Vallisneri, Michele</author>
      <author>Larson, Shane L.</author>
      <author>Baker, John G.</author>
    </authors>
  </contributors>
  <titles>
    <title>Testing General Relativity with Low-Frequency, Space-Based Gravitational-Wave Detectors</title>
    <secondary-title>Living Rev.Rel.</secondary-title>
  </titles>
  <electronic-resource-num>10.12942/lrr-2013-7</electronic-resource-num>
  <pages>7</pages>
  <volume>16</volume>
  <number/>
  <keywords>
    <keyword>eLISA</keyword>
    <keyword>data analysis</keyword>
    <keyword>general relativity</keyword>
    <keyword>gravitation</keyword>
    <keyword>black holes</keyword>
    <keyword>gravitational waves</keyword>
    <keyword>LISA</keyword>
  </keywords>
  <dates>
    <year>2013</year>
    <pub-dates>
      <date>2013</date>
    </pub-dates>
  </dates>
  <abstract>We review the tests of general relativity that will become possible with space-based gravitational-wave detectors operating in the ~ 10^{-5} - 1 Hz low-frequency band. The fundamental aspects of gravitation that can be tested include the presence of additional gravitational fields other than the metric the number and tensorial nature of gravitational-wave polarization states the velocity of propagation of gravitational waves the binding energy and gravitational-wave radiation of binaries, and therefore the time evolution of binary inspirals the strength and shape of the waves emitted from binary mergers and ringdowns the true nature of astrophysical black holes and much more. The strength of this science alone calls for the swift implementation of a space-based detector the remarkable richness of astrophysics, astronomy, and cosmology in the low-frequency gravitational-wave band make the case even stronger.</abstract>
</record>

<record>
  <contributors>
    <authors>
      <author>Amendola, Luca</author>
      <author>Group, Euclid Theory Working</author>
      <author>Bacon, David</author>
      <author>Baker, Tessa</author>
      <author>Baldi, Marco</author>
      <author>Bartolo, Nicola</author>
      <author>Blanchard, Alain</author>
      <author>Bonvin, Camille</author>
      <author>Borgani, Stefano</author>
      <author>Branchini, Enzo</author>
      <author>Burrage, Clare</author>
      <author>Camera, Stefano</author>
      <author>Carbone, Carmelita</author>
      <author>Casarini, Luciano</author>
      <author>Cropper, Mark</author>
      <author>de Rham, Claudia</author>
      <author>di Porto, Cinzia</author>
      <author>Ealet, Anne</author>
      <author>Ferreira, Pedro G.</author>
      <author>Finelli, Fabio</author>
      <author>Garcia-Bellido, Juan</author>
      <author>Giannantonio, Tommaso</author>
      <author>Guzzo, Luigi</author>
      <author>Heavens, Alan</author>
      <author>Heisenberg, Lavinia</author>
      <author>Heymans, Catherine</author>
      <author>Hoekstra, Henk</author>
      <author>Hollenstein, Lukas</author>
      <author>Holmes, Rory</author>
      <author>Horst, Ole</author>
      <author>Jahnke, Knud</author>
      <author>Kitching, Thomas D.</author>
      <author>Koivisto, Tomi</author>
      <author>Kunz, Martin</author>
      <author>La Vacca, Giuseppe</author>
      <author>March, Marisa</author>
      <author>Majerotto, Elisabetta</author>
      <author>Markovic, Katarina</author>
      <author>Marsh, David</author>
      <author>Marulli, Federico</author>
      <author>Massey, Richard</author>
      <author>Mellier, Yannick</author>
      <author>Mota, David F.</author>
      <author>Nunes, Nelson</author>
      <author>Percival, Will</author>
      <author>Pettorino, Valeria</author>
      <author>Porciani, Cristiano</author>
      <author>Quercellini, Claudia</author>
      <author>Read, Justin</author>
      <author>Rinaldi, Massimiliano</author>
      <author>Sapone, Domenico</author>
      <author>Scaramella, Roberto</author>
      <author>Skordis, Constantinos</author>
      <author>Simpson, Fergus</author>
      <author>Taylor, Andy</author>
      <author>Thomas, Shaun</author>
      <author>Trotta, Roberto</author>
      <author>Verde, Licia</author>
      <author>Vernizzi, Filippo</author>
      <author>Vollmer, Adrian</author>
      <author>Wang, Yun</author>
      <author>Weller, Jochen</author>
      <author>Zlosnik, Tom</author>
    </authors>
  </contributors>
  <titles>
    <title>Cosmology and fundamental physics with the Euclid satellite</title>
    <secondary-title>Living Rev.Rel.</secondary-title>
  </titles>
  <electronic-resource-num>10.12942/lrr-2013-6</electronic-resource-num>
  <pages>6</pages>
  <volume>16</volume>
  <number/>
  <keywords>
    <keyword>cosmology</keyword>
    <keyword>dark energy</keyword>
    <keyword>galaxy evolution</keyword>
  </keywords>
  <dates>
    <year>2013</year>
    <pub-dates>
      <date>2013</date>
    </pub-dates>
  </dates>
  <abstract>&lt;p class="abstract"&gt;Euclid is a European Space Agency medium-class mission selected for launch in 2019 within the Cosmic Vision 2015-2025 program. The main goal of Euclid is to understand the origin of the accelerated expansion of the universe. Euclid will explore the expansion history of the universe and the evolution of cosmic structures by measuring shapes and red-shifts of galaxies as well as the distribution of clusters of galaxies over a large fraction of the sky.</abstract>
</record>

<record>
  <contributors>
    <authors>
      <author>Chrusciel, Piotr T.</author>
      <author>Lopes Costa, Joao</author>
      <author>Heusler, Markus</author>
    </authors>
  </contributors>
  <titles>
    <title>Stationary Black Holes: Uniqueness and Beyond</title>
    <secondary-title>Living Rev.Rel.</secondary-title>
  </titles>
  <electronic-resource-num>10.12942/lrr-2012-7</electronic-resource-num>
  <pages>7</pages>
  <volume>15</volume>
  <number/>
  <keywords>
    <keyword>self-gravitating classical fields</keyword>
    <keyword>black holes</keyword>
    <keyword>uniqueness theorems</keyword>
  </keywords>
  <dates>
    <year>2012</year>
  </dates>
  <abstract>The spectrum of known black-hole solutions to the stationary Einstein equations has been steadily increasing, sometimes in unexpected ways. In particular, it has turned out that not all black-hole-equilibrium configurations are characterized by their mass, angular momentum and global charges. Moreover, the high degree of symmetry displayed by vacuum and electro-vacuum black-hole spacetimes ceases to exist in self-gravitating non-linear field theories. This text aims to review some developments in the subject and to discuss them in light of the uniqueness theorem for the Einstein-Maxwell system.</abstract>
</record>

<record>
  <contributors>
    <authors>
      <author>Perez, Alejandro</author>
    </authors>
  </contributors>
  <titles>
    <title>The Spin Foam Approach to Quantum Gravity</title>
    <secondary-title>Living Rev.Rel.</secondary-title>
  </titles>
  <electronic-resource-num>10.12942/lrr-2013-3</electronic-resource-num>
  <pages>3</pages>
  <volume>16</volume>
  <number/>
  <keywords>
    <keyword>Quantum gravity</keyword>
  </keywords>
  <dates>
    <year>2013</year>
    <pub-dates>
      <date>2013</date>
    </pub-dates>
  </dates>
  <abstract>This article reviews the present status of the spin-foam approach to the quantization of gravity. Special attention is payed to the pedagogical presentation of the recently-introduced new models for four-dimensional quantum gravity. The models are motivated by a suitable implementation of the path integral quantization of the Plebanski formulation of gravity on a simplicial regularization. The article also includes a self contained treatment of 2+1 gravity. The simple nature of the latter provides the basis and a perspective for the analysis of both conceptual and technical issues that remain open in four dimensions.</abstract>
</record>

<record>
  <contributors>
    <authors>
      <author>Faber, Joshua A.</author>
      <author>Rasio, Frederic A.</author>
    </authors>
  </contributors>
  <titles>
    <title>Binary Neutron Star Mergers</title>
    <secondary-title>Living Rev.Rel.</secondary-title>
  </titles>
  <electronic-resource-num>10.12942/lrr-2012-8</electronic-resource-num>
  <pages>8</pages>
  <volume>15</volume>
  <number/>
  <keywords>
    <keyword>Neutron stars</keyword>
    <keyword>General relativity</keyword>
    <keyword>Binary neutron stars</keyword>
    <keyword>Coalescing binaries</keyword>
    <keyword>Numerical relativity</keyword>
  </keywords>
  <dates>
    <year>2012</year>
  </dates>
  <abstract>We review the current status of studies of the coalescence of binary neutron star systems. We begin with a discussion of the formation channels of merging binaries and we discuss the most recent theoretical predictions for merger rates. Next, we turn to the quasi-equilibrium formalisms that are used to study binaries prior to the merger phase and to generate initial data for fully dynamical simulations. The quasi-equilibrium approximation has played a key role in developing our understanding of the physics of binary coalescence and, in particular, of the orbital instability processes that can drive binaries to merger at the end of their lifetimes. We then turn to the numerical techniques used in dynamical simulations, including relativistic formalisms, (magneto-)hydrodynamics, gravitational-wave extraction techniques, and nuclear microphysics treatments. This is followed by a summary of the simulations performed across the field to date, including the most recent results from both fully relativistic and microphysically detailed simulations. Finally, we discuss the likely directions for the field as we transition from the first to the second generation of gravitational-wave interferometers and while supercomputers reach the petascale frontier.</abstract>
</record>

<record>
  <contributors>
    <authors>
      <author>Sarbach, Olivier</author>
      <author>Tiglio, Manuel</author>
    </authors>
  </contributors>
  <titles>
    <title>Continuum and Discrete Initial-Boundary-Value Problems and Einstein's Field Equations</title>
    <secondary-title>Living Rev.Rel.</secondary-title>
  </titles>
  <electronic-resource-num>10.12942/lrr-2012-9</electronic-resource-num>
  <pages>9</pages>
  <volume>15</volume>
  <number/>
  <keywords>
    <keyword>Partial differential equations</keyword>
    <keyword>Boundary value problems</keyword>
  </keywords>
  <dates>
    <year>2012</year>
  </dates>
  <abstract>Many evolution problems in physics are described by partial differential equations on an infinite domain; therefore, one is interested in the solutions to such problems for a given initial dataset. A prominent example is the binary black hole problem within Einstein's theory of gravitation, in which one computes the gravitational radiation emitted from the inspiral of the two black holes, merger and ringdown. Powerful mathematical tools can be used to establish qualitative statements about the solutions, such as their existence, uniqueness, continuous dependence on the initial data, or their asymptotic behavior over large time scales. However, one is often interested in computing the solution itself, and unless the partial differential equation is very simple, or the initial data possesses a high degree of symmetry, this computation requires approximation by numerical discretization. When solving such discrete problems on a machine, one is faced with a finite limit to computational resources, which leads to the replacement of the infinite continuum domain with a finite computer grid. This, in turn, leads to a discrete initial-boundary value problem. The hope is to recover, with high accuracy, the exact solution in the limit where the grid spacing converges to zero with the boundary being pushed to infinity. The goal of this article is to review some of the theory necessary to understand the continuum and discrete initial-boundary value problems arising from hyperbolic partial differential equations and to discuss its applications to numerical relativity; in particular, we present well-posed initial and initial-boundary value formulations of Einstein's equations, and we discuss multi-domain high-order finite difference and spectral methods to solve them.</abstract>
</record>

<record>
  <contributors>
    <authors>
      <author>Hossenfelder, Sabine</author>
    </authors>
  </contributors>
  <titles>
    <title>Minimal Length Scale Scenarios for Quantum Gravity</title>
    <secondary-title>Living Rev.Rel.</secondary-title>
  </titles>
  <electronic-resource-num>10.12942/lrr-2013-2</electronic-resource-num>
  <pages>2</pages>
  <volume>16</volume>
  <number/>
  <keywords>
    <keyword>Minimal length</keyword>
    <keyword>Quantum gravity</keyword>
    <keyword>Generalized uncertainty principle</keyword>
  </keywords>
  <dates>
    <year>2013</year>
    <pub-dates>
      <date>2013</date>
    </pub-dates>
  </dates>
  <abstract>We review the question of whether the fundamental laws of nature limit our ability to probe arbitrarily short distances. First, we examine what insights can be gained from thought experiments for probes of shortest distances, and summarize what can be learned from different approaches to a theory of quantum gravity. Then we discuss some models that have been developed to implement a minimal length scale in quantum mechanics and quantum field theory. These models have entered the literature as the generalized uncertainty principle or the modified dispersion relation, and have allowed the study of the effects of a minimal length scale in quantum mechanics, quantum electrodynamics, thermodynamics, black-hole physics and cosmology. Finally, we touch upon the question of ways to circumvent the manifestation of a minimal length scale in short-distance physics.</abstract>
</record>

<record>
  <contributors>
    <authors>
      <author>Compère, Geoffrey</author>
    </authors>
  </contributors>
  <titles>
    <title>The Kerr/CFT correspondence and its extensions</title>
    <secondary-title>Living Rev.Rel.</secondary-title>
  </titles>
  <electronic-resource-num>10.1007/s41114-017-0003-2</electronic-resource-num>
  <pages>11</pages>
  <volume>15</volume>
  <number>1</number>
  <keywords>
    <keyword>holography</keyword>
    <keyword>Black holes</keyword>
    <keyword>AdS/CFT</keyword>
    <keyword>conformal field theory</keyword>
    <keyword>Holography</keyword>
    <keyword>Conformal field theory</keyword>
  </keywords>
  <dates>
    <year>2012</year>
    <pub-dates>
      <date>2017-02-27</date>
    </pub-dates>
  </dates>
  <abstract>We present a first-principles derivation of the main results of the Kerr/CFT correspondence and its extensions using only tools from gravity and quantum field theory. Firstly, we review properties of extremal black holes with in particular the construction of an asymptotic Virasoro symmetry in the near-horizon limit. The entropy of extremal spinning or charged black holes is shown to match with a chiral half of Cardy's formula. Secondly, we show how a thermal 2-dimensional conformal field theory (CFT) is relevant to reproduce the dynamics of near-superradiant probes around near-extremal black holes in the semi-classical limit. Thirdly, we review the hidden conformal symmetries of asymptotically-flat black holes away from extremality and present how the non-extremal entropy can be matched with Cardy's formula. We follow an effective field theory approach and consider the Kerr-Newman black hole and its generalizations in various supergravity theories. The interpretation of these results by deformed dual conformal field theories is discussed and contrasted with properties of standard 2-dimensional CFTs. We conclude with a list of open problems.</abstract>
</record>

<record>
  <contributors>
    <authors>
      <author>Danilishin, Stefan L.</author>
      <author>Khalili, Farid Ya.</author>
    </authors>
  </contributors>
  <titles>
    <title>Quantum Measurement Theory in Gravitational-Wave Detectors</title>
    <secondary-title>Living Rev.Rel.</secondary-title>
  </titles>
  <electronic-resource-num>10.12942/lrr-2012-5</electronic-resource-num>
  <pages>5</pages>
  <volume>15</volume>
  <number/>
  <keywords>
    <keyword>gravitational-wave detectors</keyword>
    <keyword>quantum measurement theory</keyword>
    <keyword>squeezed light</keyword>
    <keyword>optical rigidity</keyword>
    <keyword>filter cavities</keyword>
    <keyword>back-action evasion</keyword>
    <keyword>quantum speed meter</keyword>
    <keyword>quantum non-demolition measurement</keyword>
    <keyword>standard quantum limit</keyword>
    <keyword>quantum noise</keyword>
  </keywords>
  <dates>
    <year>2012</year>
  </dates>
  <abstract>The fast progress in improving the sensitivity of the gravitational-wave (GW) detectors, we all have witnessed in the recent years, has propelled the scientific community to the point, when quantum behaviour of such immense measurement devices as kilometer-long interferometers starts to matter. The time, when their sensitivity will be mainly limited by the quantum noise of light is round the corner, and finding the ways to reduce it will become a necessity. Therefore, the primary goal we pursued in this review was to familiarize a broad spectrum of readers with the theory of quantum measurements in the very form it finds application in the area of gravitational-wave detection. We focus on how quantum noise arises in gravitational-wave interferometers and what limitations it imposes on the achievable sensitivity. We start from the very basic concepts and gradually advance to the general linear quantum measurement theory and its application to the calculation of quantum noise in the contemporary and planned interferometric detectors of gravitational radiation of the first and second generation. Special attention is paid to the concept of Standard Quantum Limit and the methods of its surmounting.</abstract>
</record>

<record>
  <contributors>
    <authors>
      <author>Liebling, Steven L.</author>
      <author>Palenzuela, Carlos</author>
    </authors>
  </contributors>
  <titles>
    <title>Dynamical Boson Stars</title>
    <secondary-title>Living Rev.Rel.</secondary-title>
  </titles>
  <electronic-resource-num>10.12942/lrr-2012-6</electronic-resource-num>
  <pages>6</pages>
  <volume>15</volume>
  <number>1</number>
  <keywords>
    <keyword>Boson stars</keyword>
    <keyword>Numerical relativity</keyword>
    <keyword>Solitons</keyword>
  </keywords>
  <dates>
    <year>2012</year>
    <pub-dates>
      <date>2017-11-13</date>
    </pub-dates>
  </dates>
  <abstract>The idea of stable, localized bundles of energy has strong appeal as a model for particles. In the 1950s John Wheeler envisioned such bundles as smooth configurations of electromagnetic energy that he called {\em geons}, but none were found. Instead, particle-like solutions were found in the late 1960s with the addition of a scalar field, and these were given the name {\em boson stars}. Since then, boson stars find use in a wide variety of models as sources of dark matter, as black hole mimickers, in simple models of binary systems, and as a tool in finding black holes in higher dimensions with only a single killing vector. We discuss important varieties of boson stars, their dynamic properties, and some of their uses, concentrating on recent efforts.</abstract>
</record>

<record>
  <contributors>
    <authors>
      <author>Famaey, Benoit</author>
      <author>McGaugh, Stacy</author>
    </authors>
  </contributors>
  <titles>
    <title>Modified Newtonian Dynamics (MOND): Observational Phenomenology and Relativistic Extensions</title>
    <secondary-title>Living Rev.Rel.</secondary-title>
  </titles>
  <electronic-resource-num>10.12942/lrr-2012-10</electronic-resource-num>
  <pages>10</pages>
  <volume>15</volume>
  <number/>
  <keywords>
    <keyword>astrophysics</keyword>
    <keyword>Newtonian limit</keyword>
    <keyword>cosmology</keyword>
    <keyword>astronomical observations</keyword>
    <keyword>extragalactic astronomy</keyword>
    <keyword>fundamental physics</keyword>
    <keyword>theories of gravity</keyword>
    <keyword>equations of motion</keyword>
  </keywords>
  <dates>
    <year>2012</year>
  </dates>
  <abstract>A wealth of astronomical data indicate the presence of mass discrepancies in the Universe. The motions observed in a variety of classes of extragalactic systems exceed what can be explained by the mass visible in stars and gas. Either (i) there is a vast amount of unseen mass in some novel form - dark matter - or (ii) the data indicate a breakdown of our understanding of dynamics on the relevant scales, or (iii) both. Here, we first review a few outstanding challenges for the dark matter interpretation of mass discrepancies in galaxies, purely based on observations and independently of any alternative theoretical framework. We then show that many of these puzzling observations are predicted by one single relation - Milgrom's law - involving an acceleration constant (or a characteristic surface density) of the order of the square-root of the cosmological constant in natural units. This relation can at present most easily be interpreted as the effect of a single universal force law resulting from a modification of Newtonian dynamics (MOND) on galactic scales. We exhaustively review the current observational successes and problems of this alternative paradigm at all astrophysical scales, and summarize the various theoretical attempts (TeVeS, GEA, BIMOND, and others) made to effectively embed this modification of Newtonian dynamics within a relativistic theory of gravity.</abstract>
</record>

<record>
  <contributors>
    <authors>
      <author>Benacquista, Matthew J.</author>
      <author>Downing, Jonathan M.B.</author>
    </authors>
  </contributors>
  <titles>
    <title>Relativistic Binaries in Globular Clusters</title>
    <secondary-title>Living Rev.Rel.</secondary-title>
  </titles>
  <electronic-resource-num>10.12942/lrr-2013-4</electronic-resource-num>
  <pages>4</pages>
  <volume>16</volume>
  <number/>
  <keywords>
    <keyword>Accretion disks</keyword>
    <keyword>Gravitational wave sources</keyword>
    <keyword>Pulsars</keyword>
    <keyword>Black holes</keyword>
    <keyword>Globular clusters</keyword>
    <keyword>Binary systems</keyword>
  </keywords>
  <dates>
    <year>2013</year>
    <pub-dates>
      <date>2013</date>
    </pub-dates>
  </dates>
  <abstract>Galactic globular clusters are old, dense star systems typically containing 10^4 - 10^6 stars. As an old population of stars, globular clusters contain many collapsed and degenerate objects. As a dense population of stars, globular clusters are the scene of many interesting close dynamical interactions between stars. These dynamical interactions can alter the evolution of individual stars and can produce tight binary systems containing one or two compact objects. In this review, we discuss theoretical models of globular cluster evolution and binary evolution, techniques for simulating this evolution that leads to relativistic binaries, and current and possible future observational evidence for this population. Our discussion of globular cluster evolution will focus on the processes that boost the production of tight binary systems and the subsequent interaction of these binaries that can alter the properties of both bodies and can lead to exotic objects. Direct N-body integrations and Fokker-Planck simulations of the evolution of globular clusters that incorporate tidal interactions and lead to predictions of relativistic binary populations are also discussed. We discuss the current observational evidence for cataclysmic variables, millisecond pulsars, and low-mass X-ray binaries as well as possible future detection of relativistic binaries with gravitational radiation.</abstract>
</record>

<record>
  <contributors>
    <authors>
      <author>Simon, Joan</author>
    </authors>
  </contributors>
  <titles>
    <title>Brane Effective Actions, Kappa-Symmetry and Applications</title>
    <secondary-title>Living Rev.Rel.</secondary-title>
  </titles>
  <electronic-resource-num>10.12942/lrr-2012-3</electronic-resource-num>
  <pages>3</pages>
  <volume>15</volume>
  <number/>
  <keywords>
    <keyword>AdS/CFT</keyword>
    <keyword>Supersymmetry</keyword>
    <keyword>Non-abelian gauge theories</keyword>
    <keyword>Solitons</keyword>
    <keyword>Kappa-symmetry</keyword>
  </keywords>
  <dates>
    <year>2012</year>
  </dates>
  <abstract>This is a review on brane effective actions, their symmetries and some of its applications. Its first part uncovers the Green-Schwarz formulation of single M- and D-brane effective actions focusing on kinematical aspects : the identification of their degrees of freedom, the importance of world volume diffeomorphisms and kappa symmetry, to achieve manifest spacetime covariance and supersymmetry, and the explicit construction of such actions in arbitrary on-shell supergravity backgrounds. Its second part deals with applications. First, the use of kappa symmetry to determine supersymmetric world volume solitons. This includes their explicit construction in flat and curved backgrounds, their interpretation as BPS states carrying (topological) charges in the supersymmetry algebra and the connection between supersymmetry and hamiltonian BPS bounds. When available, I emphasise the use of these solitons as constituents in microscopic models of black holes. Second, the use of probe approximations to infer about non-trivial dynamics of strongly coupled gauge theories using the AdS/CFT correspondence. This includes expectation values of Wilson loop operators, spectrum information and the general use of D-brane probes to approximate the dynamics of systems with small number of degrees of freedom interacting with larger systems allowing a dual gravitational description. Its final part briefly discusses effective actions for N D-branes and M2-branes. This includes both SYM theories, their higher order corrections and partial results in covariantising these couplings to curved backgrounds, and the more recent supersymmetric Chern-Simons matter theories describing M2-branes using field theory, brane constructions and 3-algebra considerations.</abstract>
</record>

<record>
  <contributors>
    <authors>
      <author>Andreasson, Hakan</author>
    </authors>
  </contributors>
  <titles>
    <title>The Einstein-Vlasov System/Kinetic Theory</title>
    <secondary-title>Living Rev.Rel.</secondary-title>
  </titles>
  <electronic-resource-num>10.12942/lrr-2011-4</electronic-resource-num>
  <pages>4</pages>
  <volume>14</volume>
  <number/>
  <dates>
    <year>2011</year>
  </dates>
  <abstract>The main purpose of this article is to provide a guide to theorems on global properties of solutions to the Einstein--Vlasov system. This system couples Einstein's equations to a kinetic matter model. Kinetic theory has been an important field of research during several decades in which the main focus has been on non-relativistic and special relativistic physics, i.e., to model the dynamics of neutral gases, plasmas, and Newtonian self-gravitating systems. In 1990, Rendall and Rein initiated a mathematical study of the Einstein--Vlasov system. Since then many theorems on global properties of solutions to this system have been established.</abstract>
</record>

<record>
  <contributors>
    <authors>
      <author>Fryer, Chris L.</author>
      <author>New, Kimberly C.B.</author>
    </authors>
  </contributors>
  <titles>
    <title>Gravitational waves from gravitational collapse</title>
    <secondary-title>Living Rev.Rel.</secondary-title>
  </titles>
  <electronic-resource-num/>
  <pages>1</pages>
  <volume>14</volume>
  <number/>
  <dates>
    <year>2011</year>
  </dates>
  <abstract/>
</record>

<record>
  <contributors>
    <authors>
      <author>Abramowicz, Marek A.</author>
      <author>Fragile, P.Chris</author>
    </authors>
  </contributors>
  <titles>
    <title>Foundations of Black Hole Accretion Disk Theory</title>
    <secondary-title>Living Rev.Rel.</secondary-title>
  </titles>
  <electronic-resource-num>10.12942/lrr-2013-1</electronic-resource-num>
  <pages>1</pages>
  <volume>16</volume>
  <number/>
  <dates>
    <year>2013</year>
  </dates>
  <abstract>This review covers the main aspects of black hole accretion disk theory. We begin with the view that one of the main goals of the theory is to better understand the nature of black holes themselves. In this light we discuss how accretion disks might reveal some of the unique signatures of strong gravity: the event horizon, the innermost stable circular orbit, and the ergosphere. We then review, from a first-principles perspective, the physical processes at play in accretion disks. This leads us to the four primary accretion disk models that we review: Polish doughnuts (thick disks), Shakura-Sunyaev (thin) disks, slim disks, and advection-dominated accretion flows (ADAFs). After presenting the models we discuss issues of stability, oscillations, and jets. Following our review of the analytic work, we take a parallel approach in reviewing numerical studies of black hole accretion disks. We finish with a few select applications that highlight particular astrophysical applications: measurements of black hole mass and spin, black hole vs. neutron star accretion disks, black hole accretion disk spectral states, and quasi-periodic oscillations (QPOs).</abstract>
</record>

<record>
  <contributors>
    <authors>
      <author>Solodukhin, Sergey N.</author>
    </authors>
  </contributors>
  <titles>
    <title>Entanglement entropy of black holes</title>
    <secondary-title>Living Rev.Rel.</secondary-title>
  </titles>
  <electronic-resource-num>10.12942/lrr-2011-8</electronic-resource-num>
  <pages>8</pages>
  <volume>14</volume>
  <number/>
  <dates>
    <year>2011</year>
  </dates>
  <abstract>The entanglement entropy is a fundamental quantity which characterizes the correlations between sub-systems in a larger quantum-mechanical system. For two sub-systems separated by a surface the entanglement entropy is proportional to the area of the surface and depends on the UV cutoff which regulates the short-distance correlations. The geometrical nature of the entanglement entropy calculation is particularly intriguing when applied to black holes when the entangling surface is the black hole horizon. I review a variety of aspects of this calculation: the useful mathematical tools such as the geometry of spaces with conical singularities and the heat kernel method, the UV divergences in the entropy and their renormalization, the logarithmic terms in the entanglement entropy in 4 and 6 dimensions and their relation to the conformal anomalies. The focus in the review is on the systematic use of the conical singularity method. The relations to other known approaches such as 't Hooft's brick wall model and the Euclidean path integral in the optical metric are discussed in detail. The puzzling behavior of the entanglement entropy due to fields which non-minimally couple to gravity is emphasized. The holographic description of the entanglement entropy of the black hole horizon is illustrated on the two- and four-dimensional examples. Finally, I examine the possibility to interpret the Bekenstein-Hawking entropy entirely as the entanglement entropy.</abstract>
</record>

<record>
  <contributors>
    <authors>
      <author>Pitkin, Matthew</author>
      <author>Reid, Stuart</author>
      <author>Rowan, Sheila</author>
      <author>Hough, Jim</author>
    </authors>
  </contributors>
  <titles>
    <title>Gravitational Wave Detection by Interferometry (Ground and Space)</title>
    <secondary-title>Living Rev.Rel.</secondary-title>
  </titles>
  <electronic-resource-num>10.12942/lrr-2011-5</electronic-resource-num>
  <pages>5</pages>
  <volume>14</volume>
  <number/>
  <dates>
    <year>2011</year>
  </dates>
  <abstract>Significant progress has been made in recent years on the development of gravitational wave detectors. Sources such as coalescing compact binary systems, neutron stars in low-mass X-ray binaries, stellar collapses and pulsars are all possible candidates for detection. The most promising design of gravitational wave detector uses test masses a long distance apart and freely suspended as pendulums on Earth or in drag-free craft in space. The main theme of this review is a discussion of the mechanical and optical principles used in the various long baseline systems in operation around the world - LIGO (USA), Virgo (Italy/France), TAMA300 and LCGT (Japan), and GEO600 (Germany/U.K.) - and in LISA, a proposed space-borne interferometer. A review of recent science runs from the current generation of ground-based detectors will be discussed, in addition to highlighting the astrophysical results gained thus far. Looking to the future, the major upgrades to LIGO (Advanced LIGO), Virgo (Advanced Virgo), LCGT and GEO600 (GEO-HF) will be completed over the coming years, which will create a network of detectors with significantly improved sensitivity required to detect gravitational waves. Beyond this, the concept and design of possible future "third generation" gravitational wave detectors, such as the Einstein Telescope (ET), will be discussed.</abstract>
</record>

<record>
  <contributors>
    <authors>
      <author>Poisson, Eric</author>
      <author>Pound, Adam</author>
      <author>Vega, Ian</author>
    </authors>
  </contributors>
  <titles>
    <title>The Motion of point particles in curved spacetime</title>
    <secondary-title>Living Rev.Rel.</secondary-title>
  </titles>
  <electronic-resource-num>10.12942/lrr-2011-7</electronic-resource-num>
  <pages>7</pages>
  <volume>14</volume>
  <number/>
  <dates>
    <year>2011</year>
  </dates>
  <abstract>This review is concerned with the motion of a point scalar charge, a point electric charge, and a point mass in a specified background spacetime. In each of the three cases the particle produces a field that behaves as outgoing radiation in the wave zone, and therefore removes energy from the particle. In the near zone the field acts on the particle and gives rise to a self-force that prevents the particle from moving on a geodesic of the background spacetime. The field's action on the particle is difficult to calculate because of its singular nature: the field diverges at the position of the particle. But it is possible to isolate the field's singular part and show that it exerts no force on the particle. What remains after subtraction is a smooth field that is fully responsible for the self-force. The mathematical tools required to derive the equations of motion of a point scalar charge, a point electric charge, and a point mass in a specified background spacetime are developed here from scratch. The review begins with a discussion of the basic theory of bitensors. It then applies the theory to the construction of convenient coordinate systems to chart a neighbourhood of the particle's word line. It continues with a thorough discussion of Green's functions in curved spacetime. The review presents a detailed derivation of each of the three equations of motion. Because the notion of a point mass is problematic in general relativity, the review concludes with an alternative derivation of the equations of motion that applies to a small body of arbitrary internal structure.</abstract>
</record>

<record>
  <contributors>
    <authors>
      <author>Vinet, Jean-Yves</author>
    </authors>
  </contributors>
  <titles>
    <title>On special optical modes and thermal issues in advanced gravitational wave interferometric detectors</title>
    <secondary-title>Living Rev.Rel.</secondary-title>
  </titles>
  <electronic-resource-num/>
  <pages>5</pages>
  <volume>12</volume>
  <number/>
  <dates>
    <year>2009</year>
  </dates>
  <abstract/>
</record>

<record>
  <contributors>
    <authors>
      <author>Ringstrom, Hans</author>
    </authors>
  </contributors>
  <titles>
    <title>Cosmic censorship for Gowdy spacetimes</title>
    <secondary-title>Living Rev.Rel.</secondary-title>
  </titles>
  <electronic-resource-num/>
  <pages>2</pages>
  <volume>13</volume>
  <number/>
  <dates>
    <year>2010</year>
  </dates>
  <abstract/>
</record>

<record>
  <contributors>
    <authors>
      <author>Perlick, Volker</author>
    </authors>
  </contributors>
  <titles>
    <title>Gravitational Lensing from a Spacetime Perspective</title>
    <secondary-title>Living Rev.Rel.</secondary-title>
  </titles>
  <electronic-resource-num/>
  <pages/>
  <volume/>
  <number/>
  <dates>
    <year>2010</year>
  </dates>
  <abstract>The theory of gravitational lensing is reviewed from a spacetime perspective, without quasi-Newtonian approximations. More precisely, the review covers all aspects of gravitational lensing where light propagation is described in terms of lightlike geodesics of a metric of Lorentzian signature. It includes the basic equations and the relevant techniques for calculating the position, the shape, and the brightness of images in an arbitrary general-relativistic spacetime. It also includes general theorems on the classification of caustics, on criteria for multiple imaging, and on the possible number of images. The general results are illustrated with examples of spacetimes where the lensing features can be explicitly calculated, including the Schwarzschild spacetime, the Kerr spacetime, the spacetime of a straight string, plane gravitational waves, and others.</abstract>
</record>

<record>
  <contributors>
    <authors>
      <author>Barbero G., J.Fernando</author>
      <author>Villasenor, Eduardo J.S.</author>
    </authors>
  </contributors>
  <titles>
    <title>Quantization of Midisuperspace Models</title>
    <secondary-title>Living Rev.Rel.</secondary-title>
  </titles>
  <electronic-resource-num>10.12942/lrr-2010-6</electronic-resource-num>
  <pages>6</pages>
  <volume>13</volume>
  <number/>
  <dates>
    <year>2010</year>
  </dates>
  <abstract>We give a comprehensive review of the quantization of midisuperspace models. Though the main focus of the paper is on quantum aspects, we also provide an introduction to several classical points related to the definition of these models. We cover some important issues, in particular, the use of the principle of symmetric criticality as a very useful tool to obtain the required Hamiltonian formulations. Two main types of reductions are discussed: those involving metrics with two Killing vector fields and spherically symmetric models. We also review the more general models obtained by coupling matter fields to these systems. Throughout the paper we give separate discussions for standard quantizations using geometrodynamical variables and those relying on loop quantum gravity inspired methods.</abstract>
</record>

<record>
  <contributors>
    <authors>
      <author>Uzan, Jean-Philippe</author>
    </authors>
  </contributors>
  <titles>
    <title>Varying Constants, Gravitation and Cosmology</title>
    <secondary-title>Living Rev.Rel.</secondary-title>
  </titles>
  <electronic-resource-num>10.12942/lrr-2011-2</electronic-resource-num>
  <pages>2</pages>
  <volume>14</volume>
  <number/>
  <dates>
    <year>2011</year>
  </dates>
  <abstract>Fundamental constants are a cornerstone of our physical laws. Any constant varying in space and/or time would reflect the existence of an almost massless field that couples to matter. This will induce a violation of the universality of free fall. It is thus of utmost importance for our understanding of gravity and of the domain of validity of general relativity to test for their constancy. We thus detail the relations between the constants, the tests of the local position invariance and of the universality of free fall. We then review the main experimental and observational constraints that have been obtained from atomic clocks, the Oklo phenomenon, Solar system observations, meteorites dating, quasar absorption spectra, stellar physics, pulsar timing, the cosmic microwave background and big bang nucleosynthesis. At each step we describe the basics of each system, its dependence with respect to the constants, the known systematic effects and the most recent constraints that have been obtained. We then describe the main theoretical frameworks in which the low-energy constants may actually be varying and we focus on the unification mechanisms and the relations between the variation of different constants. To finish, we discuss the more speculative possibility of understanding their numerical values and the apparent fine-tuning that they confront us with.</abstract>
</record>

<record>
  <contributors>
    <authors>
      <author>Maartens, Roy</author>
      <author>Koyama, Kazuya</author>
    </authors>
  </contributors>
  <titles>
    <title>Brane-World Gravity</title>
    <secondary-title>Living Rev.Rel.</secondary-title>
  </titles>
  <electronic-resource-num>10.12942/lrr-2010-5</electronic-resource-num>
  <pages>5</pages>
  <volume>13</volume>
  <number/>
  <dates>
    <year>2010</year>
  </dates>
  <abstract>The observable universe could be a 1+3-surface (the "brane") embedded in a 1+3+\textit{d}-dimensional spacetime (the "bulk"), with Standard Model particles and fields trapped on the brane while gravity is free to access the bulk. At least one of the \textit{d} extra spatial dimensions could be very large relative to the Planck scale, which lowers the fundamental gravity scale, possibly even down to the electroweak ($\sim$ TeV) level. This revolutionary picture arises in the framework of recent developments in M theory. The 1+10-dimensional M theory encompasses the known 1+9-dimensional superstring theories, and is widely considered to be a promising potential route to quantum gravity. At low energies, gravity is localized at the brane and general relativity is recovered, but at high energies gravity "leaks" into the bulk, behaving in a truly higher-dimensional way. This introduces significant changes to gravitational dynamics and perturbations, with interesting and potentially testable implications for high-energy astrophysics, black holes, and cosmology. Brane-world models offer a phenomenological way to test some of the novel predictions and corrections to general relativity that are implied by M theory. This review analyzes the geometry, dynamics and perturbations of simple brane-world models for cosmology and astrophysics, mainly focusing on warped 5-dimensional brane-worlds based on the Randall--Sundrum models. We also cover the simplest brane-world models in which 4-dimensional gravity on the brane is modified at \emph{low} energies -- the 5-dimensional Dvali--Gabadadze--Porrati models. Then we discuss co-dimension two branes in 6-dimensional models.</abstract>
</record>

<record>
  <contributors>
    <authors>
      <author>De Felice, Antonio</author>
      <author>Tsujikawa, Shinji</author>
    </authors>
  </contributors>
  <titles>
    <title>f(R) theories</title>
    <secondary-title>Living Rev.Rel.</secondary-title>
  </titles>
  <electronic-resource-num>10.12942/lrr-2010-3</electronic-resource-num>
  <pages>3</pages>
  <volume>13</volume>
  <number/>
  <dates>
    <year>2010</year>
  </dates>
  <abstract>Over the past decade, f(R) theories have been extensively studied as one of the simplest modifications to General Relativity. In this article we review various applications of f(R) theories to cosmology and gravity - such as inflation, dark energy, local gravity constraints, cosmological perturbations, and spherically symmetric solutions in weak and strong gravitational backgrounds. We present a number of ways to distinguish those theories from General Relativity observationally and experimentally. We also discuss the extension to other modified gravity theories such as Brans-Dicke theory and Gauss-Bonnet gravity, and address models that can satisfy both cosmological and local gravity constraints.</abstract>
</record>

<record>
  <contributors>
    <authors>
      <author>Turyshev, Slava G.</author>
      <author>Toth, Viktor T.</author>
    </authors>
  </contributors>
  <titles>
    <title>The Pioneer Anomaly</title>
    <secondary-title>Living Rev.Rel.</secondary-title>
  </titles>
  <electronic-resource-num>10.12942/lrr-2010-4</electronic-resource-num>
  <pages>4</pages>
  <volume>13</volume>
  <number/>
  <dates>
    <year>2010</year>
  </dates>
  <abstract>Radio-metric Doppler tracking data received from the Pioneer 10 and 11 spacecraft from heliocentric distances of 20-70 AU has consistently indicated the presence of a small, anomalous, blue-shifted frequency drift uniformly changing with a rate of ~6 x 10^{-9} Hz/s. Ultimately, the drift was interpreted as a constant sunward deceleration of each particular spacecraft at the level of a_P = (8.74 +/- 1.33) x 10^{-10} m/s^2. This apparent violation of the Newton's gravitational inverse-square law has become known as the Pioneer anomaly; the nature of this anomaly remains unexplained. In this review, we summarize the current knowledge of the physical properties of the anomaly and the conditions that led to its detection and characterization. We review various mechanisms proposed to explain the anomaly and discuss the current state of efforts to determine its nature. A comprehensive new investigation of the anomalous behavior of the two Pioneers has begun recently. The new efforts rely on the much-extended set of radio-metric Doppler data for both spacecraft in conjunction with the newly available complete record of their telemetry files and a large archive of original project documentation. As the new study is yet to report its findings, this review provides the necessary background for the new results to appear in the near future. In particular, we provide a significant amount of information on the design, operations and behavior of the two Pioneers during their entire missions, including descriptions of various data formats and techniques used for their navigation and radio-science data analysis. As most of this information was recovered relatively recently, it was not used in the previous studies of the Pioneer anomaly, but it is critical for the new investigation.</abstract>
</record>

<record>
  <contributors>
    <authors>
      <author>Freise, Andreas</author>
      <author>Strain, Kenneth</author>
    </authors>
  </contributors>
  <titles>
    <title>Interferometer Techniques for Gravitational-Wave Detection</title>
    <secondary-title>Living Rev.Rel.</secondary-title>
  </titles>
  <electronic-resource-num>10.12942/lrr-2010-1</electronic-resource-num>
  <pages>1</pages>
  <volume>13</volume>
  <number/>
  <dates>
    <year>2010</year>
    <pub-dates>
      <date>2017-08-15</date>
    </pub-dates>
  </dates>
  <abstract>Several km-scale gravitational-wave detectors have been constructed world wide. These instruments combine a number of advanced technologies to push the limits of precision length measurement. The core devices are laser interferometers of a new kind; developed from the classical Michelson topology these interferometers integrate additional optical elements, which significantly change the properties of the optical system. Much of the design and analysis of these laser interferometers can be performed using well-known classical optical techniques; however, the complex optical layouts provide a new challenge. In this review we give a textbook-style introduction to the optical science required for the understanding of modern gravitational wave detectors, as well as other high-precision laser interferometers. In addition, we provide a number of examples for a freely available interferometer simulation software and encourage the reader to use these examples to gain hands-on experience with the discussed optical methods.</abstract>
</record>

<record>
  <contributors>
    <authors>
      <author>Adamo, T.M.</author>
      <author>Kozameh, C.N.</author>
      <author>Newman, E.T.</author>
    </authors>
  </contributors>
  <titles>
    <title>Null Geodesic Congruences, Asymptotically Flat Space-Times and Their Physical Interpretation</title>
    <secondary-title>Living Rev.Rel.</secondary-title>
  </titles>
  <electronic-resource-num>10.12942/lrr-2009-6</electronic-resource-num>
  <pages>6</pages>
  <volume>12</volume>
  <number/>
  <dates>
    <year>2009</year>
  </dates>
  <abstract>Shear-free or asymptotically shear-free null geodesic congruences possess a large number of fascinating geometric properties and to be closely related, in the context of general relativity, to a variety of physically significant affects. It is the purpose of this paper to develop these issues and find applications in GR. The applications center around the problem of extracting interior physical properties of an asymptotically flat space-time directly from the asymptotic gravitational (and Maxwell) field itself in analogy with the determination of total charge by an integral over the Maxwell field at infinity or the identification of the interior mass (and its loss) by (Bondi's) integrals of the Weyl tensor, also at infinity. More specifically we will see that the asymptotically shear-free congruences lead us to an asymptotic definition of the center-of-mass and its equations of motion. This includes a kinematic meaning, in terms of the center of mass motion, for the Bondi three-momentum. In addition, we obtain insights into intrinsic spin and, in general, angular momentum, including an angular momentum conservation law with well-defined flux terms. When a Maxwell field is present the asymptotically shear-free congruences allow us to determine/define at infinity a center-of-charge world-line and intrinsic magnetic dipole moment.</abstract>
</record>

<record>
  <contributors>
    <authors>
      <author>Sathyaprakash, B.S.</author>
      <author>Schutz, B.F.</author>
    </authors>
  </contributors>
  <titles>
    <title>Physics, Astrophysics and Cosmology with Gravitational Waves</title>
    <secondary-title>Living Rev.Rel.</secondary-title>
  </titles>
  <electronic-resource-num>10.12942/lrr-2009-2</electronic-resource-num>
  <pages>2</pages>
  <volume>12</volume>
  <number/>
  <dates>
    <year>2009</year>
  </dates>
  <abstract>Gravitational wave detectors are already operating at interesting sensitivity levels, and they have an upgrade path that should result in secure detections by 2014. We review the physics of gravitational waves, how they interact with detectors (bars and interferometers), and how these detectors operate. We study the most likely sources of gravitational waves and review the data analysis methods that are used to extract their signals from detector noise. Then we consider the consequences of gravitational wave detections and observations for physics, astrophysics, and cosmology.</abstract>
</record>

<record>
  <contributors>
    <authors>
      <author>Chamel, N.</author>
      <author>Haensel, P.</author>
    </authors>
  </contributors>
  <titles>
    <title>Physics of Neutron Star Crusts</title>
    <secondary-title>Living Rev.Rel.</secondary-title>
  </titles>
  <electronic-resource-num>10.12942/lrr-2008-10</electronic-resource-num>
  <pages>10</pages>
  <volume>11</volume>
  <number/>
  <dates>
    <year>2008</year>
  </dates>
  <abstract>The physics of neutron star crusts is vast, involving many different research fields, from nuclear and condensed matter physics to general relativity. This review summarizes the progress, which has been achieved over the last few years, in modeling neutron star crusts, both at the microscopic and macroscopic levels. The confrontation of these theoretical models with observations is also briefly discussed.</abstract>
</record>

<record>
  <contributors>
    <authors>
      <author>Rovelli, Carlo</author>
    </authors>
  </contributors>
  <titles>
    <title>Loop quantum gravity</title>
    <secondary-title>Living Rev.Rel.</secondary-title>
  </titles>
  <electronic-resource-num/>
  <pages>5</pages>
  <volume>11</volume>
  <number/>
  <dates>
    <year>2008</year>
  </dates>
  <abstract/>
</record>

<record>
  <contributors>
    <authors>
      <author>Bojowald, Martin</author>
    </authors>
  </contributors>
  <titles>
    <title>Loop quantum cosmology</title>
    <secondary-title>Living Rev.Rel.</secondary-title>
  </titles>
  <electronic-resource-num/>
  <pages>4</pages>
  <volume>11</volume>
  <number/>
  <dates>
    <year>2008</year>
  </dates>
  <abstract>Quantum gravity is expected to be necessary in order to understand situations in which classical general relativity breaks down. In particular in cosmology one has to deal with initial singularities, i.e., the fact that the backward evolution of a classical spacetime inevitably comes to an end after a finite amount of proper time. This presents a breakdown of the classical picture and requires an extended theory for a meaningful description. Since small length scales and high curvatures are involved, quantum effects must play a role. Not only the singularity itself but also the surrounding spacetime is then modified. One particular theory is loop quantum cosmology, an application of loop quantum gravity to homogeneous systems, which removes classical singularities. Its implications can be studied at different levels. The main effects are introduced into effective classical equations, which allow one to avoid the interpretational problems of quantum theory. They give rise to new kinds of early-universe phenomenology with applications to inflation and cyclic models. To resolve classical singularities and to understand the structure of geometry around them, the quantum description is necessary. Classical evolution is then replaced by a difference equation for a wave function, which allows an extension of quantum spacetime beyond classical singularities. One main question is how these homogeneous scenarios are related to full loop quantum gravity, which can be dealt with at the level of distributional symmetric states. Finally, the new structure of spacetime arising in loop quantum gravity and its application to cosmology sheds light on more general issues, such as the nature of time.</abstract>
</record>

<record>
  <contributors>
    <authors>
      <author>Cirkel-Bartelt, Vanessa</author>
    </authors>
  </contributors>
  <titles>
    <title>History of astroparticle physics and its components</title>
    <secondary-title>Living Rev.Rel.</secondary-title>
  </titles>
  <electronic-resource-num/>
  <pages>2</pages>
  <volume>11</volume>
  <number/>
  <dates>
    <year>2008</year>
  </dates>
  <abstract/>
</record>

<record>
  <contributors>
    <authors>
      <author>Lorimer, D.R.</author>
    </authors>
  </contributors>
  <titles>
    <title>Binary and Millisecond Pulsars</title>
    <secondary-title>Living Rev.Rel.</secondary-title>
  </titles>
  <electronic-resource-num>10.12942/lrr-2008-8</electronic-resource-num>
  <pages>8</pages>
  <volume>11</volume>
  <number/>
  <dates>
    <year>2008</year>
  </dates>
  <abstract>We review the main properties, demographics and applications of binary and millisecond radio pulsars. Our knowledge of these exciting objects has greatly increased in recent years, mainly due to successful surveys which have brought the known pulsar population to over 1800. There are now 83 binary and millisecond pulsars associated with the disk of our Galaxy, and a further 140 pulsars in 26 of the Galactic globular clusters. Recent highlights include the discovery of the young relativistic binary system PSR J1906+0746, a rejuvination in globular cluster pulsar research including growing numbers of pulsars with masses in excess of 1.5 solar masses, a precise measurement of relativistic spin precession in the double pulsar system and a Galactic millisecond pulsar in an eccentric (e=0.44) orbit around an unevolved companion.</abstract>
</record>

<record>
  <contributors>
    <authors>
      <author>Psaltis, Dimitrios</author>
    </authors>
  </contributors>
  <titles>
    <title>Probes and Tests of Strong-Field Gravity with Observations in the Electromagnetic Spectrum</title>
    <secondary-title>Living Rev.Rel.</secondary-title>
  </titles>
  <electronic-resource-num>10.12942/lrr-2008-9</electronic-resource-num>
  <pages>9</pages>
  <volume>11</volume>
  <number/>
  <dates>
    <year>2008</year>
  </dates>
  <abstract>Neutron stars and black holes are the astrophysical systems with the strongest gravitational fields in the universe. In this article, I review the prospect of using observations of such compact objects to probe some of the most intriguing general relativistic predictions in the strong-field regime: the absence of stable circular orbits near a compact object and the presence of event horizons around black-hole singularities. I discuss the need for a theoretical framework, within which future experiments will provide detailed, quantitative tests of gravity theories. Finally, I summarize the constraints imposed by current observations of neutron stars on potential deviations from general relativity.</abstract>
</record>

<record>
  <contributors>
    <authors>
      <author>Amelino-Camelia, Giovanni</author>
    </authors>
  </contributors>
  <titles>
    <title>Quantum-Spacetime Phenomenology</title>
    <secondary-title>Living Rev.Rel.</secondary-title>
  </titles>
  <electronic-resource-num>10.12942/lrr-2013-5</electronic-resource-num>
  <pages>5</pages>
  <volume>16</volume>
  <number/>
  <keywords>
    <keyword>Loop quantum gravity</keyword>
    <keyword>Quantum spacetime</keyword>
    <keyword>Spacetime noncommutativity</keyword>
  </keywords>
  <dates>
    <year>2013</year>
    <pub-dates>
      <date>2013</date>
    </pub-dates>
  </dates>
  <abstract>I review the current status of phenomenological programs inspired by quantum-spacetime research. I stress in particular the significance of results establishing that certain data analyses provide sensitivity to effects introduced genuinely at the Planck scale. My main focus is on phenomenological programs that affect the directions taken by studies of quantum-spacetime theories.</abstract>
</record>

<record>
  <contributors>
    <authors>
      <author>Hu, B.L.</author>
      <author>Verdaguer, E.</author>
    </authors>
  </contributors>
  <titles>
    <title>Stochastic Gravity: Theory and Applications</title>
    <secondary-title>Living Rev.Rel.</secondary-title>
  </titles>
  <electronic-resource-num>10.12942/lrr-2008-3</electronic-resource-num>
  <pages>3</pages>
  <volume>11</volume>
  <number/>
  <dates>
    <year>2008</year>
  </dates>
  <abstract>Whereas semiclassical gravity is based on the semiclassical Einstein equation with sources given by the expectation value of the stress-energy tensor of quantum fields, stochastic semiclassical gravity is based on the Einstein-Langevin equation, which has in addition sources due to the noise kernel. In the first part, we describe the fundamentals of this new theory via two approaches: the axiomatic and the functional. In the second part, we describe three applications of stochastic gravity theory. First, we consider metric perturbations in a Minkowski spacetime, compute the two-point correlation functions of these perturbations and prove that Minkowski spacetime is a stable solution of semiclassical gravity. Second, we discuss structure formation from the stochastic gravity viewpoint. Third, we discuss the backreaction of Hawking radiation in the gravitational background of a black hole and describe the metric fluctuations near the event horizon of an evaporating black hole</abstract>
</record>

<record>
  <contributors>
    <authors>
      <author>Emparan, Roberto</author>
      <author>Reall, Harvey S.</author>
    </authors>
  </contributors>
  <titles>
    <title>Black Holes in Higher Dimensions</title>
    <secondary-title>Living Rev.Rel.</secondary-title>
  </titles>
  <electronic-resource-num>10.12942/lrr-2008-6</electronic-resource-num>
  <pages>6</pages>
  <volume>11</volume>
  <number/>
  <dates>
    <year>2008</year>
  </dates>
  <abstract>We review black hole solutions of higher-dimensional vacuum gravity, and of higher-dimensional supergravity theories. The discussion of vacuum gravity is pedagogical, with detailed reviews of Myers-Perry solutions, black rings, and solution-generating techniques. We discuss black hole solutions of maximal supergravity theories, including black holes in anti-de Sitter space. General results and open problems are discussed throughout.</abstract>
</record>

<record>
  <contributors>
    <authors>
      <author>Futamase, Toshifumi</author>
      <author>Itoh, Yousuke</author>
    </authors>
  </contributors>
  <titles>
    <title>The post-Newtonian approximation for relativistic compact binaries</title>
    <secondary-title>Living Rev.Rel.</secondary-title>
  </titles>
  <electronic-resource-num>10.12942/lrr-2007-2</electronic-resource-num>
  <pages>2</pages>
  <volume>10</volume>
  <number/>
  <dates>
    <year>2007</year>
  </dates>
  <abstract>We discuss various aspects of the post-Newtonian approximation in general relativity. After presenting the foundation based on the Newtonian limit, we show a method to derive post-Newtonian equations of motion for relativistic compact binaries based on a surface integral approach and the strong field point particle limit. As an application we derive third post-Newtonian equations of motion for relativistic compact binaries which respect the Lorentz invariance in the post-Newtonian perturbative sense, admit a conserved energy, and are free from any ambiguity.</abstract>
</record>

<record>
  <contributors>
    <authors>
      <author>Gundlach, Carsten</author>
      <author>Martin-Garcia, Jose M.</author>
    </authors>
  </contributors>
  <titles>
    <title>Critical phenomena in gravitational collapse</title>
    <secondary-title>Living Rev.Rel.</secondary-title>
  </titles>
  <electronic-resource-num>10.12942/lrr-2007-5</electronic-resource-num>
  <pages>5</pages>
  <volume>10</volume>
  <number/>
  <dates>
    <year>2007</year>
  </dates>
  <abstract>As first discovered by Choptuik, the black hole threshold in the space of initial data for general relativity shows both surprising structure and surprising simplicity. Universality, power-law scaling of the black hole mass, and scale echoing have given rise to the term "critical phenomena". They are explained by the existence of exact solutions which are attractors within the black hole threshold, that is, attractors of codimension one in phase space, and which are typically self-similar. Critical phenomena give a natural route from smooth initial data to arbitrarily large curvatures visible from infinity, and are therefore likely to be relevant for cosmic censorship, quantum gravity, astrophysics, and our general understanding of the dynamics of general relativity.</abstract>
</record>

<record>
  <contributors>
    <authors>
      <author>Jaranowski, Piotr</author>
      <author>Krolak, Andrzej</author>
    </authors>
  </contributors>
  <titles>
    <title>Gravitational-Wave Data Analysis. Formalism and Sample Applications: The Gaussian Case</title>
    <secondary-title>Living Rev.Rel.</secondary-title>
  </titles>
  <electronic-resource-num/>
  <pages>3</pages>
  <volume>8</volume>
  <number/>
  <keywords>
    <keyword>signal detection</keyword>
    <keyword>parameter estimation</keyword>
    <keyword>gravitational waves</keyword>
  </keywords>
  <dates>
    <year>2005</year>
  </dates>
  <abstract>The article reviews the statistical theory of signal detection in application to analysis of deterministic gravitational-wave signals in the noise of a detector. Statistical foundations for the theory of signal detection and parameter estimation are presented. Several tools needed for both theoretical evaluation of the optimal data analysis methods and for their practical implementation are introduced. They include optimal signal-to-noise ratio, Fisher matrix, false alarm and detection probabilities, $\F$-statistic, template placement, and fitting factor. These tools apply to the case of signals buried in a stationary and Gaussian noise. Algorithms to efficiently implement the optimal data analysis techniques are discussed. Formulas are given for a general gravitational-wave signal that includes as special cases most of the deterministic signals of interest.</abstract>
</record>

<record>
  <contributors>
    <authors>
      <author>Henneaux, Marc</author>
      <author>Persson, Daniel</author>
      <author>Spindel, Philippe</author>
    </authors>
  </contributors>
  <titles>
    <title>Spacelike Singularities and Hidden Symmetries of Gravity</title>
    <secondary-title>Living Rev.Rel.</secondary-title>
  </titles>
  <electronic-resource-num>10.12942/lrr-2008-1</electronic-resource-num>
  <pages>1</pages>
  <volume>11</volume>
  <number/>
  <dates>
    <year>2008</year>
  </dates>
  <abstract>We review the intimate connection between (super-)gravity close to a spacelike singularity (the "BKL-limit") and the theory of Lorentzian Kac-Moody algebras. We show that in this limit the gravitational theory can be reformulated in terms of billiard motion in a region of hyperbolic space, revealing that the dynamics is completely determined by a (possibly infinite) sequence of reflections, which are elements of a Lorentzian Coxeter group. Such Coxeter groups are the Weyl groups of infinite-dimensional Kac-Moody algebras, suggesting that these algebras yield symmetries of gravitational theories. Our presentation is aimed to be a self-contained and comprehensive treatment of the subject, with all the relevant mathematical background material introduced and explained in detail. We also review attempts at making the infinite-dimensional symmetries manifest, through the construction of a geodesic sigma model based on a Lorentzian Kac-Moody algebra. An explicit example is provided for the case of the hyperbolic algebra E10, which is conjectured to be an underlying symmetry of M-theory. Illustrations of this conjecture are also discussed in the context of cosmological solutions to eleven-dimensional supergravity.</abstract>
</record>

<record>
  <contributors>
    <authors>
      <author>Jackson, Neal</author>
    </authors>
  </contributors>
  <titles>
    <title>The Hubble Constant</title>
    <secondary-title>Living Rev.Rel.</secondary-title>
  </titles>
  <electronic-resource-num>10.12942/lrr-2007-4</electronic-resource-num>
  <pages>4</pages>
  <volume>10</volume>
  <number/>
  <dates>
    <year>2007</year>
  </dates>
  <abstract>I review the current state of determinations of the Hubble constant, which gives the length scale of the Universe by relating the expansion velocity of objects to their distance. In the last 20 years, much progress has been made and estimates now range between 60 and 75 km/s/Mpc, with most now between 70 and 75km/s/Mpc, a huge improvement over the factor-of-2 uncertainty which used to prevail. Further improvements which gave a generally agreed margin of error of a few percent rather than the current 10% would be vital input to much other interesting cosmology. There are several programmes which are likely to lead us to this point in the next 10 years.</abstract>
</record>

<record>
  <contributors>
    <authors>
      <author>Grandclement, Philippe</author>
      <author>Novak, Jerome</author>
    </authors>
  </contributors>
  <titles>
    <title>Spectral methods for numerical relativity</title>
    <secondary-title>Living Rev.Rel.</secondary-title>
  </titles>
  <electronic-resource-num>10.12942/lrr-2009-1</electronic-resource-num>
  <pages>1</pages>
  <volume>12</volume>
  <number/>
  <dates>
    <year>2009</year>
  </dates>
  <abstract>Equations arising in general relativity are usually too complicated to be solved analytically and one must rely on numerical methods to solve sets of coupled partial differential equations. Among the possible choices, this paper focuses on a class called spectral methods in which, typically, the various functions are expanded in sets of orthogonal polynomials or functions. First, a theoretical introduction of spectral expansion is given with a particular emphasis on the fast convergence of the spectral approximation. We then present different approaches to solving partial differential equations, first limiting ourselves to the one-dimensional case, with one or more domains. Generalization to more dimensions is then discussed. In particular, the case of time evolutions is carefully studied and the stability of such evolutions investigated. We then present results obtained by various groups in the field of general relativity by means of spectral methods. Work, which does not involve explicit time-evolutions, is discussed, going from rapidly-rotating strange stars to the computation of black-hole–binary initial data. Finally, the evolution of various systems of astrophysical interest are presented, from supernovae core collapse to black-hole–binary mergers.</abstract>
</record>

<record>
  <contributors>
    <authors>
      <author>Postnov, Konstantin</author>
      <author>Yungelson, Lev</author>
    </authors>
  </contributors>
  <titles>
    <title>The Evolution of Compact Binary Star Systems</title>
    <secondary-title>Living Rev.Rel.</secondary-title>
  </titles>
  <electronic-resource-num>10.12942/lrr-2006-6</electronic-resource-num>
  <pages>6</pages>
  <volume>9</volume>
  <number/>
  <dates>
    <year>2006</year>
  </dates>
  <abstract>We review the formation and evolution of compact binary stars consisting of white dwarfs (WDs), neutron stars (NSs), and black holes (BHs). Binary NSs and BHs are thought to be the primary astrophysical sources of gravitational waves (GWs) within the frequency band of ground-based detectors, while compact binaries of WDs are important sources of GWs at lower frequencies to be covered by space interferometers (LISA). Major uncertainties in the current understanding of properties of NSs and BHs most relevant to the GW studies are discussed, including the treatment of the natal kicks which compact stellar remnants acquire during the core collapse of massive stars and the common envelope phase of binary evolution. We discuss the coalescence rates of binary NSs and BHs and prospects for their detections, the formation and evolution of binary WDs and their observational manifestations. Special attention is given to AM CVn-stars -- compact binaries in which the Roche lobe is filled by another WD or a low-mass partially degenerate helium-star, as these stars are thought to be the best LISA verification binary GW sources.</abstract>
</record>

<record>
  <contributors>
    <authors>
      <author>Blanchet, Luc</author>
    </authors>
  </contributors>
  <titles>
    <title>Gravitational radiation from post-Newtonian sources and inspiralling compact binaries</title>
    <secondary-title>Living Rev.Rel.</secondary-title>
  </titles>
  <electronic-resource-num/>
  <pages>4</pages>
  <volume>9</volume>
  <number/>
  <dates>
    <year>2006</year>
  </dates>
  <abstract/>
</record>

<record>
  <contributors>
    <authors>
      <author>Armstrong, John W.</author>
    </authors>
  </contributors>
  <titles>
    <title>Low-frequency gravitational wave searches using spacecraft Doppler tracking</title>
    <secondary-title>Living Rev.Rel.</secondary-title>
  </titles>
  <electronic-resource-num/>
  <pages>1</pages>
  <volume>9</volume>
  <number/>
  <dates>
    <year>2006</year>
  </dates>
  <abstract/>
</record>

<record>
  <contributors>
    <authors>
      <author>Niedermaier, Max</author>
      <author>Reuter, Martin</author>
    </authors>
  </contributors>
  <titles>
    <title>The Asymptotic Safety Scenario in Quantum Gravity</title>
    <secondary-title>Living Rev.Rel.</secondary-title>
  </titles>
  <electronic-resource-num>10.12942/lrr-2006-5</electronic-resource-num>
  <pages>5-173</pages>
  <volume>9</volume>
  <number/>
  <dates>
    <year>2006</year>
  </dates>
  <abstract/>
</record>

<record>
  <contributors>
    <authors>
      <author>Andersson, N.</author>
      <author>Comer, G.L.</author>
    </authors>
  </contributors>
  <titles>
    <title>Relativistic fluid dynamics: Physics for many different scales</title>
    <secondary-title>Living Rev.Rel.</secondary-title>
  </titles>
  <electronic-resource-num>10.12942/lrr-2007-1</electronic-resource-num>
  <pages>1</pages>
  <volume>10</volume>
  <number/>
  <dates>
    <year>2007</year>
  </dates>
  <abstract>The relativistic fluid is a highly successful model used to describe the dynamics of many-particle, relativistic systems. It takes as input basic physics from microscopic scales and yields as output predictions of bulk, macroscopic motion. By inverting the process, an understanding of bulk features can lead to insight into physics on the microscopic scale. Relativistic fluids have been used to model systems as ``small'' as heavy ions in collisions, and as large as the universe itself, with ``intermediate'' sized objects like neutron stars being considered along the way. The purpose of this review is to discuss the mathematical and theoretical physics underpinnings of the relativistic (multiple) fluid model. We focus on the variational principle approach championed by Brandon Carter and his collaborators, in which a crucial element is to distinguish the momenta that are conjugate to the particle number density currents. This approach differs from the ``standard'' text-book derivation of the equations of motion from the divergence of the stress-energy tensor, in that one explicitly obtains the relativistic Euler equation as an ``integrability'' condition on the relativistic vorticity. We discuss the conservation laws and the equations of motion in detail, and provide a number of (in our opinion) interesting and relevant applications of the general theory.</abstract>
</record>

<record>
  <contributors>
    <authors>
      <author>Bojowald, Martin</author>
    </authors>
  </contributors>
  <titles>
    <title>Loop quantum cosmology</title>
    <secondary-title>Living Rev.Rel.</secondary-title>
  </titles>
  <electronic-resource-num>10.12942/lrr-2005-11</electronic-resource-num>
  <pages>11</pages>
  <volume>8</volume>
  <number/>
  <dates>
    <year>2005</year>
  </dates>
  <abstract>Quantum gravity is expected to be necessary in order to understand situations where classical general relativity breaks down. In particular in cosmology one has to deal with initial singularities, i.e. the fact that the backward evolution of a classical space-time inevitably comes to an end after a finite amount of proper time. This presents a breakdown of the classical picture and requires an extended theory for a meaningful description. Since small length scales and high curvatures are involved, quantum effects must play a role. Not only the singularity itself but also the surrounding space-time is then modified. One particular realization is loop quantum cosmology, an application of loop quantum gravity to homogeneous systems, which removes classical singularities. Its implications can be studied at different levels. Main effects are introduced into effective classical equations which allow to avoid interpretational problems of quantum theory. They give rise to new kinds of early universe phenomenology with applications to inflation and cyclic models. To resolve classical singularities and to understand the structure of geometry around them, the quantum description is necessary. Classical evolution is then replaced by a difference equation for a wave function which allows to extend space-time beyond classical singularities. One main question is how these homogeneous scenarios are related to full loop quantum gravity, which can be dealt with at the level of distributional symmetric states. Finally, the new structure of space-time arising in loop quantum gravity and its application to cosmology sheds new light on more general issues such as time.</abstract>
</record>

<record>
  <contributors>
    <authors>
      <author>Thornburg, Jonathan</author>
    </authors>
  </contributors>
  <titles>
    <title>Event and apparent horizon finders for 3+1 numerical relativity</title>
    <secondary-title>Living Rev.Rel.</secondary-title>
  </titles>
  <electronic-resource-num/>
  <pages>3</pages>
  <volume>10</volume>
  <number/>
  <dates>
    <year>2007</year>
  </dates>
  <abstract>Event and apparent horizons are key diagnostics for the presence and properties of black holes. In this article I review numerical algorithms and codes for finding event and apparent horizons in numerically-computed spacetimes, focusing on calculations done using the 3+1 ADM formalism. There are 3 basic algorithms for finding event horizons, based respectively on integrating null geodesics \emph{forwards} in time, integrating null geodesics \emph{backwards} in time, and integrating null \emph{surfaces} backwards in time. The last of these is generally the most efficient and accurate. There are a large number of apparent-horizon finding algorithms, with differing trade-offs between speed, robustness, accuracy, and ease of programming. In axisymmetry, shooting algorithms work well and are fairly easy to program. In slices with no continuous symmetries, Nakamura et al.'s algorithm and elliptic-PDE algorithms are fast and accurate, but require good initial guesses to converge. In many cases Schnetter's pretracking algorithm can greatly improve an elliptic-PDE algorithm's robustness. Flow algorithms are generally quite slow, but can be very robust in their convergence.</abstract>
</record>

<record>
  <contributors>
    <authors>
      <author>Lorimer, Duncan R.</author>
    </authors>
  </contributors>
  <titles>
    <title>Binary and millisecond pulsars</title>
    <secondary-title>Living Rev.Rel.</secondary-title>
  </titles>
  <electronic-resource-num/>
  <pages>7</pages>
  <volume>8</volume>
  <number/>
  <dates>
    <year>2005</year>
  </dates>
  <abstract>We review the main properties, demographics and applications of binary and millisecond radio pulsars. Our knowledge of these exciting objects has greatly increased in recent years, mainly due to successful surveys which have brought the known pulsar population to over 1700. There are now 80 binary and millisecond pulsars associated with the disk of our Galaxy, and a further 103 pulsars in 24 of the Galactic globular clusters. Recent highlights have been the discovery of the first ever double pulsar system and a recent flurry of discoveries in globular clusters, in particular Terzan 5.</abstract>
</record>

<record>
  <contributors>
    <authors>
      <author>Will, Clifford M.</author>
    </authors>
  </contributors>
  <titles>
    <title>The Confrontation between general relativity and experiment</title>
    <secondary-title>Living Rev.Rel.</secondary-title>
  </titles>
  <electronic-resource-num>10.12942/lrr-2006-3</electronic-resource-num>
  <pages>3</pages>
  <volume>9</volume>
  <number/>
  <dates>
    <year>2006</year>
  </dates>
  <abstract>The status of experimental tests of general relativity and of theoretical frameworks for analysing them is reviewed. Einstein's equivalence principle (EEP) is well supported by experiments such as the Eotvos experiment, tests of special relativity, and the gravitational redshift experiment. Future tests of EEP and of the inverse square law are searching for new interactions arising from unification or quantum gravity. Tests of general relativity at the post-Newtonian level have reached high precision, including the light deflection, the Shapiro time delay, the perihelion advance of Mercury, and the Nordtvedt effect in lunar motion. Gravitational-wave damping has been detected in an amount that agrees with general relativity to better than half a percent using the Hulse-Taylor binary pulsar, and other binary pulsar systems have yielded other tests, especially of strong-field effects. When direct observation of gravitational radiation from astrophysical sources begins, new tests of general relativity will be possible.</abstract>
</record>

<record>
  <contributors>
    <authors>
      <author>Plefka, Jan</author>
    </authors>
  </contributors>
  <titles>
    <title>Spinning strings and integrable spin chains in the AdS/CFT correspondence</title>
    <secondary-title>Living Rev.Rel.</secondary-title>
  </titles>
  <electronic-resource-num>10.12942/lrr-2005-9</electronic-resource-num>
  <pages>9</pages>
  <volume>8</volume>
  <number/>
  <dates>
    <year>2005</year>
  </dates>
  <abstract>In this introductory review we discuss dynamical tests of the AdS_5 x S^5 string/N=4 super Yang-Mills duality. After a brief introduction to AdS/CFT we argue that semiclassical string energies yield information on the quantum spectrum of the string in the limit of large angular momenta on the S^5. The energies of the folded and circular spinning string solutions rotating on a S^3 within the S^5 are derived, which yield all loop predictions for the dual gauge theory scaling dimensions. These follow from the eigenvalues of the dilatation operator of N=4 super Yang-Mills in a minimal SU(2) subsector and we display its reformulation in terms of a Heisenberg s=1/2 spin chain along with the coordinate Bethe ansatz for its explicit diagonalization. In order to make contact to the spinning string energies we then study the thermodynamic limit of the one-loop gauge theory Bethe equations and demonstrate the matching with the folded and closed string result at this loop order. Finally the known gauge theory results at higher-loop orders are reviewed and the associated long-range spin chain Bethe ansatz is introduced, leading to an asymptotic all-loop conjecture for the gauge theory Bethe equations. This uncovers discrepancies at the three-loop order between gauge theory scaling dimensions and string theory energies and the implications of this are discussed. Along the way we comment on further developments and generalizations of the subject and point to the relevant literature.</abstract>
</record>

<record>
  <contributors>
    <authors>
      <author>Barcelo, Carlos</author>
      <author>Liberati, Stefano</author>
      <author>Visser, Matt</author>
    </authors>
  </contributors>
  <titles>
    <title>Analogue gravity</title>
    <secondary-title>Living Rev.Rel.</secondary-title>
  </titles>
  <electronic-resource-num>10.12942/lrr-2005-12</electronic-resource-num>
  <pages>12</pages>
  <volume>8</volume>
  <number/>
  <dates>
    <year>2005</year>
  </dates>
  <abstract>Analogue gravity is a research programme which investigates analogues of general relativistic gravitational fields within other physical systems, typically but not exclusively condensed matter systems, with the aim of gaining new insights into their corresponding problems. Analogue models of (and for) gravity have a long and distinguished history dating back to the earliest years of general relativity. In this review article we will discuss the history, aims, results, and future prospects for the various analogue models. We start the discussion by presenting a particularly simple example of an analogue model, before exploring the rich history and complex tapestry of models discussed in the literature. The last decade in particular has seen a remarkable and sustained development of analogue gravity ideas, leading to some hundreds of published articles, a workshop, two books, and this review article. Future prospects for the analogue gravity programme also look promising, both on the experimental front (where technology is rapidly advancing) and on the theoretical front (where variants of analogue models can be used as a springboard for radical attacks on the problem of quantum gravity).</abstract>
</record>

<record>
  <contributors>
    <authors>
      <author>Mattingly, David</author>
    </authors>
  </contributors>
  <titles>
    <title>Modern tests of Lorentz invariance</title>
    <secondary-title>Living Rev.Rel.</secondary-title>
  </titles>
  <electronic-resource-num>10.12942/lrr-2005-5</electronic-resource-num>
  <pages>5</pages>
  <volume>8</volume>
  <number/>
  <dates>
    <year>2005</year>
  </dates>
  <abstract>Motivated by ideas about quantum gravity, a tremendous amount of effort over the past decade has gone into testing Lorentz invariance in various regimes. This review summarizes both the theoretical frameworks for tests of Lorentz invariance and experimental advances that have made new high precision tests possible. The current constraints on Lorentz violating effects from both terrestrial experiments and astrophysical observations are presented.</abstract>
</record>

<record>
  <contributors>
    <authors>
      <author>Andreasson, Hakan</author>
    </authors>
  </contributors>
  <titles>
    <title>The Einstein-Vlasov system / kinetic theory</title>
    <secondary-title>Living Rev.Rel.</secondary-title>
  </titles>
  <electronic-resource-num>10.12942/lrr-2005-2</electronic-resource-num>
  <pages>2</pages>
  <volume>8</volume>
  <number/>
  <dates>
    <year>2005</year>
  </dates>
  <abstract>The main purpose of this article is to provide a guide to theorems on global properties of solutions to the Einstein-Vlasov system. This system couples Einstein's equations to a kinetic matter model. Kinetic theory has been an important field of research during several decades in which the main focus has been on nonrelativistic and special relativistic physics, {\it i.e.} to model the dynamics of neutral gases, plasmas, and Newtonian self-gravitating systems. In 1990, Rendall and Rein initiated a mathematical study of the Einstein-Vlasov system. Since then many theorems on global properties of solutions to this system have been established. The Vlasov equation describes matter phenomenologically and it should be stressed that most of the theorems presented in this article are not presently known for other such matter models ({\it i.e.} fluid models). This paper gives introductions to kinetic theory in non-curved spacetimes and then the Einstein-Vlasov system is introduced. We believe that a good understanding of kinetic theory in non-curved spacetimes is fundamental to good comprehension of kinetic theory in general relativity.</abstract>
</record>

<record>
  <contributors>
    <authors>
      <author>Merritt, David</author>
      <author>Milosavljevic, Milos</author>
    </authors>
  </contributors>
  <titles>
    <title>Massive black hole binary evolution</title>
    <secondary-title>Living Rev.Rel.</secondary-title>
  </titles>
  <electronic-resource-num>10.12942/lrr-2005-8</electronic-resource-num>
  <pages>8</pages>
  <volume>8</volume>
  <number/>
  <dates>
    <year>2005</year>
  </dates>
  <abstract>Coalescence of binary supermassive black holes (SBHs) would constitute the strongest sources of gravitational waves to be observed by LISA. While the formation of binary SBHs during galaxy mergers is almost inevitable, coalescence requires that the separation between binary components first drop by a few orders of magnitude, due presumably to interaction of the binary with stars and gas in a galactic nucleus. This article reviews the observational evidence for binary SBHs and discusses how they would evolve. No completely convincing case of a bound, binary SBH has yet been found, although a handful of systems (e.g. interacting galaxies: remnants of galaxy mergers) are now believed to contain two SBHs at projected separations of roughly one kpc. N-body studies of binary evolution in gas-free galaxies have reached large enough particle numbers to reproduce the slow, diffusive refilling of the binary's loss cone that is believed to characterize binary evolution in real galactic nuclei. While some of the results of these simulations -- e.g. the binary hardening rate and eccentricity evolution -- are strongly $N$-dependent, others -- e.g. the damage inflicted by the binary on the nucleus -- are not. Luminous early-type galaxies often exhibit depleted cores with masses of 1-2 times the mass of their nuclear SBHs, consistent with the predictions of the binary model. Studies of the interaction of massive binaries with gas are still in their infancy, although much progress is expected in the near future. Binary coalescence has a large influence on the spins of SBHs, even for mass ratios as extreme as 10:1, and evidence of spin-flips may have been observed.</abstract>
</record>

<record>
  <contributors>
    <authors>
      <author>Carlip, Steven</author>
    </authors>
  </contributors>
  <titles>
    <title>Quantum gravity in 2+1 dimensions: The Case of a closed universe</title>
    <secondary-title>Living Rev.Rel.</secondary-title>
  </titles>
  <electronic-resource-num>10.12942/lrr-2005-1</electronic-resource-num>
  <pages>1</pages>
  <volume>8</volume>
  <number/>
  <dates>
    <year>2005</year>
  </dates>
  <abstract>In three spacetime dimensions, general relativity drastically simplifies, becoming a ``topological'' theory with no propagating local degrees of freedom. Nevertheless, many of the difficult conceptual problems of quantizing gravity are still present. In this review, I summarize the rather large body of work that has gone towards quantizing (2+1)-dimensional vacuum gravity in the setting of a spatially closed universe.</abstract>
</record>

<record>
  <contributors>
    <authors>
      <author>Tinto, Massimo</author>
      <author>Dhurandhar, Sanjeev V.</author>
    </authors>
  </contributors>
  <titles>
    <title>Time-delay interferometry</title>
    <secondary-title>Living Rev.Rel.</secondary-title>
  </titles>
  <electronic-resource-num>10.12942/lrr-2005-4</electronic-resource-num>
  <pages>4</pages>
  <volume>8</volume>
  <number/>
  <dates>
    <year>2005</year>
  </dates>
  <abstract>Equal-arm interferometric detectors of gravitational radiation allow phase measurements many orders of magnitude below the intrinsic phase stability of the laser injecting light into their arms. This is because the noise in the laser light is common to both arms, experiencing exactly the same delay, and thus cancels when it is differenced at the photo detector. In this situation, much lower level secondary noises then set overall performance. If, however, the two arms have different lengths (as will necessarily be the case with space-borne interferometers), the laser noise experiences different delays in the two arms and will hence not directly cancel at the detector. In order to solve this problem, a technique involving heterodyne interferometry with unequal arm lengths and independent phase-difference readouts has been proposed. It relies on properly time-shifting and linearly combining independent Doppler measurements, and for this reason it has been called Time-Delay Interferometry (or TDI). This article provides an overview of the theory and mathematical foundations of TDI as it will be implemented by the forthcoming space-based interferometers such as the Laser Interferometer Space Antenna (LISA) mission. We have purposely left out from this first version of our ``Living Review'' article on TDI all the results of more practical and experimental nature, as well as all the aspects of TDI that the data analysts will need to account for when analyzing the LISA TDI data combinations. Our forthcoming ``second edition'' of this review paper will include these topics.</abstract>
</record>

<record>
  <contributors>
    <authors>
      <author>Perlick, V.</author>
    </authors>
  </contributors>
  <titles>
    <title>Gravitational lensing from a spacetime perspective</title>
    <secondary-title>Living Rev.Rel.</secondary-title>
  </titles>
  <electronic-resource-num/>
  <pages>9</pages>
  <volume>7</volume>
  <number/>
  <dates>
    <year>2004</year>
  </dates>
  <abstract/>
</record>

<record>
  <contributors>
    <authors>
      <author>Szabados, Laszlo B.</author>
    </authors>
  </contributors>
  <titles>
    <title>Quasi-Local Energy-Momentum and Angular Momentum in GR: A Review Article</title>
    <secondary-title>Living Rev.Rel.</secondary-title>
  </titles>
  <electronic-resource-num>10.12942/lrr-2004-4</electronic-resource-num>
  <pages>4</pages>
  <volume>7</volume>
  <number/>
  <dates>
    <year>2004</year>
  </dates>
  <abstract>The present status of the quasi-local mass-energy-momentum and angular momentum constructions in general relativity is reviewed. First the general ideas, concepts, and strategies, as well as the necessary tools to construct and analyze the quasi-local quantities are recalled. Then the various specific constructions and their properties (both successes and defects) are discussed. Finally, some of the (actual and potential) applications of the quasi-local concepts and specific constructions are briefly mentioned.</abstract>
</record>

<record>
  <contributors>
    <authors>
      <author>Ashtekar, Abhay</author>
      <author>Krishnan, Badri</author>
    </authors>
  </contributors>
  <titles>
    <title>Isolated and dynamical horizons and their applications</title>
    <secondary-title>Living Rev.Rel.</secondary-title>
  </titles>
  <electronic-resource-num>10.12942/lrr-2004-10</electronic-resource-num>
  <pages>10</pages>
  <volume>7</volume>
  <number/>
  <dates>
    <year>2004</year>
  </dates>
  <abstract>Over the past three decades, black holes have played an important role in quantum gravity, mathematical physics, numerical relativity and gravitational wave phenomenology. However, conceptual settings and mathematical models used to discuss them have varied considerably from one area to another. Over the last five years a new, quasi-local framework was introduced to analyze diverse facets of black holes in a unified manner. In this framework, evolving black holes are modeled by dynamical horizons and black holes in equilibrium by isolated horizons. We review basic properties of these horizons and summarize applications to mathematical physics, numerical relativity and quantum gravity. This paradigm has led to significant generalizations of several results in black hole physics. Specifically, it has introduced a more physical setting for black hole thermodynamics and for black hole entropy calculations in quantum gravity; suggested a phenomenological model for hairy black holes; provided novel techniques to extract physics from numerical simulations; and led to new laws governing the dynamics of black holes in exact general relativity.</abstract>
</record>

<record>
  <contributors>
    <authors>
      <author>Goenner, H.F.M.</author>
    </authors>
  </contributors>
  <titles>
    <title>On the history of unified field theories</title>
    <secondary-title>Living Rev.Rel.</secondary-title>
  </titles>
  <electronic-resource-num/>
  <pages>2</pages>
  <volume>7</volume>
  <number/>
  <dates>
    <year>2004</year>
  </dates>
  <abstract/>
</record>

<record>
  <contributors>
    <authors>
      <author>Maartens, Roy</author>
    </authors>
  </contributors>
  <titles>
    <title>Brane world gravity</title>
    <secondary-title>Living Rev.Rel.</secondary-title>
  </titles>
  <electronic-resource-num>10.12942/lrr-2004-7</electronic-resource-num>
  <pages>7</pages>
  <volume>7</volume>
  <number/>
  <dates>
    <year>2004</year>
  </dates>
  <abstract>The observable universe could be a 1+3-surface (the "brane") embedded in a 1+3+d-dimensional spacetime (the "bulk"), with standard-model particles and fields trapped on the brane while gravity is free to access the bulk. At least one of the d extra spatial dimensions could be very large relative to the Planck scale, which lowers the fundamental gravity scale, possibly even down to the electroweak (~ TeV) level. This revolutionary picture arises in the framework of recent developments in M theory. The 1+10-dimensional M theory encompasses the known 1+9-dimensional superstring theories, and is widely considered to be a promising potential route to quantum gravity. General relativity cannot describe gravity at high enough energies and must be replaced by a quantum gravity theory, picking up significant corrections as the fundamental energy scale is approached. At low energies, gravity is localized at the brane and general relativity is recovered, but at high energies gravity "leaks" into the bulk, behaving in a truly 1+3+d-dimensional way. This introduces significant changes to gravitational dynamics and perturbations, with interesting testable implications for high-energy astrophysics, black holes and cosmology. Brane-world models offer a phenomenological way to test some of the novel predictions and corrections to general relativity that are implied by M theory. This review discusses the geometry, dynamics and perturbations of simple brane-world models for cosmology and astrophysics, mainly focusing on warped 5-dimensional brane-worlds based on the Randall-Sundrum models.</abstract>
</record>

<record>
  <contributors>
    <authors>
      <author>Burgess, C.P.</author>
    </authors>
  </contributors>
  <titles>
    <title>Quantum gravity in everyday life: General relativity as an effective field theory</title>
    <secondary-title>Living Rev.Rel.</secondary-title>
  </titles>
  <electronic-resource-num>10.12942/lrr-2004-5</electronic-resource-num>
  <pages>5-56</pages>
  <volume>7</volume>
  <number/>
  <dates>
    <year>2004</year>
  </dates>
  <abstract>This article is meant as a summary and introduction to the ideas of effective field theory as applied to gravitational systems. Contents: 1. Introduction 2. Effective Field Theories 3. Low-Energy Quantum Gravity 4. Explicit Quantum Calculations 5. Conclusions</abstract>
</record>

<record>
  <contributors>
    <authors>
      <author>Lahav, Ofer</author>
      <author>Suto, Yasushi</author>
    </authors>
  </contributors>
  <titles>
    <title>Measuring our universe from galaxy redshift surveys</title>
    <secondary-title>Living Rev.Rel.</secondary-title>
  </titles>
  <electronic-resource-num>10.12942/lrr-2004-8</electronic-resource-num>
  <pages>8</pages>
  <volume>7</volume>
  <number/>
  <dates>
    <year>2004</year>
  </dates>
  <abstract>Galaxy redshift surveys have achieved significant progress over the last couple of decades. Those surveys tell us in the most straightforward way what our local universe looks like. While the galaxy distribution traces the bright side of the universe, detailed quantitative analyses of the data have even revealed the dark side of the universe dominated by non-baryonic dark matter as well as more mysterious dark energy (or Einstein's cosmological constant). We describe several methodologies of using galaxy redshift surveys as cosmological probes, and then summarize the recent results from the existing surveys. Finally we present our views on the future of redshift surveys in the era of Precision Cosmology.</abstract>
</record>

<record>
  <contributors>
    <authors>
      <author>Stairs, Ingrid H.</author>
    </authors>
  </contributors>
  <titles>
    <title>Testing general relativity with pulsar timing</title>
    <secondary-title>Living Rev.Rel.</secondary-title>
  </titles>
  <electronic-resource-num>10.12942/lrr-2003-5</electronic-resource-num>
  <pages>5</pages>
  <volume>6</volume>
  <number/>
  <dates>
    <year>2003</year>
  </dates>
  <abstract>Pulsars of very different types - isolated objects, and binaries with short- and long-period orbits, white-dwarf and neutron-star companions - provide the means to test both the predictions of general relativity and the viability of alternate theories of gravity. This article presents an overview of pulsars, then discusses the current status and future prospects of tests of equivalence principle violations and strong-field gravitational experiments.</abstract>
</record>

<record>
  <contributors>
    <authors>
      <author>Hu, B.L.</author>
      <author>Verdaguer, E.</author>
    </authors>
  </contributors>
  <titles>
    <title>Stochastic gravity: Theory and applications</title>
    <secondary-title>Living Rev.Rel.</secondary-title>
  </titles>
  <electronic-resource-num>10.12942/lrr-2004-3</electronic-resource-num>
  <pages>3</pages>
  <volume>7</volume>
  <number/>
  <dates>
    <year>2004</year>
  </dates>
  <abstract>Whereas semiclassical gravity is based on the semiclassical Einstein equation with sources given by the expectation value of the stress-energy tensor of quantum fields, stochastic semiclassical gravity is based on the Einstein-Langevin equation, which has in addition sources due to the noise kernel.In the first part, we describe the fundamentals of this new theory via two approaches: the axiomatic and the functional. In the second part, we describe three applications of stochastic gravity theory. First, we consider metric perturbations in a Minkowski spacetime: we compute the two-point correlation functions for the linearized Einstein tensor and for the metric perturbations. Second, we discuss structure formation from the stochastic gravity viewpoint. Third, we discuss the backreaction of Hawking radiation in the gravitational background of a quasi-static black hole.</abstract>
</record>

<record>
  <contributors>
    <authors>
      <author>Sasaki, Misao</author>
      <author>Tagoshi, Hideyuki</author>
    </authors>
  </contributors>
  <titles>
    <title>Analytic black hole perturbation approach to gravitational radiation</title>
    <secondary-title>Living Rev.Rel.</secondary-title>
  </titles>
  <electronic-resource-num>10.12942/lrr-2003-6</electronic-resource-num>
  <pages>6</pages>
  <volume>6</volume>
  <number/>
  <dates>
    <year>2003</year>
  </dates>
  <abstract>We review analytic methods to perform the post-Newtonian expansion of gravitational waves induced by a particle orbiting a massive compact body, based on the black hole perturbation theory. There exist two different methods of the post-Newtonian expansion. Both are based the Teukolsky equation. In one method, the Teukolsky equation is transformed into a Regge-Wheeler type equation that reduces to the standard Klein-Gordon equation in the flat space limit, while in the other method, which were introduced by Mano, Suzuki and Takasugi relatively recently, the Teukolsky equation is directly used in its original form. The former has an advantage that it is intuitively easy to understand how various curved space effects come into play. However, it becomes increasingly complicated when one goes on to higher and higher post-Newtonian orders. In contrast, the latter has an advantage that a systematic calculation to higher post-Newtonian orders is relatively easily implementable, but otherwise so mathematical that it is hard to understand the interplay of higher order terms. In this paper, we review both methods so that their pros and cons may be clearly seen. We also review some results of calculations of gravitational radiation emitted by a particle orbiting a black hole.</abstract>
</record>

<record>
  <contributors>
    <authors>
      <author>Poisson, Eric</author>
    </authors>
  </contributors>
  <titles>
    <title>The Motion of point particles in curved space-time</title>
    <secondary-title>Living Rev.Rel.</secondary-title>
  </titles>
  <electronic-resource-num>10.12942/lrr-2004-6</electronic-resource-num>
  <pages>6</pages>
  <volume>7</volume>
  <number/>
  <dates>
    <year>2004</year>
  </dates>
  <abstract>This review is concerned with the motion of a point scalar charge, a point electric charge, and a point mass in a specified background spacetime. In each of the three cases the particle produces a field that behaves as outgoing radiation in the wave zone, and therefore removes energy from the particle. In the near zone the field acts on the particle and gives rise to a self-force that prevents the particle from moving on a geodesic of the background spacetime. The field's action on the particle is difficult to calculate because of its singular nature: the field diverges at the position of the particle. But it is possible to isolate the field's singular part and show that it exerts no force on the particle -- its only effect is to contribute to the particle's inertia. What remains after subtraction is a smooth field that is fully responsible for the self-force. Because this field satisfies a homogeneous wave equation, it can be thought of as a free (radiative) field that interacts with the particle; it is this interaction that gives rise to the self-force. The mathematical tools required to derive the equations of motion of a point scalar charge, a point electric charge, and a point mass in a specified background spacetime are developed here from scratch. The review begins with a discussion of the basic theory of bitensors (part I). It then applies the theory to the construction of convenient coordinate systems to chart a neighbourhood of the particle's word line (part II). It continues with a thorough discussion of Green's functions in curved spacetime (part III). The review concludes with a detailed derivation of each of the three equations of motion (part IV).</abstract>
</record>

<record>
  <contributors>
    <authors>
      <author>Stergioulas, Nikolaos</author>
    </authors>
  </contributors>
  <titles>
    <title>Rotating Stars in Relativity</title>
    <secondary-title>Living Rev.Rel.</secondary-title>
  </titles>
  <electronic-resource-num>10.12942/lrr-2003-3</electronic-resource-num>
  <pages>3</pages>
  <volume>6</volume>
  <number/>
  <dates>
    <year>2003</year>
  </dates>
  <abstract>Rotating relativistic stars have been studied extensively in recent years, both theoretically and observationally, because of the information one could obtain about the equation of state of matter at extremely high densities and because they are considered to be promising sources of gravitational waves. The latest theoretical understanding of rotating stars in relativity is reviewed in this updated article. The sections on the equilibrium properties and on the nonaxisymmetric instabilities in f-modes and r-modes have been updated and several new sections have been added on analytic solutions for the exterior spacetime, rotating stars in LMXBs, rotating strange stars, and on rotating stars in numerical relativity.</abstract>
</record>

<record>
  <contributors>
    <authors>
      <author>Rendall, Alan D.</author>
    </authors>
  </contributors>
  <titles>
    <title>Theorems on existence and global dynamics for the Einstein equations</title>
    <secondary-title>Living Rev.Rel.</secondary-title>
  </titles>
  <electronic-resource-num>10.12942/lrr-2005-6</electronic-resource-num>
  <pages>6</pages>
  <volume>8</volume>
  <number/>
  <dates>
    <year>2002</year>
  </dates>
  <abstract>This article is a guide to theorems on existence and global dynamics of solutions of the Einstein equations. It draws attention to open questions in the field. The local-in-time Cauchy problem, which is relatively well understood, is surveyed. Global results for solutions with various types of symmetry are discussed. A selection of results from Newtonian theory and special relativity that offer useful comparisons is presented. Treatments of global results in the case of small data and results on constructing spacetimes with prescribed singularity structure or late-time asymptotics are given. A conjectural picture of the asymptotic behaviour of general cosmological solutions of the Einstein equations is built up. Some miscellaneous topics connected with the main theme are collected in a separate section.</abstract>
</record>

<record>
  <contributors>
    <authors>
      <author>Sumner, T.J.</author>
    </authors>
  </contributors>
  <titles>
    <title>Experimental searches for dark matter</title>
    <secondary-title>Living Rev.Rel.</secondary-title>
  </titles>
  <electronic-resource-num/>
  <pages>4</pages>
  <volume>5</volume>
  <number/>
  <dates>
    <year>2002</year>
  </dates>
  <abstract/>
</record>

<record>
  <contributors>
    <authors>
      <author>Bern, Zvi</author>
    </authors>
  </contributors>
  <titles>
    <title>Perturbative quantum gravity and its relation to gauge theory</title>
    <secondary-title>Living Rev.Rel.</secondary-title>
  </titles>
  <electronic-resource-num>10.12942/lrr-2002-5</electronic-resource-num>
  <pages>5</pages>
  <volume>5</volume>
  <number/>
  <dates>
    <year>2002</year>
  </dates>
  <abstract>In this review we describe a non-trivial relationship between perturbative gauge theory and gravity scattering amplitudes. At the semi-classical or tree level, the scattering amplitudes of gravity theories in flat space can be expressed as a sum of products of well defined pieces of gauge theory amplitudes. These relationships were first discovered by Kawai, Lewellen and Tye in the context of string theory, but hold more generally. In particular, they hold for standard Einstein gravity. A method based on D-dimensional unitarity can then be used to systematically construct all quantum loop corrections order-by-order in perturbation theory using as input the gravity tree amplitudes expressed in terms of gauge theory ones. More generally, the unitarity method provides a means for perturbatively quantizing massless gravity theories without the usual formal apparatus associated with the quantization of constrained systems. As one application, this method was used to demonstrate that maximally supersymmetric gravity is less divergent in the ultraviolet than previously thought.</abstract>
</record>

<record>
  <contributors>
    <authors>
      <author>Andreasson, Hakan</author>
    </authors>
  </contributors>
  <titles>
    <title>The Einstein-Vlasov System/Kinetic Theory</title>
    <secondary-title>Living Rev.Rel.</secondary-title>
  </titles>
  <electronic-resource-num>10.12942/lrr-2002-7</electronic-resource-num>
  <pages>7</pages>
  <volume>5</volume>
  <number/>
  <dates>
    <year>2002</year>
  </dates>
  <abstract>The main purpose of this article is to guide the reader to theorems on global properties of solutions to the Einstein-Vlasov system. This system couples Einstein's equations to a kinetic matter model. Kinetic theory has been an important field of research during several decades where the main focus has been on nonrelativistic- and special relativistic physics, e.g. to model the dynamics of neutral gases, plasmas and Newtonian self-gravitating systems. In 1990 Rendall and Rein initiated a mathematical study of the Einstein-Vlasov system. Since then many theorems on global properties of solutions to this system have been established. The Vlasov equation describes matter phenomenologically and it should be stressed that most of the theorems presented in this article are not presently known for other such matter models (e.g. fluid models). The first part of this paper gives an introduction to kinetic theory in non-curved spacetimes and then the Einstein-Vlasov system is introduced. We believe that a good understanding of kinetic theory in non-curved spacetimes is fundamental in order to get a good comprehension of kinetic theory in general relativity.</abstract>
</record>

<record>
  <contributors>
    <authors>
      <author>New, Kimberly C.B.</author>
    </authors>
  </contributors>
  <titles>
    <title>Gravitational waves from gravitational collapse</title>
    <secondary-title>Living Rev.Rel.</secondary-title>
  </titles>
  <electronic-resource-num>10.12942/lrr-2003-2</electronic-resource-num>
  <pages>2</pages>
  <volume>6</volume>
  <number/>
  <dates>
    <year>2003</year>
  </dates>
  <abstract>Gravitational wave emission from the gravitational collapse of massive stars has been studied for more than three decades. Current state of the art numerical investigations of collapse include those that use progenitors with realistic angular momentum profiles, properly treat microphysics issues, account for general relativity, and examine non--axisymmetric effects in three dimensions. Such simulations predict that gravitational waves from various phenomena associated with gravitational collapse could be detectable with advanced ground--based and future space--based interferometric observatories.</abstract>
</record>

<record>
  <contributors>
    <authors>
      <author>Rendall, Alan D.</author>
    </authors>
  </contributors>
  <titles>
    <title>Theorems on existence and global dynamics for the Einstein equations</title>
    <secondary-title>Living Rev.Rel.</secondary-title>
  </titles>
  <electronic-resource-num/>
  <pages>6</pages>
  <volume>5</volume>
  <number/>
  <dates>
    <year>2002</year>
  </dates>
  <abstract>This article is a guide to theorems on existence and global dynamics of solutions of the Einstein equations. It draws attention to open questions in the field. The local in time Cauchy problem, which is relatively well understood, is surveyed. Global results for solutions with various types of symmetry are discussed. A selection of results from Newtonian theory and special relativity which offer useful comparisons is presented. Treatments of global results in the case of small data and results on constructing spacetimes with prescribed singularity structure are given. A conjectural picture of the asymptotic behaviour of general cosmological solutions of the Einstein equations is built up. Some miscellaneous topics connected with the main theme are collected in a separate section.</abstract>
</record>

<record>
  <contributors>
    <authors>
      <author>Blanchet, Luc</author>
    </authors>
  </contributors>
  <titles>
    <title>Gravitational radiation from postNewtonian sources and inspiraling compact binaries</title>
    <secondary-title>Living Rev.Rel.</secondary-title>
  </titles>
  <electronic-resource-num>10.12942/lrr-2002-3</electronic-resource-num>
  <pages>3</pages>
  <volume>5</volume>
  <number/>
  <dates>
    <year>2002</year>
  </dates>
  <abstract>The article reviews the current status of a theoretical approach to the problem of the emission of gravitational waves by isolated systems in the context of general relativity. Part A of the article deals with general post-Newtonian sources. The exterior field of the source is investigated by means of a combination of analytic post-Minkowskian and multipolar approximations. The physical observables in the far-zone of the source are described by a specific set of radiative multipole moments. By matching the exterior solution to the metric of the post-Newtonian source in the near-zone we obtain the explicit expressions of the source multipole moments. The relationships between the radiative and source moments involve many non-linear multipole interactions, among them those associated with the tails (and tails-of-tails) of gravitational waves. Part B of the article is devoted to the application to compact binary systems. We present the equations of binary motion, and the associated Lagrangian and Hamiltonian, at the third post-Newtonian (3PN) order beyond the Newtonian acceleration. The gravitational-wave energy flux, taking consistently into account the relativistic corrections in the binary moments as well as the various tail effects, is derived through 3.5PN order with respect to the quadrupole formalism. The binary's orbital phase, whose prior knowledge is crucial for searching and analyzing the signals from inspiralling compact binaries, is deduced from an energy balance argument.</abstract>
</record>

<record>
  <contributors>
    <authors>
      <author>Benacquista, Matthew J.</author>
    </authors>
  </contributors>
  <titles>
    <title>Relativistic binaries in globular clusters</title>
    <secondary-title>Living Rev.Rel.</secondary-title>
  </titles>
  <electronic-resource-num>10.12942/lrr-2002-2</electronic-resource-num>
  <pages>2</pages>
  <volume>5</volume>
  <number/>
  <dates>
    <year>2002</year>
  </dates>
  <abstract>The galactic population of globular clusters are old, dense star systems, with a typical cluster containing $10^4 - 10^6$ stars. As an old population of stars, globular clusters contain many collapsed and degenerate objects. As a dense population of stars, globular clusters are the scene of many interesting close dynamical interactions between stars. These dynamical interactions can alter the evolution of individual stars and can produce tight binary systems containing one or two compact objects. In this review, we discuss the theoretical models of globular cluster evolution and binary evolution, techniques for simulating this evolution which lead to relativistic binaries, and current and possible future observational evidence for this population. Globular cluster evolution will focus on the properties that boost the production of hard binary systems and on the tidal interactions of the galaxy with the cluster, which tend to alter the structure of the globular cluster with time. The interaction of the components of hard binary systems alters the evolution of both bodies and can lead to exotic objects. Direct $N$-body integrations and Fokker-Planck simulations of the evolution of globular clusters that incorporate tidal interactions and lead to predictions of relativistic binary populations are also discussed. We discuss the current observational evidence for cataclysmic variables, millisecond pulsars, and low-mass X-ray binaries as well as possible future detection of relativistic binaries with gravitational radiation.</abstract>
</record>

<record>
  <contributors>
    <authors>
      <author>Berger, Beverly K.</author>
    </authors>
  </contributors>
  <titles>
    <title>Numerical approaches to space-time singularities</title>
    <secondary-title>Living Rev.Rel.</secondary-title>
  </titles>
  <electronic-resource-num>10.12942/lrr-2002-1</electronic-resource-num>
  <pages>1</pages>
  <volume>5</volume>
  <number/>
  <dates>
    <year>2002</year>
  </dates>
  <abstract>This Living Review updates a previous version which its itself an update of a review article. Numerical exploration of the properties of singularities could, in principle, yield detailed understanding of their nature in physically realistic cases. Examples of numerical investigations into the formation of naked singularities, critical behavior in collapse, passage through the Cauchy horizon, chaos of the Mixmaster singularity, and singularities in spatially inhomogeneous cosmologies are discussed.</abstract>
</record>

<record>
  <contributors>
    <authors>
      <author>Lorimer, D.R.</author>
    </authors>
  </contributors>
  <titles>
    <title>Binary and millisecond pulsars at the new millennium</title>
    <secondary-title>Living Rev.Rel.</secondary-title>
  </titles>
  <electronic-resource-num/>
  <pages>5</pages>
  <volume>4</volume>
  <number/>
  <dates>
    <year>2001</year>
  </dates>
  <abstract>We review the properties and applications of binary and millisecond pulsars. Our knowledge of these exciting objects has greatly increased in recent years, mainly due to successful surveys which have brought the known pulsar population to over 1300. There are now 56 binary and millisecond pulsars in the Galactic disk and a further 47 in globular clusters. This review is concerned primarily with the results and spin-offs from these surveys which are of particular interest to the relativity community.</abstract>
</record>

<record>
  <contributors>
    <authors>
      <author>Anninos, Peter</author>
    </authors>
  </contributors>
  <titles>
    <title>Computational cosmology: From the early universe to the large scale structure</title>
    <secondary-title>Living Rev.Rel.</secondary-title>
  </titles>
  <electronic-resource-num>10.12942/lrr-2001-2</electronic-resource-num>
  <pages>2</pages>
  <volume>4</volume>
  <number/>
  <dates>
    <year>2001</year>
  </dates>
  <abstract>In order to account for the observable Universe, any comprehensive theory or model of cosmology must draw from many disciplines of physics, including gauge theories of strong and weak interactions, the hydrodynamics and microphysics of baryonic matter, electromagnetic fields, and spacetime curvature, for example. Although it is difficult to incorporate all these physical elements into a single complete model of our Universe, advances in computing methods and technologies have contributed significantly towards our understanding of cosmological models, the Universe, and astrophysical processes within them. A sample of numerical calculations (and numerical methods) applied to specific issues in cosmology are reviewed in this article: from the Big Bang singularity dynamics to the fundamental interactions of gravitational waves; from the quark-hadron phase transition to the large scale structure of the Universe. The emphasis, although not exclusively, is on those calculations designed to test different models of cosmology against the observed Universe.</abstract>
</record>

<record>
  <contributors>
    <authors>
      <author>Will, Clifford M.</author>
    </authors>
  </contributors>
  <titles>
    <title>The Confrontation between general relativity and experiment</title>
    <secondary-title>Living Rev.Rel.</secondary-title>
  </titles>
  <electronic-resource-num>10.12942/lrr-2001-4</electronic-resource-num>
  <pages>4</pages>
  <volume>4</volume>
  <number/>
  <dates>
    <year>2001</year>
  </dates>
  <abstract>The status of experimental tests of general relativity and of theoretical frameworks for analysing them are reviewed. Einstein's equivalence principle (EEP) is well supported by experiments such as the E\"otv\"os experiment, tests of special relativity, and the gravitational redshift experiment. Future tests of EEP and of the inverse square law will search for new interactions arising from unification or quantum gravity. Tests of general relativity at the post-Newtonian level have reached high precision, including the light deflection, the Shapiro time delay, the perihelion advance of Mercury, and the Nordtvedt effect in lunar motion. Gravitational wave damping has been detected to half a percent using the binary pulsar, and new binary pulsar systems may yield further improvements. When direct observation of gravitational radiation from astrophysical sources begins, new tests of general relativity will be possible.</abstract>
</record>

<record>
  <contributors>
    <authors>
      <author>Winicour, Jeffrey</author>
    </authors>
  </contributors>
  <titles>
    <title>Characteristic evolution and matching</title>
    <secondary-title>Living Rev.Rel.</secondary-title>
  </titles>
  <electronic-resource-num>10.12942/lrr-2001-3</electronic-resource-num>
  <pages>3</pages>
  <volume>4</volume>
  <number/>
  <keywords>
    <keyword>Numerical relativity</keyword>
    <keyword>Characteristic initial value problem</keyword>
    <keyword>Numerical methods</keyword>
  </keywords>
  <dates>
    <year>2001</year>
  </dates>
  <abstract>I review the development of numerical evolution codes for general relativity based upon the characteristic initial value problem. Progress is traced from the early stage of 1D feasibility studies to current 3D black codes that simulate binary black holes. A prime application of characteristic evolution is Cauchy-characteristic matching, which is also reviewed.</abstract>
</record>

<record>
  <contributors>
    <authors>
      <author>Frauendiener, Jorg</author>
    </authors>
  </contributors>
  <titles>
    <title>Conformal infinity</title>
    <secondary-title>Living Rev.Rel.</secondary-title>
  </titles>
  <electronic-resource-num/>
  <pages>4</pages>
  <volume>3</volume>
  <number/>
  <dates>
    <year>2000</year>
  </dates>
  <abstract/>
</record>

<record>
  <contributors>
    <authors>
      <author>Rowan, Sheila</author>
      <author>Hough, Jim</author>
    </authors>
  </contributors>
  <titles>
    <title>Gravitational wave detection by interferometry (ground and space)</title>
    <secondary-title>Living Rev.Rel.</secondary-title>
  </titles>
  <electronic-resource-num/>
  <pages>3</pages>
  <volume>3</volume>
  <number/>
  <dates>
    <year>2000</year>
  </dates>
  <abstract/>
</record>

<record>
  <contributors>
    <authors>
      <author>Cook, Gregory B.</author>
    </authors>
  </contributors>
  <titles>
    <title>Initial data for numerical relativity</title>
    <secondary-title>Living Rev.Rel.</secondary-title>
  </titles>
  <electronic-resource-num>10.12942/lrr-2000-5</electronic-resource-num>
  <pages>5</pages>
  <volume>3</volume>
  <number/>
  <dates>
    <year>2000</year>
  </dates>
  <abstract>Initial data are the starting point for any numerical simulation. In the case of numerical relativity, Einstein's equations constrain our choices of these initial data. We will examine several of the formalisms used for specifying Cauchy initial data in the 3+1 decomposition of Einstein's equations. We will then explore how these formalisms have been used in constructing initial data for spacetimes containing black holes and neutron stars. In the topics discussed, emphasis is placed on those issues that are important for obtaining astrophysically realistic initial data for compact binary coalescence.</abstract>
</record>

<record>
  <contributors>
    <authors>
      <author>Carroll, Sean M.</author>
    </authors>
  </contributors>
  <titles>
    <title>The Cosmological constant</title>
    <secondary-title>Living Rev.Rel.</secondary-title>
  </titles>
  <electronic-resource-num>10.12942/lrr-2001-1</electronic-resource-num>
  <pages>1</pages>
  <volume>4</volume>
  <number/>
  <dates>
    <year>2001</year>
  </dates>
  <abstract>This is a review of the physics and cosmology of the cosmological constant. Focusing on recent developments, I present a pedagogical overview of cosmology in the presence of a cosmological constant, observational constraints on its magnitude, and the physics of a small (and potentially nonzero) vacuum energy.</abstract>
</record>

<record>
  <contributors>
    <authors>
      <author>Font, Jose A.</author>
    </authors>
  </contributors>
  <titles>
    <title>Numerical hydrodynamics in general relativity</title>
    <secondary-title>Living Rev.Rel.</secondary-title>
  </titles>
  <electronic-resource-num>10.12942/lrr-2000-2</electronic-resource-num>
  <pages>2</pages>
  <volume>3</volume>
  <number/>
  <dates>
    <year>2000</year>
  </dates>
  <abstract>The current status of numerical solutions for the equations of ideal general relativistic hydrodynamics is reviewed. With respect to an earlier version of the article the present update provides additional information on numerical schemes and extends the discussion of astrophysical simulations in general relativistic hydrodynamics. Different formulations of the equations are presented, with special mention of conservative and hyperbolic formulations well-adapted to advanced numerical methods. A large sample of available numerical schemes is discussed, paying particular attention to solution procedures based on schemes exploiting the characteristic structure of the equations through linearized Riemann solvers. A comprehensive summary of astrophysical simulations in strong gravitational fields is presented. These include gravitational collapse, accretion onto black holes and hydrodynamical evolutions of neutron stars. The material contained in these sections highlights the numerical challenges of various representative simulations. It also follows, to some extent, the chronological development of the field, concerning advances on the formulation of the gravitational field and hydrodynamic equations and the numerical methodology designed to solve them.</abstract>
</record>

<record>
  <contributors>
    <authors>
      <author>Rendall, Alan D.</author>
    </authors>
  </contributors>
  <titles>
    <title>Local and global existence theorems for the Einstein equations</title>
    <secondary-title>Living Rev.Rel.</secondary-title>
  </titles>
  <electronic-resource-num>10.12942/lrr-2000-1</electronic-resource-num>
  <pages>1</pages>
  <volume>3</volume>
  <number/>
  <dates>
    <year>2000</year>
  </dates>
  <abstract>This article is a guide to the literature on existence theorems for the Einstein equations which also draws attention to open problems in the field. The local in time Cauchy problem, which is relatively well understood, is treated first. Next global results for solutions with symmetry are discussed. A selection of results from Newtonian theory and special relativity which offer useful comparisons is presented. This is followed by a survey of global results in the case of small data and results on constructing spacetimes with given singularity structure. The article ends with some miscellaneous topics connected with the main theme.</abstract>
</record>

<record>
  <contributors>
    <authors>
      <author>Gundlach, Carsten</author>
    </authors>
  </contributors>
  <titles>
    <title>Critical phenomena in gravitational collapse</title>
    <secondary-title>Living Rev.Rel.</secondary-title>
  </titles>
  <electronic-resource-num/>
  <pages>4</pages>
  <volume>2</volume>
  <number/>
  <dates>
    <year>1999</year>
  </dates>
  <abstract>As first discovered by Choptuik, the black hole threshold in the space of initial data for general relativity shows both surprising structure and surprising simplicity. Universality, power-law scaling of the black hole mass, and scale echoing have given rise to the term ``critical phenomena''. They are explained by the existence of exact solutions which are attractors within the black hole threshold, that is, attractors of codimension one in phase space, and which are typically self-similar. This review gives an introduction to the phenomena, tries to summarize the essential features of what is happening, and then presents extensions and applications of this basic scenario. Critical phenomena are of interest particularly for creating surprising structure from simple equations, and for the light they throw on cosmic censorship and the generic dynamics of general relativity.</abstract>
</record>

<record>
  <contributors>
    <authors>
      <author>Wald, Robert M.</author>
    </authors>
  </contributors>
  <titles>
    <title>The thermodynamics of black holes</title>
    <secondary-title>Living Rev.Rel.</secondary-title>
  </titles>
  <electronic-resource-num>10.12942/lrr-2001-6</electronic-resource-num>
  <pages>6</pages>
  <volume>4</volume>
  <number/>
  <dates>
    <year>2001</year>
  </dates>
  <abstract>We review the present status of black hole thermodynamics. Our review includes discussion of classical black hole thermodynamics, Hawking radiation from black holes, the generalized second law, and the issue of entropy bounds. A brief survey also is given of approaches to the calculation of black hole entropy. We conclude with a discussion of some unresolved open issues.</abstract>
</record>

<record>
  <contributors>
    <authors>
      <author>Kokkotas, Kostas D.</author>
      <author>Schmidt, Bernd G.</author>
    </authors>
  </contributors>
  <titles>
    <title>Quasinormal modes of stars and black holes</title>
    <secondary-title>Living Rev.Rel.</secondary-title>
  </titles>
  <electronic-resource-num>10.12942/lrr-1999-2</electronic-resource-num>
  <pages>2</pages>
  <volume>2</volume>
  <number/>
  <dates>
    <year>1999</year>
  </dates>
  <abstract>Perturbations of stars and black holes have been one of the main topics of relativistic astrophysics for the last few decades. They are of particular importance today, because of their relevance to gravitational wave astronomy. In this review we present the theory of quasi-normal modes of compact objects from both the mathematical and astrophysical points of view. The discussion includes perturbations of black holes (Schwarzschild, Reissner-Nordstr\"om, Kerr and Kerr-Newman) and relativistic stars (non-rotating and slowly-rotating). The properties of the various families of quasi-normal modes are described, and numerical techniques for calculating quasi-normal modes reviewed. The successes, as well as the limits, of perturbation theory are presented, and its role in the emerging era of numerical relativity and supercomputers is discussed.</abstract>
</record>

<record>
  <contributors>
    <authors>
      <author>Marti, Jose M.</author>
      <author>Mueller, Ewald</author>
    </authors>
  </contributors>
  <titles>
    <title>Numerical hydrodynamics in special relativity</title>
    <secondary-title>Living Rev.Rel.</secondary-title>
  </titles>
  <electronic-resource-num/>
  <pages>3</pages>
  <volume>2</volume>
  <number/>
  <dates>
    <year>1999</year>
  </dates>
  <abstract>This review is concerned with a discussion of numerical methods for the solution of the equations of special relativistic hydrodynamics (SRHD). Particular emphasis is put on a comprehensive review of the application of high-resolution shock-capturing methods in SRHD. Results obtained with different numerical SRHD methods are compared, and two astrophysical applications of SRHD flows are discussed. An evaluation of the various numerical methods is given and future developments are analyzed.</abstract>
</record>

<record>
  <contributors>
    <authors>
      <author>Muller, Ingo</author>
    </authors>
  </contributors>
  <titles>
    <title>Speeds of propagation in classical and relativistic extended thermodynamics</title>
    <secondary-title>Living Rev.Rel.</secondary-title>
  </titles>
  <electronic-resource-num/>
  <pages>1</pages>
  <volume>2</volume>
  <number/>
  <dates>
    <year>1999</year>
  </dates>
  <abstract/>
</record>

<record>
  <contributors>
    <authors>
      <author>Loll, Renate</author>
    </authors>
  </contributors>
  <titles>
    <title>Discrete approaches to quantum gravity in four-dimensions</title>
    <secondary-title>Living Rev.Rel.</secondary-title>
  </titles>
  <electronic-resource-num>10.12942/lrr-1998-13</electronic-resource-num>
  <pages>13</pages>
  <volume>1</volume>
  <number/>
  <dates>
    <year>1998</year>
  </dates>
  <abstract>The construction of a consistent theory of quantum gravity is a problem in theoretical physics that has so far defied all attempts at resolution. One ansatz to try to obtain a non-trivial quantum theory proceeds via a discretization of space-time and the Einstein action. I review here three major areas of research: gauge-theoretic approaches, both in a path-integral and a Hamiltonian formulation, quantum Regge calculus, and the method of dynamical triangulations, confining attention to work that is strictly four-dimensional, strictly discrete, and strictly quantum in nature.</abstract>
</record>

<record>
  <contributors>
    <authors>
      <author>Stergioulas, Nikolaos</author>
    </authors>
  </contributors>
  <titles>
    <title>Rotating stars in relativity</title>
    <secondary-title>Living Rev.Rel.</secondary-title>
  </titles>
  <electronic-resource-num>10.12942/lrr-1998-8</electronic-resource-num>
  <pages>8</pages>
  <volume>1</volume>
  <number/>
  <dates>
    <year>1998</year>
  </dates>
  <abstract>Rotating relativistic stars are receiving significant attention in recent years, because of the information they can yield about the equation of state of matter at extremely high densities and because they are one of the more possible sources of detectable gravitational waves. We review the latest theoretical and numerical methods for modeling rotating relativistic stars, including stars with a strong magnetic field and hot proto-neutron stars. We also review nonaxisymmetric oscillations and instabilities in rotating stars and summarize the latest developments regarding the gravitational wave-driven (CFS) instability in both polar and axial quasi-normal modes.</abstract>
</record>

<record>
  <contributors>
    <authors>
      <author>Jones, A.W.</author>
      <author>Lasenby, A.N.</author>
    </authors>
  </contributors>
  <titles>
    <title>The Cosmic microwave background</title>
    <secondary-title>Living Rev.Rel.</secondary-title>
  </titles>
  <electronic-resource-num/>
  <pages>11</pages>
  <volume>1</volume>
  <number/>
  <dates>
    <year>1998</year>
  </dates>
  <abstract/>
</record>

<record>
  <contributors>
    <authors>
      <author>Wambsganss, Joachim</author>
    </authors>
  </contributors>
  <titles>
    <title>Gravitational lensing in astronomy</title>
    <secondary-title>Living Rev.Rel.</secondary-title>
  </titles>
  <electronic-resource-num>10.12942/lrr-1998-12</electronic-resource-num>
  <pages>12</pages>
  <volume>1</volume>
  <number/>
  <dates>
    <year>1998</year>
  </dates>
  <abstract>Deflection of light by gravity was predicted by General Relativity and observationaly confirmed in 1919. In the following decades various aspects of the gravitational lens effect were explored theoretically, among them the possibility of multiple or ring-like images of background sources, the use of lensing as a gravitational telescope on very faint and distant objects, and the possibility to determine Hubble's constant with lensing. Only relatively recently gravitational lensing became an observational science after the discovery of the first doubly imaged quasar in 1979. Today lensing is a booming part of astrophysics. In addition to multiply-imaged quasars, a number of other aspects of lensing have been discovered since, e.g. giant luminous arcs, quasar microlensing, Einstein rings, galactic microlensing events, arclets, or weak gravitational lensing. By now literally hundreds of individual gravitational lens phenomena are known. Although still in its childhood, lensing has established itself as a very useful astrophysical tool with some remarkable successes. It has contributed significant new results in areas as different as the cosmological distance scale, the large scale matter distribution in the universe, mass and mass distribution of galaxy clusters, physics of quasars, dark matter in galaxy halos, or galaxy structure.</abstract>
</record>

<record>
  <contributors>
    <authors>
      <author>Lorimer, D.R.</author>
    </authors>
  </contributors>
  <titles>
    <title>Binary and millisecond pulsars</title>
    <secondary-title>Living Rev.Rel.</secondary-title>
  </titles>
  <electronic-resource-num/>
  <pages>10</pages>
  <volume>1</volume>
  <number/>
  <dates>
    <year>1998</year>
  </dates>
  <abstract/>
</record>

<record>
  <contributors>
    <authors>
      <author>Anninos, Peter</author>
    </authors>
  </contributors>
  <titles>
    <title>Computational cosmology: From the early universe to the large scale structure</title>
    <secondary-title>Living Rev.Rel.</secondary-title>
  </titles>
  <electronic-resource-num/>
  <pages>9</pages>
  <volume>1</volume>
  <number/>
  <dates>
    <year>1998</year>
  </dates>
  <abstract/>
</record>

<record>
  <contributors>
    <authors>
      <author>Berger, Beverly K.</author>
    </authors>
  </contributors>
  <titles>
    <title>Numerical approaches to space-time singularities</title>
    <secondary-title>Living Rev.Rel.</secondary-title>
  </titles>
  <electronic-resource-num/>
  <pages>7</pages>
  <volume>1</volume>
  <number/>
  <dates>
    <year>1998</year>
  </dates>
  <abstract/>
</record>

<record>
  <contributors>
    <authors>
      <author>Heusler, Markus</author>
    </authors>
  </contributors>
  <titles>
    <title>Stationary black holes: Uniqueness and beyond</title>
    <secondary-title>Living Rev.Rel.</secondary-title>
  </titles>
  <electronic-resource-num/>
  <pages>6</pages>
  <volume>1</volume>
  <number/>
  <dates>
    <year>1998</year>
  </dates>
  <abstract/>
</record>

<record>
  <contributors>
    <authors>
      <author>Reula, Oscar A.</author>
    </authors>
  </contributors>
  <titles>
    <title>Hyperbolic methods for Einstein's equations</title>
    <secondary-title>Living Rev.Rel.</secondary-title>
  </titles>
  <electronic-resource-num/>
  <pages>3</pages>
  <volume>1</volume>
  <number/>
  <dates>
    <year>1998</year>
  </dates>
  <abstract/>
</record>

<record>
  <contributors>
    <authors>
      <author>Rovelli, Carlo</author>
    </authors>
  </contributors>
  <titles>
    <title>Loop quantum gravity</title>
    <secondary-title>Living Rev.Rel.</secondary-title>
  </titles>
  <electronic-resource-num>10.12942/lrr-1998-1</electronic-resource-num>
  <pages>1</pages>
  <volume>1</volume>
  <number/>
  <dates>
    <year>1998</year>
  </dates>
  <abstract>The problem of finding the quantum theory of the gravitational field, and thus understanding what is quantum spacetime, is still open. One of the most active of the current approaches is loop quantum gravity. Loop quantum gravity is a mathematically well-defined, non-perturbative and background independent quantization of general relativity, with its conventional matter couplings. The research in loop quantum gravity forms today a vast area, ranging from mathematical foundations to physical applications. Among the most significative results obtained are: (i) The computation of the physical spectra of geometrical quantities such as area and volume; which yields quantitative predictions on Planck-scale physics. (ii) A derivation of the Bekenstein-Hawking black hole entropy formula. (iii) An intriguing physical picture of the microstructure of quantum physical space, characterized by a polymer-like Planck scale discreteness. This discreteness emerges naturally from the quantum theory and provides a mathematically well-defined realization of Wheeler's intuition of a spacetime ``foam''. Long standing open problems within the approach (lack of a scalar product, overcompleteness of the loop basis, implementation of reality conditions) have been fully solved. The weak part of the approach is the treatment of the dynamics: at present there exist several proposals, which are intensely debated. Here, I provide a general overview of ideas, techniques, results and open problems of this candidate theory of quantum gravity, and a guide to the relevant literature.</abstract>
</record>

</records>
</xml>